<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Whitfield-etal-2017-Assessing">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Assessing the quality of the streamflow record for a long-term reference hydrometric station: Bow River at Banff</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">P</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Whitfield</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">J</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Pomeroy</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2017</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Global Water Futures 2017</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
            <place>
                <placeTerm type="text">Online</placeTerm>
            </place>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">conference publication</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>The operational history of one of Canada’s longest operating hydrometric stations is reviewed in detail, including flood estimates that precede formal hydrometric monitoring. The assessment inspects the early and operational history, the published streamflow record and the stage-discharge measurements collected since 1909. Methods used to estimate pre-operational high flows and the operational history are reviewed to establish potential issues with changes in technology, location and measurement sections. The streamflow record is screened for discontinuities and change. The stage-discharge measurements used to establish the rating curve for open-water and ice-covered periods are assessed and used to establish the degree of support for the published data over the period of record. In the period 1882 to 1909, occasional high-stage estimates were used to estimate peak discharge, but with considerable uncertainty due to lack of stream velocity measurements and bed profiles. For the period 1909–1914 it is difficult to confirm the validity of the data as benchmarks and gauge corrections are unclear. Since 1922 when the station was established in its present location, many changes in the technology used for recording stage and measuring discharge have occurred. Rating curve support for high and low flows has varied over the period of record, particularly after cableway measurements of high flows were recently abandoned. Several important quality issues were identified that may require user caution, most notably an inconsistency with respect to the recording of winter ice-cover. These changes and issues have not affected the quality of the record in any substantial way. The stability of the flow control has remained remarkably consistent, resulting in high data quality for most of the period of record.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Whitfield-etal-2017-Assessing</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1080/07011784.2017.1399086</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/2017.GWF-1.46</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2017</date>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
