<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Thériault-etal-2018-Precipitation">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Precipitation characteristics and associated weather conditions on the eastern slopes of the Canadian Rockies during March–April 2015</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">J</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Thériault</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Ida</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Hung</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">P</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Vaquer</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">R</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Stewart</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">J</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Pomeroy</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2018</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Global Water Futures 2018</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
            <place>
                <placeTerm type="text">Online</placeTerm>
            </place>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">conference publication</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>Abstract. Precipitation events that bring rain and snow to theBanff–Calgary area of Alberta are a critical aspect of the region’s watercycle and can lead to major flooding events such as the June 2013 event thatwas the second most costly natural disaster in Canadian history. Because nospecial atmospheric-oriented observations of these events have been made, afield experiment was conducted in March and April 2015 in Kananaskis,Alberta, to begin to fill this gap. The goal was to characterize and betterunderstand the formation of the precipitation at the surface duringspring 2015 at a specific location in the Kananaskis Valley. Within theexperiment, detailed measurements of precipitation and weather conditionswere obtained, a vertically pointing Doppler radar was deployed and weatherballoons were released. Although 17 precipitation events occurred, thisperiod was associated with much less precipitation than normal (−35 %)and above-normal temperatures (2.5 ∘C). Of the 133 h of observedprecipitation, solid precipitation occurred 71 % of the time, mixedprecipitation occurred 9 % and rain occurred 20 %. An analysis of17 504 precipitation particles from 1181 images showed that a wide varietyof crystals and aggregates occurred and approximately 63 % showed signs ofriming. This was largely independent of whether flows aloft were upslope(easterly) or downslope (westerly). In the often sub-saturated surfaceconditions, hydrometeors containing ice occurred at temperatures as high as9 ∘C. Radar structures aloft were highly variable with reflectivitysometimes \textgreater30 dBZe and Doppler velocity up to −1 m s−1, whichindicates upward motion of particles within ascending air masses.Precipitation was formed in this region within cloud fields sometimes havingvariable structures and within which supercooled water at least sometimesexisted to produce accreted particles massive enough to reach the surfacethrough the relatively dry sub-cloud region.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Thériault-etal-2018-Precipitation</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.5194/HESS-22-4491-2018</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/2018.GWF-1.131</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2018</date>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
