<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Shatilla-etal-2019-Assessing">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Assessing inter-annual and seasonal patterns of DOC and DOM quality across a complex alpine watershed underlain by discontinuous permafrost in Yukon, Canada</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">N</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Shatilla</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">S</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Carey</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2019</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Global Water Futures 2019</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
            <place>
                <placeTerm type="text">Online</placeTerm>
            </place>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">conference publication</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>Abstract. High-latitude environments store approximately half of the globalorganic carbon pool in peatlands, organic soils and permafrost, while largeArctic rivers convey an estimated 18–50 Tg C a−1 to the Arctic Ocean.Warming trends associated with climate change affect dissolved organiccarbon (DOC) export from terrestrial to riverine environments. However,there is limited consensus as to whether exports will increase or decreasedue to complex interactions between climate, soils, vegetation, andassociated production, mobilization and transport processes. A large body ofresearch has focused on large river system DOC and dissolved organic matter (DOM) lability and observedtrends conserved across years, whereas investigation at smaller watershedscales show that thermokarst and fire have a transient impact onhydrologically mediated solute transport. This study, located in the WolfCreek Research Basin situated ∼20 km south of Whitehorse, YT,Canada, utilizes a nested design to assess seasonal and annual patterns ofDOC and DOM composition across diverse landscape types (headwater, wetland and lake) and watershed scales. Peak DOC concentration and export occurredduring freshet, as is the case in most northern watersheds; however, peaks were lower thana decade ago at the headwater site Granger Creek. DOM composition was mostvariable during freshet with high A254 and SUVA254 and low FI and BIX. DOMcomposition was relatively insensitive to flow variation during summer andfall. The influence of increasing watershed scale and downstream mixing oflandscape contributions was an overall dampening of DOC concentrations andoptical indices with increasing groundwater contribution. Forecastedvegetation shifts, enhanced permafrost and seasonal thaw, earlier snowmelt,increased rainfall and other projected climate-driven changes will alter DOMsources and transport pathways. The results from this study support a projected shift frompredominantly organic soils (high aromaticity and less fresh) to decomposingvegetation (more fresh and lower aromaticity). These changes may alsofacilitate flow and transport via deeper flow pathways and enhancegroundwater contributions to runoff.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Shatilla-etal-2019-Assessing</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.5194/HESS-23-3571-2019</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/2019.GWF-1.13</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2019</date>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
