<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>List of all posts on ACL Anthology</title><link>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-anthology/posts/</link><description>Recent content in List of all posts on ACL Anthology</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-anthology/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Help Shape the ACL Anthology!</title><link>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-anthology/posts/volunteer/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-anthology/posts/volunteer/</guid><description>The ACL Anthology is a treasure. It is the repository of our community&amp;rsquo;s scientific contributions extending back over fifty years; its engine is nicely designed custom in-house software that still works well after almost two decades; and it has enabled research projects examining topics like author networks and topic shift over time. That all of this labor has been donated by its members further distinguishes the Anthology: it is not a found treasure, but one that has been crafted and shaped over countless hours, as if by a hundred Berninis, holding keyboards instead of chisels.</description></item><item><title>Twenty More Years of Computational Linguistics</title><link>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-anthology/posts/reflections-aj/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-anthology/posts/reflections-aj/</guid><description>The title can be read in two ways. Either I should comment on the past twenty years of ACL (which coincide with the period between ACL 1982 held at Penn and ACL 2002 also held at Penn) or twenty more years from ACL 2002. As you will see many of my comments will be relevant to both these interpretations.
How did I get into computational linguistics (CL)? I did not really get into it.</description></item><item><title>ACL 1993—1994</title><link>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-anthology/posts/reflections-ksj/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-anthology/posts/reflections-ksj/</guid><description>As an organisation, the ACL has clearly evolved over the forty years since its foundation. (Whether, or how, it has evolved in its area of intellectual interest over the same period is a tricky and interesting question.) The ACL&amp;rsquo;s organisational development in the period up to Don Walker&amp;rsquo;s death in 1993 was, however, rather different from its evolution since. This was partly because the ACL&amp;rsquo;s community was not very large in its first two decades, partly because there were only three Secretary-Treasurers in the whole period from 1963 to 1993.</description></item></channel></rss>