<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>List of all posts on GWF Publications</title><link>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/posts/</link><description>Recent content in List of all posts on GWF Publications</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Help Shape the ACL Anthology!</title><link>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/posts/volunteer/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/posts/volunteer/</guid><description>&lt;p>The ACL Anthology is a treasure. It is the repository of our community&amp;rsquo;s
scientific contributions extending back over fifty years; its engine is nicely
designed custom in-house software that still works well after almost two
decades; and it has enabled research projects examining topics like author
networks and topic shift over time. That all of this labor has been donated by
its members further distinguishes the Anthology: it is not a found treasure, but
one that has been crafted and shaped over countless hours, as if by a hundred
Berninis, holding keyboards instead of chisels.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Twenty More Years of Computational Linguistics</title><link>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/posts/reflections-aj/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/posts/reflections-aj/</guid><description>&lt;p>The title can be read in two ways. Either I should comment on the past twenty
years of ACL (which coincide with the period between ACL 1982 held at Penn and
ACL 2002 also held at Penn) or twenty more years from ACL 2002. As you will see
many of my comments will be relevant to both these interpretations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How did I get into computational linguistics (CL)? I did not really get into
it. It sort of happened to me, much like Voltaire realizing one day that he was
indeed writing prose. This is simply due to the fact that I started doing what
is now called CL (or natural language processing) well before there was such a
recognized field or a professional society with that name. As a matter of fact
for the first couple of years of ACL (until about early 64) I did not officially
belong to ACL. This was not because I disliked something about ACL or the people
connected with it. Far from it. I knew the people very well and respected
them. In retrospect, I am sure part of my reason for not rushing into it was the
initial name of the current ACL. More importantly, I guess I was not sure myself
that what I was doing was the same as the proclaimed goals of the organization
at the start. I was also not sure that what I was doing at that time was either
part of linguistics or part of computer science, or combination of the two, and
perhaps, therefore, not needing any special name. Of course, once I joined ACL I
threw myself into it in every possible way. However, I believe my initial
experience described above may reflect in some way in my remarks below.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ACL 1993—1994</title><link>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/posts/reflections-ksj/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/posts/reflections-ksj/</guid><description>&lt;p>As an organisation, the ACL has clearly evolved over the forty years since its
foundation. (Whether, or how, it has evolved in its area of intellectual
interest over the same period is a tricky and interesting question.) The ACL&amp;rsquo;s
organisational development in the period up to Don Walker&amp;rsquo;s death in 1993 was,
however, rather different from its evolution since. This was partly because the
ACL&amp;rsquo;s community was not very large in its first two decades, partly because
there were only three Secretary-Treasurers in the whole period from 1963
to 1993. Don Walker&amp;rsquo;s term of office, from 1976-1993, was a particularly
important period in the development of the ACL, and both for these reasons and
because Don had been in post for so long, the two years 1993-1994 &amp;ndash; 1993 when
Don was ill and died, and 1994 when I was President &amp;ndash; were a rough transition
time.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>