<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G11"><volume id="1"><meta><booktitle>Environmental Chemistry and Toxicology of Mercury</booktitle><publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc.</publisher><address /><year>2011</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Bioaccumulation and Biomagnification of Mercury through Food Webs</title><author><first>Karen</first><last>Kidd</last></author><author><first>Meredith</first><last>Clayden</last></author><author><first>Tim</first><last>Jardine</last></author><abstract /><url hash="5c7dc95b">G11-1001</url><pages>453-499</pages><doi>10.1002/9781118146644.ch14</doi><bibkey>Kidd-2011-Bioaccumulation</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="2"><meta><booktitle>Journal of Physics: Conference Series, Volume 290</booktitle><publisher>IOP Publishing</publisher><address /><year>2011</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>International Conference on Inverse Problems 2010</title><author><first>Yiu-Chung</first><last>Hon</last></author><author><first>Leevan</first><last>Ling</last></author><abstract>Following the first International Conference on Inverse Problems – Recent Theoretical Development and Numerical Approaches held at the City University of Hong Kong in 2002, the fifth International Conference was held again at the City University during December 13–17, 2010. This fifth conference was jointly organized by Professor Yiu-Chung Hon (Co-Chair, City University of Hong Kong, HKSAR), Dr Leevan Ling (Co-Chair, Hong Kong Baptist University, HKSAR), Professor Jin Cheng (Fudan University, China), Professor June-Yub Lee (Ewha Womans University, South Korea), Professor Gui-Rong Liu (University of Cincinnati, USA), Professor Jenn-Nan Wang (National Taiwan University, Taiwan), and Professor Masahiro Yamamoto (The University of Tokyo, Japan). It was agreed to alternate holding the conference among the above places (China, Japan, Korea, Taiwan, and Hong Kong) once every two years. The next conference has been scheduled to be held at the Southeast University (Nanjing, China) in 2012. The purpose of this series of conferences is to establish a strong collaborative link among the universities of the Asian-Pacific regions and worldwide leading researchers in inverse problems. The conference addressed both theoretical (mathematics), applied (engineering) and developmental aspects of inverse problems. The conference was intended to nurture Asian-American-European collaborations in the evolving interdisciplinary areas and it was envisioned that the conference would lead to long-term commitments and collaborations among the participating countries and researchers. There was a total of more than 100 participants. A call for the submission of papers was sent out after the conference, and a total of 19 papers were finally accepted for publication in this proceedings. The papers included in the proceedings cover a wide scope, which reflects the current flourishing theoretical and numerical research into inverse problems. Finally, as the co-chairs of the Inverse Problems Conference 2010, we wish to express our cordial thanks to all the keynote, plenary, and invited speakers and members of the Advisory Board. We would like to thank the City University of Hong Kong, the Hong Kong Mathematical Society, the K C Wong Education Foundation, the Lee Hysan Foundation, and the Wei Lun Foundation for their generous financial support. Particularly, we wish to thank Miss Lonn Chan for her excellent administrative work in making all the arrangements for the conference. March 2011Yiu-Chung Hon, City University of Hong Kong, HKSARLeevan Ling, Hong Kong Baptist University, HKSAR Invited Keynote SpeakerH Thomas Banks, North Carolina State University, USA Invited Plenary SpeakersRyuichi Ashino, Osaka Kyoiku University, JapanAndrea Caponnetto, City University of Hong Kong, HKSARJeng-Tzong Chen, National Taiwan Ocean University, TaiwanHiromichi Itou, Gunma University, JapanHyeonbae Kang, Inha University, South KoreaMichael Klibanov, University of North Carolina at Charlotte, USAKim Knudsen, Technical University of Denmark, DenmarkRainer Kress, Georg-August-Universitat Gottingen, GermanyJerome Le Rousseau, University of Orleans, FranceChang-Ock Lee, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (KAIST), South KoreaGui-Rong Liu, University of Cincinnati, USAShuai Lu, Fudan University, ChinaFadil Santosa, University of Minnesota, USATomoya Takeuchi, North Carolina State University, USAXiang Xu, Zhejiang University, ChinaJun Zou, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, HKSAR Invited SpeakersMohamed Abdel-Mooty, The American University in Cairo, EgyptKrishna Agarwal, National University of Singapore, SingaporeHui Cao, Sun Yat-sen University, ChinaWen Chen, Hohai University, ChinaJin Cheng, Fudan University, ChinaLian Duan, University of Oxford, UKMeibao Ge, Zhejiang Sci-Tech University, ChinaRalf Hielscher, TU Chemnitz, GermanyGuanghui Hu, Weierstrass Institute for Applied Analysis and Stochastics (WIAS), GermanyKiwan Jeon, National Institute for Mathematical Sciences, South KoreaYu Jiang, Hokkaido University, JapanDe-Xing Kong, Zhejiang University, ChinaOlga Krivorotko, Novosibirsk State University, RussiaPhilipp Kuegler, Austrian Academy of Sciences, AustriaKiwoon Kwon, Dongguk University, South KoreaChun-Kong Law, National Sun Yat-sen University, TaiwanJune-Yub Lee, Ewha Womans University, South KoreaMing Li, City University of Hong Kong, HKSARMikyoung Lim, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (KAIST), South KoreaJijun Liu, Southeast University, ChinaXiaodong Liu, Chinese Academy of Sciences, ChinaFuming Ma, Jilin University, ChinaHang Ma, Shanghai University, ChinaValdemar Melicher, Ghent University, BelgiumGen Nakamura, Hokkaido University, JapanLong Tuan Nguyen, Ruhr-Universitat Bochum, GermanyEtibar Panakhov, Firat University, TurkeyRobert Plato, University of Siegen, GermanyJean-Pierre Puel, The University of Tokyo, JapanHans-Jurgen Reinhardt, University of Siegen, GermanyMaxim Shishlenin, Sobolev Institute of Mathematics, RussiaIlya Silvestrov, Institute of Petroleum Geology and Geophysics SB RAS, RussiaMourad Sini, Austrian Academy of Sciences, AustriaJan Sladek, Slovak Academy of Sciences, SlovakiaZhijun Tan, Sun Yat-sen University, ChinaQuan-Fang Wang, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, HKSARWenyan Wang, The University of Tokyo, JapanPihua Wen, Queen Mary, University of London, UKZhihai Xiang, Tsinghua University, ChinaXiang-Tuan Xiong, Northwest Normal University, ChinaDinghua Xu, Zhejiang Sci-Tech University, ChinaYongzhi Steve Xu, University of Louisville, USAJiaqing Yang, Chinese Academy of Sciences, ChinaJian Zhang, Sichuan Normal University, ChinaYing Zhang, Fudan University, ChinaTing Zhou, University of Washington, USAJianxin Zhu, Zhejiang University, China Advisory BoardH Thomas Banks, North Carolina State University, USATony F Chan, The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, HKSARHeinz W Engl, Johannes Kepler Universitat Linz, AustriaRainer Kress, Georg-August-Universitat Gottingen, GermanyTatsien (Daqian) Li, Fudan University, ChinaGunther Uhlmann, University of Washington, USA Organizing CommitteeJin Cheng, Fudan University, ChinaYiu-Chung Hon (Co-Chair), City University of Hong Kong, HKSARJune-Yub Lee, Ewha Womans University, South KoreaLeevan Ling (Co-Chair), Hong Kong Baptist University, HKSARGui-Rong Liu, University of Cincinnati, USAJenn-Nan Wang, National Taiwan University, TaiwanMasahiro Yamamoto, The University of Tokyo, Japan</abstract><url hash="4ec866b5">G11-2001</url><pages>011001</pages><doi>10.1088/1742-6596/290/1/011001</doi><bibkey>Hon-2011-International</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="3"><meta><booktitle>Earth System Dynamics, Volume 2, Issue 1</booktitle><publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher><address /><year>2011</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Quantifying the thermodynamic entropy budget of the land surface: is this useful?</title><author><first>N. A.</first><last>Brunsell</last></author><author><first>S. J.</first><last>Schymanski</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Kleidon</last></author><abstract>Abstract. As a system is moved away from a state of thermodynamic equilibrium, spatial and temporal heterogeneity is induced. A possible methodology to assess these impacts is to examine the thermodynamic entropy budget and assess the role of entropy production and transfer between the surface and the atmosphere. Here, we adopted this thermodynamic framework to examine the implications of changing vegetation fractional cover on land surface energy exchange processes using the NOAH land surface model and eddy covariance observations. Simulations that varied the relative fraction of vegetation were used to calculate the resultant entropy budget as a function of fraction of vegetation. Results showed that increasing vegetation fraction increases entropy production by the land surface while decreasing the overall entropy budget (the rate of change in entropy at the surface). This is accomplished largely via simultaneous increase in the entropy production associated with the absorption of solar radiation and a decline in the Bowen ratio (ratio of sensible to latent heat flux), which leads to increasing the entropy export associated with the latent heat flux during the daylight hours and dominated by entropy transfer associated with sensible heat and soil heat fluxes during the nighttime hours. Eddy covariance observations also show that the entropy production has a consistent sensitivity to land cover, while the overall entropy budget appears most related to the net radiation at the surface, however with a large variance. This implies that quantifying the thermodynamic entropy budget and entropy production is a useful metric for assessing biosphere-atmosphere-hydrosphere system interactions.</abstract><url hash="f67401d0">G11-3001</url><pages>87-103</pages><doi>10.5194/esd-2-87-2011</doi><bibkey>Brunsell-2011-Quantifying</bibkey></paper></volume></collection>