<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G13"><volume id="1"><meta><booktitle>Oikos, Volume 123, Issue 3</booktitle><publisher>Wiley</publisher><address /><year>2013</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Is the relationship between algal diversity and biomass in North American lakes consistent with biodiversity experiments?</title><author><first>Emily K.</first><last>Zimmerman</last></author><author><first>Bradley J.</first><last>Cardinale</last></author><abstract>Over the past few decades, a large body of research has examined how biodiversity loss influences the functioning of ecosystems, as well as the cascading impacts on the goods and services ecosystems provide to humanity. The relationship between biodiversity and ecosystem functions quantified in prior experiments suggests that initial losses of biodiversity have relatively small impacts on properties like community biomass production; however, beyond some threshold, increasing losses lead to accelerating declines in function. Some have questioned whether a saturating relationship between diversity and community biomass production is an artifact of overly simplified experiments that manipulate diversity in homogeneous conditions over short time-scales in which niche differences may not be realized. Others have questioned whether even the modest effects of biodiversity observed in experiments would be discernible in natural systems where they could be over-ridden by the stronger influence of abiotic factors. Here, we used a biogeographic dataset to assess how the taxonomic richness of aquatic primary producers relates to community biomass in unmanipulated lake ecosystems in the US, and then compared these findings to prior experiments. We used structural equation modeling to evaluate hypotheses about the effects of algal richness on community biomass while accounting for covariance with environmental parameters measured in the USEPA's National Lakes Assessment (NLA), which sampled 1157 freshwater lakes. These analyses converged on a single best-fit model (χ2= 0.31, p = 0.58) wherein community algal biomass was a function of three explanatory variables – nitrogen, phosphorus, and algal richness. The quantitative magnitude of the algal diversity (x) – biomass (y) relationship in the NLA dataset is statistically greater than that documented in the average biodiversity experiment. It did, however, lie at approximately the 75th percentile of experimental relationships, indicating the diversity–biomass relationship in unmanipulated lakes is within the range that has been characterized experimentally.</abstract><url hash="11b56850">G13-1001</url><pages>267-278</pages><doi>10.1111/j.1600-0706.2013.00777.x</doi><bibkey>Zimmerman-2013-Is</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="2"><meta><booktitle>IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing, Volume 6, Issue 3</booktitle><publisher>Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)</publisher><address /><year>2013</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Monitoring Soil Moisture in an Agricultural Test Site Using SAR Data: Design and Test of a Pre-Operational Procedure</title><author><first>Nazzareno</first><last>Pierdicca</last></author><author><first>Luca</first><last>Pulvirenti</last></author><author><first>Christian</first><last>Bignami</last></author><author><first>Francesca</first><last>Ticconi</last></author><abstract>An algorithm for pre-operational high resolution soil moisture mapping using Synthetic Aperture Radar (SAR) data is presented. It has been conceived to be inserted in the operational weather alert system of the Italian Department of Civil Protection. The Maximum A Posteriori (MAP) probability criterion is applied to retrieve soil moisture by inverting a forward backscattering model, and ancillary data such as optical images and land cover maps are also used to identify areas in which the retrieval can be carried out. The well-established semiempirical water cloud model is adopted to correct for the effect of vegetation on SAR data. In anticipation of the use of the algorithm in an operational system, in which the SAR-derived high resolution soil moisture product can be assimilated within weather prediction models or hydrological ones, an uncertainty index is associated to each estimate. The algorithm has been tested on a dataset consisting of ground data gathered for seven years (2003-2010) on an agricultural test site in Northern Italy and radar data provided by the C-band ENVISAT/ASAR instrument. A comparison, performed at field scale, between estimated and in situ soil moisture data has shown that, by discarding the estimates with the largest uncertainty, the correlation coefficient can exceed 0.80 and the root mean square estimation error is less than 0.05 m3/m3. Moreover, the uncertainty index has turned out to be fairly correlated to the actual estimation error.</abstract><url hash="0300c7be">G13-2001</url><pages>1199-1210</pages><doi>10.1109/jstars.2012.2237162</doi><bibkey>Pierdicca-2013-Monitoring</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="3"><meta><booktitle>Polar Biology, Volume 36, Issue 6</booktitle><publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher><address /><year>2013</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>The impact of snow accumulation on a heath spider community in a sub-Arctic landscape</title><author><first>Geoffrey</first><last>Legault</last></author><author><first>Arthur E.</first><last>Weis</last></author><abstract /><url hash="bbbca0db">G13-3001</url><pages>885-894</pages><doi>10.1007/s00300-013-1313-9</doi><bibkey>Legault-2013-The</bibkey></paper></volume></collection>