<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G14"><volume id="1"><meta><booktitle>Journal of Plant Growth Regulation, Volume 33, Issue 3</booktitle><publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher><address /><year>2014</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Effects of Combined Abiotic Stresses on Growth, Trace Element Accumulation, and Phytohormone Regulation in Two Halophytic Species</title><author><first>I.</first><last>Bankaji</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Sleimi</last></author><author><first>M. F.</first><last>López-Climent</last></author><author><first>R. M.</first><last>Perez-Clemente</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Gomez-Cadenas</last></author><abstract /><url hash="0cb058e8">G14-1001</url><pages>632-643</pages><doi>10.1007/s00344-014-9413-5</doi><bibkey>Bankaji-2014-Effects</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="2"><meta><booktitle>Environmental Health Insights, Volume 8</booktitle><publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher><address /><year>2014</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>A Framework for Building Research Partnerships with First Nations Communities</title><author><first>Lalita</first><last>Bharadwaj</last></author><abstract>Solutions to complex health and environmental issues experienced by First Nations communities in Canada require the adoption of collaborative modes of research. The traditional “helicopter” approach to research applied in communities has led to disenchantment on the part of First Nations people and has impeded their willingness to participate in research. University researchers have tended to develop projects without community input and to adopt short term approaches to the entire process, perhaps a reflection of granting and publication cycles and other realities of academia. Researchers often enter communities, collect data without respect for local culture, and then exit, having had little or no community interaction or consideration of how results generated could benefit communities or lead to sustainable solutions. Community-based participatory research (CBPR) has emerged as an alternative to the helicopter approach and is promoted here as a method to research that will meet the objectives of both First Nations and research communities. CBPR is a collaborative approach that equitably involves all partners in the research process. Although the benefits of CBPR have been recognized by segments of the University research community, there exists a need for comprehensive changes in approaches to First Nations centered research, and additional guidance to researchers on how to establish respectful and productive partnerships with First Nations communities beyond a single funded research project. This article provides a brief overview of ethical guidelines developed for researchers planning studies involving Aboriginal people as well as the historical context and principles of CBPR. A framework for building research partnerships with First Nations communities that incorporates and builds upon the guidelines and principles of CBPR is then presented. The framework was based on 10 years’ experience working with First Nations communities in Saskatchewan. The framework for research partnership is composed of five phases. They are categorized as the pre-research, community consultation, community entry, research and research dissemination phases. These phases are cyclical, non-linear and interconnected. Elements of, and opportunities for, exploration, discussion, engagement, consultation, relationship building, partnership development, community involvement, and information sharing are key components of the five phases within the framework. The phases and elements within this proposed framework have been utilized to build and implement sustainable collaborative environmental health research projects with Saskatchewan First Nations communities.</abstract><url hash="1e05f706">G14-2001</url><pages>EHI.S10869</pages><doi>10.4137/ehi.s10869</doi><bibkey>Bharadwaj-2014-A</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="3"><meta><booktitle>Transforming Government: People, Process and Policy, Volume 8, Issue 2</booktitle><publisher>Emerald</publisher><address /><year>2014</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Design principles for improving the process of publishing open data</title><author><first>Anneke</first><last>Zuiderwijk</last></author><author><first>Marijn</first><last>Janssen</last></author><author><first>Sunil</first><last>Choenni</last></author><author><first>Ronald</first><last>Meijer</last></author><abstract>Purpose – The purpose of this paper is to derive design principles for improving the open data publishing process of public organizations. Although governments create large amounts of data, the publication of open data is often cumbersome and there are no standard procedures and processes for opening data, blocking the easy publication of government data. Design/methodology/approach – Action design research (ADR) was used to derive design principles. The literature was used as a foundation, and discussion sessions with civil servants were used to evaluate the usefulness of the principles. Findings – Barriers preventing easy and low-cost publication of open data were identified and connected to design principles, which can be used to guide the design of an open data publishing process. Five new principles are: start thinking about the opening of data at the beginning of the process; develop guidelines, especially about privacy and policy sensitivity of data; provide decision support by integrating insight in the activities of other actors involved in the publishing process; make data publication an integral, well-defined and standardized part of daily procedures and routines; and monitor how the published data are reused. Research limitations/implications – The principles are derived using ADR in a single case. A next step can be to investigate multiple comparative case studies and detail the principles further. We recommend using these principles to develop a reference architecture. Practical implications – The design principles can be used by public organizations to improve their open data publishing processes. The design principles are derived from practice and discussed with practitioners. The discussions showed that the principles could improve the publication process. Social implications – Decreasing the barriers for publishing open government data could result in the publication of more open data. These open data can then be used to stimulate various public values, such as transparency, accountability, innovation, economic growth and informed decision- and policymaking. Originality/value – Publishing data by public organizations is a complex and ill-understood activity. The lack of suitable business processes and the unclear division of responsibilities block publication of open data. This paper contributes to the literature by presenting design principles which can be used to improve the open data publishing process of public sector organizations.</abstract><url hash="a6b99063">G14-3001</url><pages>185-204</pages><doi>10.1108/tg-07-2013-0024</doi><bibkey>Zuiderwijk-2014-Design</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="4"><meta><booktitle>Journal of The Royal Society Interface, Volume 11, Issue 97</booktitle><publisher>The Royal Society</publisher><address /><year>2014</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>How much information can be obtained from tracking the position of the leading edge in a scratch assay?</title><author><first>Stuart T.</first><last>Johnston</last></author><author><first>Matthew J.</first><last>Simpson</last></author><author><first>D. L. Sean</first><last>McElwain</last></author><abstract>Moving cell fronts are an essential feature of wound healing, development and disease. The rate at which a cell front moves is driven, in part, by the cell motility, quantified in terms of the cell diffusivity D , and the cell proliferation rate λ . Scratch assays are a commonly reported procedure used to investigate the motion of cell fronts where an initial cell monolayer is scratched, and the motion of the front is monitored over a short period of time, often less than 24 h. The simplest way of quantifying a scratch assay is to monitor the progression of the leading edge. Use of leading edge data is very convenient because, unlike other methods, it is non-destructive and does not require labelling, tracking or counting individual cells among the population. In this work, we study short-time leading edge data in a scratch assay using a discrete mathematical model and automated image analysis with the aim of investigating whether such data allow us to reliably identify D and λ . Using a naive calibration approach where we simply scan the relevant region of the ( D , λ ) parameter space, we show that there are many choices of D and λ for which our model produces indistinguishable short-time leading edge data. Therefore, without due care, it is impossible to estimate D and λ from this kind of data. To address this, we present a modified approach accounting for the fact that cell motility occurs over a much shorter time scale than proliferation. Using this information, we divide the duration of the experiment into two periods, and we estimate D using data from the first period, whereas we estimate λ using data from the second period. We confirm the accuracy of our approach using in silico data and a new set of in vitro data, which shows that our method recovers estimates of D and λ that are consistent with previously reported values except that that our approach is fast, inexpensive, non-destructive and avoids the need for cell labelling and cell counting.</abstract><url hash="3b6ea8da">G14-4001</url><pages>20140325</pages><doi>10.1098/rsif.2014.0325</doi><bibkey>Johnston-2014-How</bibkey></paper></volume></collection>