<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<collection id="G24">
	<volume id="1">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Geoderma, Volume 443</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>The apparent temperature sensitivity (Q10) of peat soil respiration: A synthesis study</title>
			<author>
				<first>Haojie</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fereidoun</first>
				<last>Rezanezhad</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ying</first>
				<last>Zhao</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hongxing</first>
				<last>He</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bernd</first>
				<last>Lennartz</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The temperature sensitivity (Q10) of soil respiration is a critical parameter in modeling soil carbon dynamics; yet the regulating factors and the underlying mechanisms of Q10 in peat soils remain unclear. To address this gap, we conducted a comprehensive synthesis data analysis from 87 peatland sites (350 observations) spanning boreal, temperate, and tropical zones, and investigated the spatial distribution pattern of Q10 and its correlation with climate conditions, soil properties, and hydrology. Findings revealed distinct Q10 values across climate zones: boreal peatlands exhibited the highest Q10, trailed by temperate and then tropical peatlands. Latitude presented a positive correlation with Q10, while mean annual air temperature and precipitation revealed a negative correlation. The results from the structural equation model suggest that soil properties, such as carbon-to-nitrogen ratio (C/N) and peat type, were the primary drivers of the variance in Q10 of peat respiration. Peat C/N ratios negatively correlated with Q10 of peat respiration and the relationship between C/N and Q10 varied significantly between peat types. Our data analyses also revealed that Q10 was influenced by soil moisture levels, with significantly lower values observed for peat soils under wet than dry conditions. Essentially, boreal and temperate peatlands seem more vulnerable to global warming-induced soil organic carbon decomposition than tropical counterparts, with wet peatlands showing higher climate resilience.</abstract>
			<url hash="3d584275">G24-1001</url>
			<pages>116844</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.geoderma.2024.116844</doi>
			<bibkey>Liu-2024-The</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="2">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Applied Geochemistry, Volume 162</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Road salt-induced salinization impacts water geochemistry and mixing regime of a Canadian urban lake</title>
			<author>
				<first>Jovana</first>
				<last>Radosavljevic</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stephanie</first>
				<last>Slowinski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fereidoun</first>
				<last>Rezanezhad</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mahyar</first>
				<last>Shafii</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bahram</first>
				<last>Gharabaghi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The extensive use of road salts as deicers during winter months is causing the salinization of freshwater systems in cold climate regions worldwide. We analyzed 20 years (2001–2020) of data on lake water chemistry, land cover changes, and road salt applications for Lake Wilcox (LW) located in southern Ontario, Canada. The lake is situated within a rapidly urbanizing watershed in which, during the period of observation, on average 785 tons of road salt were applied annually. However, only about a quarter of this salt has reached the lake so far. That is, most salt has been retained in the watershed, likely through accumulation in soils and groundwater. Despite the high watershed salt retention, time series trend analyses for LW show significant increases in the dissolved concentrations of sodium (Na+) and chloride (Cl−), as well as those of sulfate (SO42−), calcium (Ca2+), and magnesium (Mg2+). The relative changes in the major ion concentrations indicate a shift of the lake water chemistry from the mixed SO42–Cl–Ca2+-Mg2+ type to the Na + -Cl- type. Salinization of LW has further been strengthening and lengthening the lake's summer stratification, which, in turn, has been enhancing hypoxia in the hypolimnion and increasing the internal loading of the limiting nutrient phosphorus. The theoretical salinity threshold at which fall overturn would become increasingly unlikely was estimated at around 1.23 g kg−1. A simple chloride mass balance model predicts that, under the current trend of impermeable land cover expansion, LW could reach this salinity threshold by mid-century. Our results also highlight the need for additional research on the accruing salt legacies in urbanizing watersheds because they represent potential long-term threats to water quality for receiving freshwater ecosystems and regional groundwater resources.</abstract>
			<url hash="2feded9b">G24-2001</url>
			<pages>105928</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.apgeochem.2024.105928</doi>
			<bibkey>Radosavljevic-2024-Road</bibkey>
			<project>prj26</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="3">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Chemosphere, Volume 349</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Co-precipitation of iron and silicon: Reaction kinetics, elemental ratios and the influence of phosphorus</title>
			<author>
				<first>Lu</first>
				<last>Huang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Chris T.</first>
				<last>Parsons</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stephanie</first>
				<last>Slowinski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>A sufficient supply of dissolved silicon (DSi) relative to dissolved phosphorus (DP) may decrease the likelihood of harmful algal blooms in eutrophic waters. Oxidative precipitation of Fe(II) at oxic-anoxic interfaces may contribute to the immobilization of DSi, thereby exerting control over the DSi availability in the overlying water. Nevertheless, the efficacy of DSi immobilization in this context remains to be precisely determined. To investigate the behavior of DSi during Fe(II) oxidation, anoxic solutions containing mixtures of aqueous Fe(II), DSi, and dissolved phosphorus (DP) were exposed to dissolved oxygen (DO) in the batch system. The experimental data, combined with kinetic reaction modeling, indicate that DSi removal during Fe(II) oxidation occurs via two pathways. At the beginning of the experiments, the oxidation of Fe(II)-DSi complexes induces the fast removal of DSi. Upon complete oxidation of Fe(II), further DSi removal is due to adsorption to surface sites of the Fe(III) oxyhydroxides. The presence of DP effectively competes with DSi via both of these pathways during the initial and later stages of the experiments, with as a result more limited removal of DSi during Fe(II) oxidation. Overall, we conclude that at near neutral pH the oxidation of Fe(II) has considerable capacity to immobilize DSi, where the rapid homogeneous oxidation of Fe(II)-DSi results in greater DSi removal compared to surface adsorption. Elevated DP concentration, however, effectively outcompetes DSi in co-precipitation interactions, potentially contributing to enhanced DSi availability within aquatic systems.</abstract>
			<url hash="97518afe">G24-3001</url>
			<pages>140930</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.140930</doi>
			<bibkey>Huang-2024-Co-precipitation</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="4">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Hydrology, Volume 630</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Advancement and perspectives of hyporheic zone hydrology: Technology, theory and environmental implication</title>
			<author>
				<first>Zhang</first>
				<last>Wen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hui</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fereidoun</first>
				<last>Rezanezhad</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stefan</first>
				<last>Krause</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="0a86b247">G24-4001</url>
			<pages>130721</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.jhydrol.2024.130721</doi>
			<bibkey>Wen-2024-Advancement</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="5">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Geophysical Research Letters, Volume 51, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Geophysical Union (AGU)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Constraining Projected Changes in Rare Intense Precipitation Events Across Global Land Regions</title>
			<author>
				<first>Chao</first>
				<last>Li</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Qiaohong</first>
				<last>Sun</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jianyu</first>
				<last>Wang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yongxiao</first>
				<last>Liang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Francis W.</first>
				<last>Zwiers</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Xuebin</first>
				<last>Zhang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Tong</first>
				<last>Li</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Rare precipitation events with return periods of multiple decades to hundreds of years are particularly damaging to natural and societal systems. Projections of such rare, damaging precipitation events in the future climate are, however, subject to large inter‐model variations. We show that a substantial portion of these differences can be ascribed to the projected warming uncertainty, and can be robustly reduced by using the warming observed during recent decades as an observational constraint, implemented either by directly constraining the projections with the observed warming or by conditioning them on constrained warming projections, as verified by extensive model‐based cross‐validation. The temperature constraint reduces &gt;40% of the warming‐induced uncertainty in the projected intensification of future rare daily precipitation events for a climate that is 2°C warmer than preindustrial across most regions. This uncertainty reduction together with validation of the reliability of the projections should permit more confident adaptation planning at regional levels.</abstract>
			<url hash="3d584275">G24-1001</url>
			<doi>10.1029/2023gl105605</doi>
			<bibkey>Li-2024-Constraining</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="6">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Atmosphere-Ocean, Volume 62, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Performance Evaluation of High-resolution Reanalysis Datasets Over North-central British Columbia</title>
			<author>
				<first>Uttam</first>
				<last>Goswami</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stephen J.</first>
				<last>Déry</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Vincent</first>
				<last>Fortin</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Version 2.1 of Environment and Climate Change Canada's Canadian Surface Reanalysis (CaSR), based on the Regional Deterministic Reforecast System (RDRS), was implemented in 2022 to provide temporally complete meteorological data over 1980–2018 covering Canada at 10 km spatial resolution. Similarly, the fifth generation of the European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF) Re-Analysis-Land (ERA5-Land) dataset at ∼9 km spatial resolution became available. To assess their performance in complex topography, this paper undertakes spatiotemporal inter-comparisons between the RDRS and ERA5-Land reanalysis products with station-based data across British Columbia's Skeena and Nechako watersheds for 1980–2018. Results reveal persistent cold biases, ranging from −6.2°C to −1.6°C basin-wide, in reanalysis mean annual air temperatures relative to observations, but biases vary in both space and time. Conversely, reanalysis total annual precipitation shows wet biases, ranging from 25% to 59% basin-wide. Analyses generally show wetting trends for observations and ERA5-Land while RDRS exhibits drying trends. Reanalysis datasets achieve better agreement overall with observations over the Nechako Watershed, likely due to its denser network of meteorological stations and less complex terrain than the Skeena Watershed. Despite some deficiencies, the RDRS and ERA5-Land reanalyses remain particularly useful products to assess regional climate variability and climatic change given their generally skilful representation of spatial patterns and temporal trends in meteorological variables across the Nechako and Skeena watersheds.</abstract>
			<url hash="2feded9b">G24-2001</url>
			<pages>222-242</pages>
			<doi>10.1080/07055900.2024.2308878</doi>
			<bibkey>Goswami-2024-Performance</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="7">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Cluster Computing, Volume 27, Issue 5</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Improving resource utilization and fault tolerance in large simulations via actors</title>
			<author>
				<first>Kyle</first>
				<last>Klenk</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Raymond J.</first>
				<last>Spiteri</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="97518afe">G24-3001</url>
			<pages>6323-6340</pages>
			<doi>10.1007/s10586-024-04318-5</doi>
			<bibkey>Klenk-2024-Improving</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="8">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Numerical Algorithms, Volume 96, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>The effect of splitting strategy on qualitative property preservation</title>
			<author>
				<first>Siqi</first>
				<last>Wei</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Raymond J.</first>
				<last>Spiteri</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="0a86b247">G24-4001</url>
			<pages>1391-1421</pages>
			<doi>10.1007/s11075-023-01730-7</doi>
			<bibkey>Wei-2024-The</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="9">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Geoderma, Volume 442</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>An efficient soil moisture sampling scheme for the improvement of remotely sensed soil moisture validation over an agricultural field</title>
			<author>
				<first>Z.</first>
				<last>Alijani</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Riley</first>
				<last>Eyre</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Daniel</first>
				<last>Saurette</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ahmed</first>
				<last>Laamrani</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John B.</first>
				<last>Lindsay</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Andrew W.</first>
				<last>Western</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Aaron</first>
				<last>Berg</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>An efficient and robust soil moisture (SM) sampling scheme that can capture the spatial variability of SM is required for the accurate calibration and validation of satellite-based SM retrievals. Often, this process requires numerous sampling points, consuming a significant amount of time. Therefore, it is crucial to develop efficient sampling methods for the improvement of satellite-based SM estimations. The objectives of this study were to define an efficient sampling strategy that could be beneficial for the validation of satellite SM estimations; investigate the role of RS covariates in developing such a strategy; and evaluate the performance of the new sampling scheme over various spatial and temporal domains. In this study, we used the conditioned Latin hypercube sampling (cLHS) algorithm to define an efficient sampling strategy. To this end, remote sensing (RS) raster and digital elevation models (DEM) were used to identify numerous environmental covariates to locate sampling points for characterizing spatial variability of SM at the agricultural field scale. A random forest-based technique, the Boruta algorithm, was also applied to select the most important covariates for utilization into the cLHS algorithm. We used the statistical moments (mean and standard deviation, SD) of the field to select the efficient sample size that can best represent SM status in the field. To evaluate the new sampling scheme, a second data set obtained during a different month for the same agricultural field was used. However, because of the potential for high spatial and temporal correlations between training and test covariates when obtained for the same region, we also used different test datasets in New Zealand to evaluate the sampling scheme. Results showed that the RS covariates obtained from SAR and optical imagery were among the most significant covariates for capturing the spatial variability of SM even if they were not acquired on the day of collection. Also, the new sampling scheme could capture the SM spatial pattern of the field for both test datasets with RMSE less than 4% volumetric SM, which is within the range of the expected performance for most satellite SM products. The evaluation of the new sampling scheme on the New Zealand datasets confirmed the functionality of the proposed sampling scheme for a different temporal and spatial domain.</abstract>
			<url hash="b23ad522">G24-5001</url>
			<pages>116763</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.geoderma.2023.116763</doi>
			<bibkey>Alijani-2024-An</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="10">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Environmental Management, Volume 354</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Improving water quality in a hypereutrophic lake and tributary through agricultural nutrient mitigation: A Multi-year monitoring analysis</title>
			<author>
				<first>Barry</first>
				<last>Husk</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Paul</first>
				<last>Julian</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Dana F.</first>
				<last>Simon</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nicolas</first>
				<last>Tromas</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Dawson</first>
				<last>Phan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kristin J.</first>
				<last>Painter</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Helen M.</first>
				<last>Baulch</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sébastien</first>
				<last>Sauvé</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="a08f7acc">G24-6001</url>
			<pages>120411</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.120411</doi>
			<bibkey>Husk-2024-Improving</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="11">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Science of The Total Environment, Volume 912</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>‘Paleofloodscapes’: Application of sediment source fingerprinting to track flood regime change over space and time at the Peace-Athabasca Delta, Canada</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mitchell L.</first>
				<last>Kay</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Lauren A.</first>
				<last>MacDonald</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Johan A.</first>
				<last>Wiklund</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Cory A.M.</first>
				<last>Girard</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brent B.</first>
				<last>Wolfe</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Roland I.</first>
				<last>Hall</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Deltas are hydrologically dynamic landscapes where river floodwaters create a mosaic of productive ecosystems that provide important services. The flood regime, however, is vulnerable to upstream anthropogenic activities, climate change and geomorphic processes. Deciphering the roles of multiple potential stressors on flood regime change is critical for developing appropriate adaptive and mitigative strategies but requires knowledge of hydrological variability at broader scales of space and time than is typically available from instrumental and observational records. At the globally recognized Peace-Athabasca Delta (Canada), the timing, magnitude and causes of reduced flooding and drawdown of perched basin water levels remain an intense focus of investigation. Here we employ novel 'paleofloodscapes', generated from geospatial interpolation of Bayesian mixing model fingerprinting of sediment elemental concentrations, to quantify variation in the delta's flood regime during the past ~140 years. Results reveal that flooding of the delta began to decline several decades before hydroelectric regulation of Peace River flow, not coincident with it, and the influence of floodwaters from the unregulated Athabasca River has declined more than the regulated Peace River. A key discovery is that widespread flooding of perched basins occurs when ice-jam events on the river(s) coincide with a relatively high water-plane in the delta's open-drainage network. Without knowledge of open-drainage water levels, inferred change to the flood regime of perched basins may be inaccurate when derived solely from analyses of Peace River hydrometric data and climatic records. The paleofloodscapes illustrate that rising sediment delivery to the site of a proposed weir, caused by a natural river avulsion in 1982, may undermine the weir's intended purpose. The most recent paleofloodscape, developed from lake surface sediment sampling shortly after widespread flooding, demonstrates the value of the approach as a landscape hydrological monitoring tool, and is readily transferrable to other floodplains to track flood regime change.</abstract>
			<url hash="18331da9">G24-7001</url>
			<pages>169538</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.169538</doi>
			<bibkey>Kay-2024-‘Paleofloodscapes’:</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="12">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Science of The Total Environment, Volume 923</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Human biomonitoring of dioxins, furans, and non-ortho dioxin-like polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) in blood plasma from Old Crow, Yukon, Canada (2019)</title>
			<author>
				<first>Ashlyn K.</first>
				<last>Simpson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mallory</first>
				<last>Drysdale</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mary</first>
				<last>Gamberg</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ken</first>
				<last>Froese</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jeremy R.</first>
				<last>Brammer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Pierre</first>
				<last>Dumas</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mylène</first>
				<last>Ratelle</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kelly</first>
				<last>Skinner</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brian</first>
				<last>Laird</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Dioxins, furans, and dioxin-like polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) are a group of persistent and toxic chemicals that are known to have human health effects at low levels. These chemicals have been produced for commercial use (PCBs) or unintentionally as by-products of industry or natural processes (PCBs, dioxins, and furans). Additionally, dioxin-like PCBs were formerly used in electrical applications before being banned internationally (2004). These chemicals are widely dispersed in the environment as they can contaminate air and travel hundreds to thousands of kilometers before depositing on land or water, thereafter, potentially entering food chains. Community concerns surrounding the safety of traditional foods prompted a human biomonitoring project in Old Crow, Yukon Territory (YT), Canada (2019). Through collaborative community engagement, dioxins and like compounds were identified as a priority for exposure assessment from biobanked samples. In 2022, biobanked plasma samples (n = 54) collected in Old Crow were used to measure exposures to seven dioxins, ten furans, and four dioxin-like PCBs. 1,2,3,6,7,8-HxCDD, 1,2,3,7,8,9-HxCDD, 1,2,3,4,6,7,8-HpCDD, OCDD, 2,3,4,7,8-PeCDF, 1,2,3,6,7,8-HxCDF, PCB 126, and PCB 169 were detected in at least 50 % of samples. Among these analytes, the only congener at elevated levels was PCB 169, which was approximately ∼2-fold higher than the general population of Canada. No significant sex-based or body mass index (BMI) differences in biomarker concentrations were observed. Generally, the concentrations of the detected congeners increased with age, except for 1,2,3,4,6,7,8-HpCDD. For the first time, this research measures dioxin and like-compound exposures in Old Crow, advancing the information available on chemical exposures in the Arctic. Further research could be directed towards the investigation of PCB 169 exposure sources and temporal monitoring of exposures and determinants.</abstract>
			<url hash="40500dff">G24-8001</url>
			<pages>171222</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.171222</doi>
			<bibkey>Simpson-2024-Human</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="13">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Science of The Total Environment, Volume 919</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Short-term dynamics of beaver dam flow states</title>
			<author>
				<first>Ignacio</first>
				<last>Aguirre</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Glynnis A.</first>
				<last>Hood</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Cherie J.</first>
				<last>Westbrook</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Beavers (Castor canadensis and C. fiber) build dams that modify catchment and pond water balances, and it has been suggested that they can be a nature-based solution for reducing flood hydrographs, enhancing low flow hydrographs and restoring hydrological functioning of degraded streams. How water moves through a beaver dam is determined by its flow state (e.g., overflow, underflow). However, current conceptual models only consider flow state as changing over the beaver site occupation-abandonment cycle. To assess whether flow state changes at shorter timescales and identify possible triggers (e.g., rainfall, animals), we integrated camera trap imagery, machine learning, water level measurements, and hydrometeorological data at beaver dams in a montane peatland in the Canadian Rocky Mountains. Contrary to current models, we found that flow states changed frequently, changing a maximum 12 times during the 139-day study period, but that changes had limited synchronicity amongst the dams in the same stream. More than two-thirds of the changes coincided with rainfall events. We observed no changes in flow state in response to beaver activity or wildlife crossings perhaps due to the camera positioning. Our findings augment the long-term oriented framework, which links changes to the occupancy cycle of a beaver pond and frequent and hydrological-driven changes. To develop realistic predictions of hydrological impacts of beaver dams, ecohydrological models should update their representation of the influence of beaver dams to include short-term dynamism of flow states and potential triggers. Our study advances the understanding of the important, yet understudied, role of beaver dams in stream restoration and climate change initiatives.</abstract>
			<url hash="f8ec6a9a">G24-9001</url>
			<pages>170825</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.170825</doi>
			<bibkey>Aguirre-2024-Short-term</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="14">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Science: Advances, Volume 3, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>Royal Society of Chemistry (RSC)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>A preliminary investigation of microbial communities on the Athabasca Glacier within deposited organic matter</title>
			<author>
				<first>Milena</first>
				<last>Esser</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Phillip</first>
				<last>Ankley</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Caroline</first>
				<last>Aubry‐Wake</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yuwei</first>
				<last>Xie</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Helen M.</first>
				<last>Baulch</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Cameron</first>
				<last>Hoggarth</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Markus</first>
				<last>Hecker</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Henner</first>
				<last>Hollert</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Markus</first>
				<last>Brinkmann</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Glacier ecosystems are shrinking at an accelerating rate due to changes in climate, and increased darkening from allochthonous and autochthonous carbon is leading to changes in light absorption, associated heat, and microbial communities.</abstract>
			<url hash="ba950307">G24-10001</url>
			<pages>355-365</pages>
			<doi>10.1039/d3va00176h</doi>
			<bibkey>Esser-2024-A</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="15">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Science: Advances, Volume 3, Issue 6</booktitle>
			<publisher>Royal Society of Chemistry (RSC)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Mineral formation explains the high retention efficiency of dissolved reactive phosphorus in a residential stormwater pond</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mahyar</first>
				<last>Shafii</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stephanie</first>
				<last>Slowinski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Md Abdus</first>
				<last>Sabur</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Alina</first>
				<last>Arvisais</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yubraj</first>
				<last>Bhusal</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>William</first>
				<last>Withers</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Konrad</first>
				<last>Krogstad</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Chris T.</first>
				<last>Parsons</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Stormwater ponds (SWPs) alter the export of the macronutrient phosphorus (P) from urban landscapes, hence impacting the trophic state and water quality of downstream aquatic environments.</abstract>
			<url hash="02296462">G24-11001</url>
			<pages>819-832</pages>
			<doi>10.1039/d3va00267e</doi>
			<bibkey>Shafii-2024-Mineral</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="16">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Annals of Botany</booktitle>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Low-severity fires in the boreal region: reproductive implications for black spruce stands in between stand-replacing fire events</title>
			<author>
				<first>Raquel</first>
				<last>Alfaro‐Sánchez</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jill F.</first>
				<last>Johnstone</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jennifer L.</first>
				<last>Baltzer</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Stand-replacing crown fires are the most prevalent type of fire regime in boreal forests in North America. However, a substantial proportion of low-severity fires are found within fire perimeters. Here we aimed to investigate the effects of low-severity fires on the reproductive potential and seedling recruitment in boreal forests stands in between stand-replacing fire events.</abstract>
			<url hash="109ccb8c">G24-12001</url>
			<doi>10.1093/aob/mcae055</doi>
			<bibkey>Alfaro-Sánchez-2024-Low-severity</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="17">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Reviews, Volume 32, Issue 4</booktitle>
			<publisher>Canadian Science Publishing</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>A review of arsenic speciation in freshwater fish: perspectives on monitoring approaches and analytical methods</title>
			<author>
				<first>Adam T.</first>
				<last>Lepage</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brian</first>
				<last>Laird</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kelly</first>
				<last>Skinner</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John M.</first>
				<last>Gunn</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Gretchen L.</first>
				<last>Lescord</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Arsenic accumulation in fish poses concerns for subsistence and recreational fishers worldwide. However, the toxicity of arsenic to consumers strongly depends on the chemical forms, or species, present. Risk assessments often rely on total arsenic concentrations ([As]), adjusting for assumed small percentages of the most harmful inorganic species. While studies on arsenic speciation in marine fish are widespread, and commonly report less toxic arsenobetaine (AsB) as the dominant form, fewer studies have been conducted on freshwater fish, where arsenic speciation may be more variable. To assess these findings, we conducted a systematic literature review on arsenic speciation in freshwater fish using Covidence© review management software. From over 1100 screened studies, 41 were selected for inclusion based on predefined criteria. These studies reported highly variable arsenic speciation patterns in freshwater fish, calling into question the assumption that AsB is the dominant form present. Sites with suspected or known arsenic contamination issues were prominent, with &gt;50% of data reviewed originating from a contaminated river or lake, but the effect of contamination on arsenic speciation was variable. Although AsB and other organic forms typically dominated, some studies (6/41; 15%) identified fish with elevated concentrations of inorganic arsenic (&gt;1 mg/kg dry wt.), most often corresponding to over 20% of total arsenic. Furthermore, arsenic speciation results accounted for a highly variable proportion of total [As] in fish, often less than 50%. Assuming 20% inorganic arsenic appears to be a poor approximation that cannot be applied to all fish. Based on this considerable variability, we recommend the direct measurement of arsenic species whenever possible, especially when total [As] is elevated above relevant guidelines for the most toxic species (e.g., 0.1-2 mg/kg inorganic arsenic wet wt.). We also recommend future works communicate their results in more detail, including complete description of QAQC protocols, to improve the potential for future meta-analyses. Additional work is needed to characterize arsenic speciation in freshwater fish and assess the toxicity of various arsenic species to accurately evaluate the environmental and human health risks associated with arsenic in fish.</abstract>
			<url hash="a820ace9">G24-13001</url>
			<pages>539-556</pages>
			<doi>10.1139/er-2024-0011</doi>
			<bibkey>Lepage-2024-A</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="18">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Remote Sensing, Volume 16, Issue 9</booktitle>
			<publisher>MDPI AG</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Comparative Evaluation of Semi-Empirical Approaches to Retrieve Satellite-Derived Chlorophyll-a Concentrations from Nearshore and Offshore Waters of a Large Lake (Lake Ontario)</title>
			<author>
				<first>Ali Reza</first>
				<last>Shahvaran</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Homa Kheyrollah</first>
				<last>Pour</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Chlorophyll-a concentration (Chl-a) is commonly used as a proxy for phytoplankton abundance in surface waters of large lakes. Mapping spatial and temporal Chl-a distributions derived from multispectral satellite data is therefore increasingly popular for monitoring trends in trophic state of these important ecosystems. We evaluated products of eleven atmospheric correction processors (LEDAPS, LaSRC, Sen2Cor, ACOLITE, ATCOR, C2RCC, DOS 1, FLAASH, iCOR, Polymer, and QUAC) and 27 reflectance indexes (including band-ratio, three-band, and four-band algorithms) recommended for Chl-a concentration retrieval. These were applied to the western basin of Lake Ontario by pairing 236 satellite scenes from Landsat 5, 7, 8, and Sentinel-2 acquired between 2000 and 2022 to 600 near-synchronous and co-located in situ-measured Chl-a concentrations. The in situ data were categorized based on location, seasonality, and Carlson’s Trophic State Index (TSI). Linear regression Chl-a models were calibrated for each processing scheme plus data category. The models were compared using a range of performance metrics. Categorization of data based on trophic state yielded improved outcomes. Furthermore, Sentinel-2 and Landsat 8 data provided the best results, while Landsat 5 and 7 underperformed. A total of 28 Chl-a models were developed across the different data categorization schemes, with RMSEs ranging from 1.1 to 14.1 μg/L. ACOLITE-corrected images paired with the blue-to-green band ratio emerged as the generally best performing scheme. However, model performance was dependent on the data filtration practices and varied between satellites.</abstract>
			<url hash="35f79450">G24-14001</url>
			<pages>1595</pages>
			<doi>10.3390/rs16091595</doi>
			<bibkey>Shahvaran-2024-Comparative</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="19">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Remote Sensing, Volume 16, Issue 12</booktitle>
			<publisher>MDPI AG</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Assessing Ice Break-Up Trends in Slave River Delta through Satellite Observations and Random Forest Modeling</title>
			<author>
				<first>Ida</first>
				<last>Moalemi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Homa Kheyrollah</first>
				<last>Pour</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>K. Andrea</first>
				<last>Scott</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The seasonal temperature trends and ice phenology in the Great Slave Lake (GSL) are significantly influenced by inflow from the Slave River. The river undergoes a sequence of mechanical break-ups all the way to the GSL, initiating the GSL break-up process. Additionally, upstream water management practices impact the discharge of the Slave River and, consequently, the ice break-up of the GSL. Therefore, monitoring the break-up process at the Slave River Delta (SRD), where the river meets the lake, is crucial for understanding the cascading effects of upstream activities on GSL ice break-up. This research aimed to use Random Forest (RF) models to monitor the ice break-up processes at the SRD using a combination of satellite images with relatively high spatial resolution, including Landsat-5, Landsat-8, Sentinel-2a, and Sentinel-2b. The RF models were trained using selected training pixels to classify ice, open water, and cloud. The onset of break-up was determined by data-driven thresholds on the ice fraction in images with less than 20% cloud coverage. Analysis of break-up timing from 1984 to 2023 revealed a significant earlier trend using the Mann–Kendall test with a p-value of 0.05. Furthermore, break-up data in recent years show a high degree of variability in the break-up rate using images in recent years with better temporal resolution.</abstract>
			<url hash="8d4bf335">G24-15001</url>
			<pages>2244</pages>
			<doi>10.3390/rs16122244</doi>
			<bibkey>Moalemi-2024-Assessing</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="20">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>ACS Earth and Space Chemistry, Volume 8, Issue 4</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Chemical Society (ACS)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Arsenic Mobilization from Thawing Permafrost</title>
			<author>
				<first>Elliott K.</first>
				<last>Skierszkan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Valerie A.</first>
				<last>Schoepfer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matthew</first>
				<last>Fellwock</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Dockrey</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ardalan</first>
				<last>Hayatifar</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Viorica F.</first>
				<last>Bondici</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Joyce</first>
				<last>McBeth</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matthew B.J.</first>
				<last>Lindsay</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Thawing permafrost releases labile organic carbon and alters groundwater geochemistry and hydrology with uncertain outcomes for the mobility of hazardous metal(loid)s. Managing water quality in thawing permafrost regions is predicated on a detailed understanding of the speciation and abundance of metal(loid)s in permafrost soils and porewaters produced during thaw, which remains limited at present. This study contributes new knowledge on the sources and fate of arsenic during the thaw of organic-rich permafrost using samples collected from a subarctic permafrost region associated with geogenic arsenic (Dawson Range, Yukon, Canada). Several permafrost cores and active-layer samples from this region were analyzed for their solid-phase and aqueous geochemical characteristics and their arsenic speciation. Porewaters were extracted from permafrost cores after thaw under anaerobic conditions for aqueous geochemical analyses. Bedrock samples from the field site were also analyzed for arsenic speciation and mineralogy. X-ray diffraction and X-ray near-edge spectroscopy (XANES) analyses of weathered bedrock upgradient of soil sampling locations contained arsenic(V) hosted in iron-(oxyhydr)oxides and scorodite. XANES and micro X-ray fluorescence analyses of permafrost soils indicated a mixture of arsenic(III) and arsenic(V), indicating redox recycling of arsenic. Soil-bound arsenic was colocated with iron, likely as arseniferous iron-(oxyhydr)oxides that have been encapsulated by aggrading permafrost over geologic time. However, permafrost thaw produced porewater containing elevated dissolved arsenic (median 40 μg L–1, range 2–96 μg L–1). Thawed permafrost porewater also contained elevated dissolved iron (median 5.5 mg L–1, range 0.5–40 mg L–1) and dissolved organic carbon (median 423 mg L–1, range 72–3240 mg L–1), indicative of reducing conditions. This study highlights that arsenic can be found in reactive forms in permafrost soil, and that its thaw can release arsenic and iron to porewater and produce poor water quality.</abstract>
			<url hash="9ffe5cdb">G24-16001</url>
			<pages>745-759</pages>
			<doi>10.1021/acsearthspacechem.3c00355</doi>
			<bibkey>Skierszkan-2024-Arsenic</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="21">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Science &amp; Technology, Volume 58, Issue 26</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Chemical Society (ACS)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Urban Stormwater Phosphorus Export Control: Comparing Traditional and Low-impact Development Best Management Practices</title>
			<author>
				<first>Bowen</first>
				<last>Zhou</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Chris T.</first>
				<last>Parsons</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Data from the International Stormwater Best Management Practices (BMP) Database were used to compare the phosphorus (P) control performance of six categories of stormwater BMPs representing traditional systems (stormwater pond, wetland basin, and detention basin) and low-impact development (LID) systems (bioretention cell, grass swale, and grass strip). Machine learning (ML) models were trained to predict the reduction or enrichment factors of surface runoff concentrations and loadings of total P (TP) and soluble reactive P (SRP) for the different categories of BMP systems. Relative to traditional BMPs, LIDs generally enriched TP and SRP concentrations in stormwater surface outflow and yielded poorer P runoff load control. The SRP concentration reduction and enrichment factors of LIDs also tended to be more sensitive to variations in climate and watershed characteristics. That is, LIDs were more likely to enrich surface runoff SRP concentrations in drier climates, when inflow SRP concentrations were low, and for watersheds exhibiting high impervious land cover. Overall, our results imply that stormwater BMPs do not universally attenuate urban P export and that preferentially implementing LIDs over traditional BMPs may increase TP and SRP export to receiving freshwater bodies, hence magnifying eutrophication risks.</abstract>
			<url hash="27423bbe">G24-17001</url>
			<pages>11376-11385</pages>
			<doi>10.1021/acs.est.4c01705</doi>
			<bibkey>Zhou-2024-Urban</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="22">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Remote Sensing of Environment, Volume 304</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Arctic ice-wedge landscape mapping by CNN using a fusion of Radarsat constellation Mission and ArcticDEM</title>
			<author>
				<first>Michael</first>
				<last>Merchant</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Laura</first>
				<last>Bourgeau‐Chavez</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Masoud</first>
				<last>Mahdianpari</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brian</first>
				<last>Brisco</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mayah</first>
				<last>Obadia</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ben</first>
				<last>DeVries</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Aaron</first>
				<last>Berg</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="7f212be8">G24-18001</url>
			<pages>114052</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.rse.2024.114052</doi>
			<bibkey>Merchant-2024-Arctic</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="23">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Science of The Total Environment, Volume 914</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Hexachlorobenzene and omega-3 fatty acid intake from traditional foods in the northern Yukon: A risk and benefit analysis</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mallory</first>
				<last>Drysdale</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mary</first>
				<last>Gamberg</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jeremy R.</first>
				<last>Brammer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Shannon E.</first>
				<last>Majowicz</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sara</first>
				<last>Packull-McCormick</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kelly</first>
				<last>Skinner</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brian</first>
				<last>Laird</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="c79d4c8d">G24-19001</url>
			<pages>169205</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.169205</doi>
			<bibkey>Drysdale-2024-Hexachlorobenzene</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="24">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing, Volume 17</booktitle>
			<publisher>Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Potential of GNSS-R for the Monitoring of Lake Ice Phenology</title>
			<author>
				<first>Yusof</first>
				<last>Ghiasi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Claude</first>
				<last>Duguay</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Justin</first>
				<last>Murfitt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Milad</first>
				<last>Asgarimehr</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yuhao</first>
				<last>Wu</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>This study introduces the first use of Global Navigation Satellite System Reflectometry (GNSS-R) for monitoring lake ice phenology. This is demonstrated using Qinghai Lake, Tibetan Plateau, as a case study. Signal-to-Noise Ratio (SNR) values obtained from the Cyclone GNSS (CYGNSS) constellation over four ice seasons (2018 to 2022) were used to examine the impact of lake surface conditions on reflected GNSS signals during open water and ice cover seasons. A moving t-test algorithm was applied to time-varying SNR values allowing for the detection of lake ice at daily temporal resolution. Good agreement was achieved between ice phenology records derived from CYGNSS data and Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) imagery. The CYGNSS timings for freeze-up, i.e., the period starting with the first appearance of ice on the lake (freeze-up start; FUS) until the lake becomes fully ice covered (freeze-up end; FUE), as well as those for breakup, i.e., the period beginning with the first pixel of open water (breakup start; BUS) and ending when the whole lake becomes ice-free (breakup end; BUE), were validated against the phenology dates derived from MODIS images. Mean absolute errors are 7, 5, 10, 4 and 5 days for FUS, FUE, BUS, BUE and ice cover duration, respectively. Observations revealed the sensitivity of GNSS reflected signals to surface melt prior to the appearance of open water conditions as determined from MODIS, which explains the larger difference of 10 days for BUS.</abstract>
			<url hash="fd3579d7">G24-20001</url>
			<pages>660-673</pages>
			<doi>10.1109/jstars.2023.3330745</doi>
			<bibkey>Ghiasi-2024-Potential</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="25">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Ecosystems, Volume 27, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Response of Boreal Plant Communities and Forest Floor Carbon Fluxes to Experimental Nutrient Additions</title>
			<author>
				<first>Katherine M.</first>
				<last>Standen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Anastasia E.</first>
				<last>Sniderhan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Oliver</first>
				<last>Sonnentag</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Carolina</first>
				<last>Voigt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jennifer L.</first>
				<last>Baltzer</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="45891eb2">G24-21001</url>
			<pages>462-478</pages>
			<doi>10.1007/s10021-023-00899-1</doi>
			<bibkey>Standen-2024-Response</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="26">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Science of The Total Environment, Volume 908</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Seasonal controls on stream metal(loid) signatures in mountainous discontinuous permafrost</title>
			<author>
				<first>Elliott K.</first>
				<last>Skierszkan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sean K.</first>
				<last>Carey</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Scott I.</first>
				<last>Jackson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matthew</first>
				<last>Fellwock</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>C.</first>
				<last>Fraser</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matthew B.J.</first>
				<last>Lindsay</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="573cb15c">G24-22001</url>
			<pages>167999</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.167999</doi>
			<bibkey>Skierszkan-2024-Seasonal</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="27">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Geophysical Research Letters, Volume 51, Issue 8</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Geophysical Union (AGU)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Radiation, Air Temperature, and Soil Water Availability Drive Tree Water Deficit Across Temporal Scales in Canada's Western Boreal Forest</title>
			<author>
				<first>Nia</first>
				<last>Perron</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jennifer L.</first>
				<last>Baltzer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matteo</first>
				<last>Detto</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Magali F.</first>
				<last>Nehemy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Christopher</first>
				<last>Spence</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Gabriel</first>
				<last>Hould‐Gosselin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Haley</first>
				<last>Alcock</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bram</first>
				<last>Hadiwijaya</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Colin P.</first>
				<last>Laroque</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Oliver</first>
				<last>Sonnentag</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Changes are projected for the boreal biome with complex and variable effects on forest vegetation including drought‐induced tree mortality and forest loss. With soil and atmospheric conditions governing drought intensity, specific drivers of trees water stress can be difficult to disentangle across temporal scales. We used wavelet analysis and causality detection to identify potential environmental controls (evapotranspiration, soil moisture, rainfall, vapor pressure deficit, air temperature and photosynthetically active radiation) on daily tree water deficit and on longer periods of tree dehydration in black spruce and tamarack. Daily tree water deficit was controlled by photosynthetically active radiation, vapor pressure deficit, and air temperature, causing greater stand evapotranspiration. Prolonged periods of tree water deficit (multi‐day) were regulated by photosynthetically active radiation and soil moisture. We provide empirical evidence that continued warming and drying will cause short‐term increases in black spruce and tamarack transpiration, but greater drought stress with reduced soil water availability.</abstract>
			<url hash="ef80d639">G24-23001</url>
			<doi>10.1029/2023gl107477</doi>
			<bibkey>Perron-2024-Radiation,</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="28">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences, Volume 129, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Geophysical Union (AGU)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Albedo‐Induced Global Warming Potential Following Disturbances in Global Temperate and Boreal Forests</title>
			<author>
				<first>Qingsong</first>
				<last>Zhu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jiquan</first>
				<last>Chen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bourque Charles</first>
				<last>P.‐A.</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Oliver</first>
				<last>Sonnentag</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Leonardo</first>
				<last>Montagnani</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>T. L.</first>
				<last>O’Halloran</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Russell L.</first>
				<last>Scott</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jeremy</first>
				<last>Forsythe</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bo</first>
				<last>Song</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Huimin</first>
				<last>Zou</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Meihui</first>
				<last>Duan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Xianglan</first>
				<last>Li</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Forest disturbances can result in very different canopies that carry elevated albedo, thus causing substantial cooling effects on the climate. Unfortunately, the resulting dynamic global warming potential from altered albedo (GWP Δα ) is poorly understood. We examined and modeled the changes in albedo over time after disturbances (i.e., forest age) by forest type, disturbance type and geographic location using direct measurements from 107 sites in temperate and boreal regions. Albedo in undisturbed forests was used as the reference to calculate albedo changes (Δα) and GWP Δα after a disturbance. We found that age is a significant factor for predicting albedo amid the obvious regulations from forest type and geographic locations. We found the strongest cooling GWP Δα in the first 10 years after a disturbance, but it decreased rapidly with time. The changes in GWP Δα were very different from the chronosequence of net ecosystem production (NEP). In the first decade after disturbances, GWP Δα was negative (i.e., cooling) and surprisingly larger in magnitude, with an average of −0.609 kg CO 2 m −2 yr −1 , compared to NEP of −0.166 kg CO 2 m −2 yr −1 . Albedo continued to decrease and approached pre‐disturbance levels until around 50 years, resulting in a nearly zero GWP Δα . This research illustrates that many forests in temperate and boreal regions can be considered significant cooling agents by taking into account the high albedo of young forests following disturbances.</abstract>
			<url hash="7257ee80">G24-24001</url>
			<doi>10.1029/2023jg007848</doi>
			<bibkey>Zhu-2024-Albedo‐Induced</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
</collection>
