<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G15"><volume id="1"><meta><booktitle>Global Water Futures 2015</booktitle><publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher><address>Online</address><year>2015</year></meta><frontmatter><url hash="b97d2682">2015.GWF-1.0</url><bibkey>G15-2015-water</bibkey></frontmatter><paper id="1"><title>DAESA—A Matlab Tool for Structural Analysis of Differential-Algebraic Equations</title><author><first>J.</first><last>Pryce</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Nedialkov</last></author><author><first>Guangning</first><last>Tan</last></author><abstract>daesa, Differential-Algebraic Equations Structural Analyzer, is a Matlab tool for structural analysis of differential-algebraic equations (DAEs). It allows convenient translation of a DAE system into Matlab and provides a small set of easy-to-use functions. daesa can analyze systems that are fully nonlinear, high-index, and of any order. It determines structural index, number of degrees of freedom, constraints, variables to be initialized, and suggests a solution scheme. The structure of a DAE can be readily visualized by this tool. It also can construct a block-triangular form of the DAE, which can be exploited to solve it efficiently in a block-wise manner. This article describes the theory and algorithms underlying the code.</abstract><url hash="ce7a1614">2015.GWF-1.1</url><doi>10.1145/2689664</doi><bibkey>Pryce-etal-2015-DAESA—A</bibkey></paper><paper id="2"><title>Understanding failure to rescue and improving safety culture.</title><author><first>A.</first><last>Ghaferi</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Dimick</last></author><abstract>Although every hospital has surgical complications, the quality of the response to adverse events varies widely across institutions.1 A high quality response is essential to halt the potential transition from an initial serious complication to a progressive cascade of adverse occurrences that can lead to death, or “failure to rescue”. As most surgeons know, this tragic ending to a patient’s clinical trajectory is not abrupt or wholly unexpected. Instead, theses failures are preceded by a steady accumulation of small clinical clues. In this issue of Annals, Johnston and colleagues2 provide valuable insight into the process of recognizing these clues and the subsequent “escalation of care” using a method rarely applied in surgery—Healthcare Failure Mode and Effects Analysis (HFMEA). Escalation of care (EOC) is an apt term that the authors define as “the recognition and communication of patient deterioration to a senior colleague.” 
 
FMEA (without the H) is a technique for evaluating complex industrial or organizational processes. FMEA derives from the engineering community with principles that readily translate to the complex systems encountered by medical professionals. HFMEA (with the H) was born out of a need to tailor FMEA to a medical audience and resulted in utilizing components of several process evaluation tools, including root cause analysis (RCA). 
 
RCA has a very similar structure to HFMEA. It also involves a multi-step process that includes the formation of a multidisciplinary team, diagraming the general steps in a process, and gathering of data related to specific series of events to identify potential contributing factors, and ultimately developing and implementing an action plan. The use of historical data and events in RCA guide the understanding and development of changes to prevent adverse events. In contrast, HFMEA does not view a system retrospectively after an event, but examines a system for potential hazards prospectively. Because HFMEA does not have an event to draw upon, the identification of hazards relies mostly on the “end-user” or expert opinion to develop an understanding of potential vulnerabilities. Thus, RCA and HFMEA provide different views of how adverse events occur and are potentially prevented. Using actual historical events and decisions made at branch points in care may give RCA an advantage in the understanding and prevention of future events. 
 
Nonetheless, HFMEA has some advantages over RCA. It is explicitly aimed at the prevention of adverse events. Because HFMEA does not require a previous bad outcome or near miss, any system can be studied. Through the evaluation process, organizations can make these systems less vulnerable to failure. Finally, the method is “fault tolerant.” In other words HFMEA allows for minor errors or faults to occur in the system since such events may be inevitable and difficult to completely eliminate. Rather, it creates or reinforces a system that is responsive and less prone to recall bias or the fear of disclosure, embarrassment, blame, and punishment that can arise in the wake of an actual event. 
 
However, HFMEA clearly also has disadvantages. While this approach may prove fruitful for low risk, low complexity tasks such has hand hygiene, it is prone to significant blind spots. Using the Johari window cognitive psychology tool as an analogy (Fig. 1), the main area of greatest concern in the rescue process may be the surgical team’s blind spot, ie, the unknown quadrant in Figure 1. Unfortunately, sometimes a failure must occur before the steps or missteps leading to an adverse event can be identified, studied, and remedied. Therefore, the use of HFMEA and RCA together can provide an organization a more complete picture of dynamic, complex systems. While the authors present HFMEA as a prospective (and thus superior) approach to risk assessment over RCA, these methods are more accurately viewed as complementary, each with its own advantages and disadvantages. 
 
 
 
Figure 1 
 
The Johari Window 
 
 
 
Johnston and colleagues present a very thorough, well designed and executed evaluation of the EOC process in surgery using the HFMEA. They summarize their findings by citing communication technology, understaffing, and hierarchy as key drivers of escalation of care. As noted by the authors, these findings are well known and consistent with prior literature regarding how medical teams should respond to these events.2 To summarize the authors’ findings, we view their recommended interventions for improving escalation of care in three distinct buckets. First, there are structural components that require improvement or modification of existing systems. Examples from this study include the need for more permanent or experienced staff members on the wards or improvement in technology for the medical record or methods to enhance communication (ie, mobile phones). These interventions require significant capital investment and may take time to purchase and implement. However, these are already well-known contributors to good patient care. 
 
Second, there are several improvements to processes of care recommended by the study participants. Specific examples from this study include development of escalation protocols or establishing explicit physiologic parameter thresholds to ensure the patient is receiving the appropriate levels of care. These interventions rely on some evidence and mostly expert opinion. However, as we have seen with other process measures or interventions, such as checklists, these are prone to user fatigue as providers return to their previous habits and practices. 
 
Third, and potentially most important, is the culture of the organization and its members. As many have said before, “culture eats strategy for breakfast”. The present study hints at several recommendations related to safety culture, but falls short of emphasizing this as the key element to achieving improvements in rescue. A safe culture is the foundation on which aspects of organizational structure and processes of care can be built to promote more effective rescue. For example, investing in education for nurses to detect deteriorating patients or disseminating escalation protocols are only as effective as the unit or organization’s willingness to learn, implement, and adapt. 
 
What is culture? And what does a safe culture look like? Culture refers to the shared, often unconscious attitudes and standards that govern behavior, especially in crisis situations that lack clearly defined pathways or processes. To better understand culture, one can think of it as the forces in an organization that operate in the background. These forces are shaped by the organization’s values, beliefs, traditions, norms, and even myths. Paradoxically, an organization’s culture is simultaneously nearly impossible to measure but an understanding of it is absolutely essential to change the organization. 
 
Traditionally, qualitative methods, such as interviews, focus groups, or ethnography, have been employed to study culture. This requires an appreciation for the unique aspects of individual social settings and the nuances of the interactions between the levels of hierarchy over time. In order to change organizational safety culture and climate, healthcare leaders, practitioners, and researchers will need to move from the current “blame and shame” in the face of medical errors to an enriched progressive culture where errors are recognized as learning opportunities to better the organization. 
 
Extensive research into the approach to supporting a positive safety culture have resulted in the following key organizational commitments—to construct reliable systems and processes, to support and encourage error reporting with an open and just culture, to embrace management practices and behaviors supportive of safety, and to detect and analyze errors and adverse events with robust investigation.3–5 This final commitment lends itself to some well-established methods for quality improvement, such as FMEA or RCA, which have begun to penetrate healthcare systems. 
 
There are only a few rigorous examples of effectively changing culture to improve practice. Probably the most well-known and studied example of cultural change improving clinical outcomes is the Johns Hopkins Comprehensive Unit Based Safety Program (CUSP). Developed and pioneered by Peter Pronovost, CUSP evolved through literature review, discussion with experts, trial, and adaptation. The goal of this program was to create a safety program with several goals—it could be implemented sequentially in work units, would improve the culture of safety, would allow staff to focus safety efforts on unit-specific problems, and would include rigorous data collection that could be disseminated beyond the study setting.6 It has since been implemented in several large-scale quality improvement initiatives. However, while CUSP has been applied broadly, its effectiveness outside the ICU and specifically in the context of complication rescue or escalation of care is unknown. 
 
Ultimately, improvements in surgical safety will require significant work in measuring culture, designing cultural improvement initiatives, and implementing change through continuous and rigorous engagement. Johnston et al have provided an important first step in that direction, but significant work remains in order to identify high leverage targets and implement widespread efforts to transform units towards a culture that better supports appropriate and timely escalation of care and improves the rescue of patients from postoperative complications.</abstract><url hash="577347ae">2015.GWF-1.2</url><doi>10.1097/SLA.0000000000001135</doi><bibkey>Ghaferi-etal-2015-Understanding</bibkey></paper><paper id="3"><title>All Farmers’ Risks Are Below Average</title><author><first>J.</first><last>May</last></author><abstract>Just down (or is it up?) the road from Marshfield, WI, lies the mythical town of Lake Woebegone, where, famously, “all the children are above average.” The situation is just the opposite for health and safety in the workplace. All workers (including farmers) are below average—at least in terms of their perception of risk.1 Optimistic bias is the phenomenon by which individuals believe themselves less likely to be harmed by negative events as compared to others. It is, in short, the belief that bad things will happen to other people. This view appears to be situational – it does not apply for any given individual in all instances. If optimistic bias is not universal, it certainly is a common aspect of the human condition, ranging across ages, genders, education levels, occupations, and cultures. Since first being described in the 1980s,2 there have been literally hundreds of studies of “comparative optimism” influencing peoples’ perception of personal risk in myriad situations. Japanese students, bungee jumpers, sex workers, male drivers, smokers, drinkers, eaters, and sun tanners all find ways to exempt themselves from generally recognized risks. And farmers. Sorensen et al. found optimistic bias to be one of the most consistent barriers encountered during in-depth explorations of farmers’ decisions not to retrofit vulnerable tractors with rollover protective structures.3 Subsequent discussions of power takeoff shielding also revealed evidence of comparative optimism influencing farmers’ view of risk and related decisions.4 While it appears to be a barrier to some desirable safety behaviors, optimistic bias is also acknowledged to be a mechanism for selfenhancement and self-defense. It may serve to protect self-esteem and guard against depression and anxiety. In some situations optimistic expectations were associated with positive attitudes, positive mood, an elevated sense of control, reduced anxiety, increased attention to risk information, and engagement in more healthpromoting behaviors. Thus, optimistic bias is best viewed as a two-edged sword. In addition to its ego-enhancing effects, this unrealistic optimism can be maladaptive and associated with less attentive processing of risk information and reduced motivation to change risky behaviors. For a phenomenon that has been extensively studied and reported, a great deal of uncertainty remains about optimistic bias. Some argue that the methods for measuring optimistic bias, estimating one’s personal risk and then estimating the risk of others, can be powerfully influenced by statistical artifact.5 Many have found little evidence of demographic proclivities for optimistic bias, while others feel that better educated persons, males—particularly older males—may experience more such bias (depending upon the risk being explored). Because nearly all studies have been cross-sectional there is limited understanding of the resilience of optimistic bias. Does it wax and wane or is it consistent over time? The few longitudinal studies (on hurricanes and H1N1 influenza in Korea) suggest that, once adopted, optimistic bias for a given risk is a robust and resilient phenomenon. While it may be moderated by recent experience, this is typically a transient reduction with the bias returning to pre-event levels rather quickly.6 As noted by Harris and colleagues, the degree of such optimism varies within and across both events and people for reasons that are still being</abstract><url hash="20747738">2015.GWF-1.3</url><doi>10.1080/1059924X.2015.1000096</doi><bibkey>May-etal-2015-All</bibkey></paper><paper id="4"><title>A Novel Statistical Channel Model for Turbulence-Induced Fading in Free-Space Optical Systems</title><author><first>M.</first><last>A. Kashani</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Uysal</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Kavehrad</last></author><abstract>In this paper, we propose a new probability distribution function which accurately describes turbulence-induced fading under a wide range of turbulence conditions. The proposed model, termed double-generalized gamma (double GG), is based on a doubly stochastic theory of scintillation and developed via the product of two generalized gamma distributions. The proposed double GG distribution generalizes many existing turbulence channel models and provides an excellent fit to the published plane and spherical waves simulation data. Using this new statistical channel model, we derive closed form expressions for the outage probability and the average bit error as well as corresponding asymptotic expressions of free-space optical communication systems over turbulence channels. We demonstrate that our derived expressions cover many existing results in the literature earlier reported for gamma-gamma, double-Weibull and K channels as special cases.</abstract><url hash="be10e29b">2015.GWF-1.4</url><doi>10.1109/JLT.2015.2410695</doi><bibkey>A. Kashani-etal-2015-A</bibkey></paper><paper id="5"><title>Evaluation of the risk factors contributing to the African swine fever occurrence in Sardinia, Italy</title><author><first>B.</first><last>Martínez-López</last></author><author><first>Andrés</first><last>Perez</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Feliziani</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Rolesu</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Mur</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Sánchez-Vizcaíno</last></author><abstract>This study assesses the relation between hypothesized risk factors and African swine fever virus (ASFV) distribution in Sardinia (Italy) after the beginning of the eradication program in 1993, using a Bayesian multivariable logistic regression mixed model. Results indicate that the probability of ASFV occurrence in Sardinia was associated to particular socio-cultural, productive and economical factors found in the region, particularly to large number of confined (i.e., closed) farms (most of them backyard), high road density, high mean altitude, large number of open fattening farms, and large number of pigs per commune. Conversely, large proportion of open farms with at least one census and large proportion of open farms per commune, were found to be protective factors for ASFV. Results suggest that basic preventive and control strategies, such as yearly census or registration of the pigs per farm and better control of the public lands where pigs are usually raised, together with endanced effords of outreach and communication with pig producers should help in the success of the eradication program for ASF in the Island. Methods and results presented here will inform decision making to better control and eradicate ASF in Sardinia and in all those areas with similar management and epidemiological conditions.</abstract><url hash="c917d20d">2015.GWF-1.5</url><doi>10.3389/fmicb.2015.00314</doi><bibkey>Martínez-López-etal-2015-Evaluation</bibkey></paper><paper id="6"><title>The potential of water markets to allocate water between industry, agriculture, and public water utilities as an adaptation mechanism to climate change</title><author><first>Jason</first><last>F. L. Koopman</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Kuik</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Tol</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Brouwer</last></author><abstract /><url hash="501e83b7">2015.GWF-1.6</url><doi>10.1007/s11027-015-9662-z</doi><bibkey>F. L. Koopman-etal-2015-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="7"><title>Variance Based Global Sensitivity Analysis for Uncorrelated and Correlated Inputs With Gaussian Processes</title><author><first>Ankur</first><last>Srivastava</last></author><author><first>Arun</first><last>K. Subramaniyan</last></author><author><first>Liping</first><last>Wang</last></author><abstract>Methods for efficient variance based global sensitivity analysis of complex high-dimensional problems are presented and compared. Variance decomposition methods rank inputs according to Sobol indices which can be computationally expensive to evaluate. Main and interaction effect Sobol indices can be computed efficiently in the Kennedy &amp; O’Hagan framework with Gaussian Processes (GPs). These methods use the High Dimensional Model Representation (HDMR) concept for variance decomposition which presents a unique model representation when inputs are uncorrelated. However, when the inputs are correlated, multiple model representations may be possible leading to ambiguous sensitivity ranking with Sobol indices. In this work we present the effect of input correlation on sensitivity analysis and discuss the methods presented by Li &amp; Rabitz in the context of Kennedy &amp; O’ Hagan framework with GPs. Results are demonstrated on simulated and real problems for correlated and uncorrelated inputs and demonstrate the utility of variance decomposition methods for sensitivity analysis.Copyright © 2015 by ASME</abstract><url hash="2719b321">2015.GWF-1.7</url><doi>10.1115/GT2015-43693</doi><bibkey>Srivastava-etal-2015-Variance</bibkey></paper></volume></collection>