<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G16">
	<volume id="1">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Climate Dynamics, Volume 48, Issue 7-8</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Future changes to drought characteristics over the Canadian Prairie Provinces based on NARCCAP multi-RCM ensemble</title>
			<author>
				<first>M. B.</first>
				<last>Masud</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>M. N.</first>
				<last>Khaliq</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>H. S.</first>
				<last>Wheater</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>This study assesses projected changes to drought characteristics in Alberta, Saskatchewan and Manitoba, the prairie provinces of Canada, using a multi-regional climate model (RCM) ensemble available through the North American Regional Climate Change Assessment Program. Simulations considered include those performed with six RCMs driven by National Center for Environmental Prediction reanalysis II for the 1981–2003 period and those driven by four Atmosphere–Ocean General Circulation Models for the 1970–1999 and 2041–2070 periods (i.e. eleven current and the same number of corresponding future period simulations). Drought characteristics are extracted using two drought indices, namely the Standardized Precipitation Index (SPI) and the Standardized Precipitation Evapotranspiration Index (SPEI). Regional frequency analysis is used to project changes to selected 20- and 50-year regional return levels of drought characteristics for fifteen homogeneous regions, covering the study area. In addition, multivariate analyses of drought characteristics, derived on the basis of 6-month SPI and SPEI values, are developed using the copula approach for each region. Analysis of multi-RCM ensemble-averaged projected changes to mean and selected return levels of drought characteristics show increases over the southern and south-western parts of the study area. Based on bi- and trivariate joint occurrence probabilities of drought characteristics, the southern regions along with the central regions are found highly drought vulnerable, followed by the southwestern and southeastern regions. Compared to the SPI-based analysis, the results based on SPEI suggest drier conditions over many regions in the future, indicating potential effects of rising temperatures on drought risks. These projections will be useful in the development of appropriate adaptation strategies for the water and agricultural sectors, which play an important role in the economy of the study area.</abstract>
			<url hash="4178f9e3">G16-1001</url>
			<pages>2685-2705</pages>
			<doi>10.1007/s00382-016-3232-2</doi>
			<bibkey>Masud-2016-Future</bibkey>
			<project>prj2</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="2">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Climate Dynamics, Volume 49, Issue 5-6</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Projected changes to short- and long-duration precipitation extremes over the Canadian Prairie Provinces</title>
			<author>
				<first>M. B.</first>
				<last>Masud</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>M. N.</first>
				<last>Khaliq</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>H. S.</first>
				<last>Wheater</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The effects of climate change on April–October short- and long-duration precipitation extremes over the Canadian Prairie Provinces were evaluated using a multi-Regional Climate Model (RCM) ensemble available through the North American Regional Climate Change Assessment Program. Simulations considered include those performed with six RCMs driven by the National Centre for Environmental Prediction (NCEP) reanalysis II product for the 1981–2000 period and those driven by four Atmosphere–Ocean General Circulation Models (AOGCMs) for the current 1971–2000 and future 2041–2070 periods (i.e. a total of 11 current-to-future period simulation pairs). A regional frequency analysis approach was used to develop 2-, 5-, 10-, 25-, and 50-year return values of precipitation extremes from NCEP and AOGCM-driven current and future period simulations that respectively were used to study the performance of RCMs and projected changes for selected return values at regional, grid-cell and local scales. Performance errors due to internal dynamics and physics of RCMs studied for the 1981–2000 period reveal considerable variation in the performance of the RCMs. However, the performance errors were found to be much smaller for RCM ensemble averages than for individual RCMs. Projected changes in future climate to selected regional return values of short-duration (e.g. 15- and 30-min) precipitation extremes and for longer return periods (e.g. 50-year) were found to be mostly larger than those to the longer duration (e.g. 24- and 48-h) extremes and short return periods (e.g. 2-year). Overall, projected changes in precipitation extremes were larger for southeastern regions followed by southern and northern regions and smaller for southwestern and western regions of the study area. The changes to return values were also found to be statistically significant for the majority of the RCM–AOGCM simulation pairs. These projections might be useful as a key input for the future planning of urban drainage infrastructure and development of strategic climate change adaptation measures.</abstract>
			<url hash="53cd560d">G16-2001</url>
			<pages>1597-1616</pages>
			<doi>10.1007/s00382-016-3404-0</doi>
			<bibkey>Masud-2016-Projected</bibkey>
			<project>prj2</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="3">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrology Research, Volume 48, Issue 4</booktitle>
			<publisher>IWA Publishing</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>The significance of spatial variability of rainfall on simulated runoff: an evaluation based on the Upper Lee catchment, UK</title>
			<author>
				<first>Ilias</first>
				<last>Pechlivanidis</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Neil</first>
				<last>McIntyre</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>H. S.</first>
				<last>Wheater</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The significance of spatial variability of rainfall on runoff is explored as a function of catchment scale and type, and antecedent conditions via the continuous time, semi-distributed probability distributed model (PDM) hydrological model applied to the Upper Lee catchment, UK. The impact of catchment scale and type is assessed using 11 nested catchments, and further assessed by artificially changing the catchment characteristics and translating these to model parameters (MPs) with uncertainty using model regionalisation. Dry and wet antecedent conditions are represented by ‘warming up’ the model under different rainfall time series. Synthetic rainfall events are introduced to directly relate the change in simulated runoff to the spatial variability of rainfall. Results show that runoff volume and peak are more sensitive to the spatial rainfall for more impermeable catchments; however, this sensitivity is significantly undermined under wet antecedent conditions. Although there is indication that the impact of spatial rainfall on runoff varies as a function of catchment scale, the variability of antecedent conditions between the synthetic catchments seems to mask this significance. Parameter uncertainty analysis highlights the importance of accurately representing the spatial variability of the catchment properties and their translation to MPs when investigating the effects of spatial properties of rainfall on runoff.</abstract>
			<url hash="eb713168">G16-3001</url>
			<pages>1118-1130</pages>
			<doi>10.2166/nh.2016.038</doi>
			<bibkey>Pechlivanidis-2016-The</bibkey>
			<project>prj2</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="4">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Ecosystems, Volume 20, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Losing Legacies, Ecological Release, and Transient Responses: Key Challenges for the Future of Northern Ecosystem Science</title>
			<author>
				<first>M. R.</first>
				<last>Turetsky</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jennifer L.</first>
				<last>Baltzer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jill F.</first>
				<last>Johnstone</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michelle C.</first>
				<last>Mack</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kevin S.</first>
				<last>McCann</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Edward A. G.</first>
				<last>Schuur</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Northern ecosystem processes play out across scales that are rare elsewhere on contemporary earth: large ranging predator–prey systems are still operational, invasive species are rare, and large-scale natural disturbances occur extensively. Disturbances in the far north affect huge areas of land and are difficult to control or manage. Historically, disturbance patterns and processes ranging across a number of spatio-temporal scales have played an important role in the resilience of northern ecosystems. However, due to interactions with a warming climate, these disturbances are now erasing key legacies of the last millennia of ecosystem processes. Building on the concepts of legacies and cross-scale interactions, we highlight several general conceptual issues that represent key challenges for the future of northern ecosystem science, but that also have relevance to other biomes.</abstract>
			<url hash="76a609d1">G16-4001</url>
			<pages>23-30</pages>
			<doi>10.1007/s10021-016-0055-2</doi>
			<bibkey>Turetsky-2016-Losing</bibkey>
			<project>prj1</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="5">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrological Processes, Volume 30, Issue 17</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>The cold rain-on-snow event of June 2013 in the Canadian Rockies - characteristics and diagnosis</title>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Xing</first>
				<last>Fang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Danny</first>
				<last>Marks</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The June 2013 flood in the Canadian Rockies featured rain‐on‐snow (ROS) runoff generation at alpine elevations that contributed to the high streamflows observed during the event. Such a mid‐summer ROS event has not been diagnosed in detail, and a diagnosis may help to understand future high discharge‐producing hydrometeorological events in mountainous cold regions. The alpine hydrology of the flood was simulated using a physically based model created with the modular cold regions hydrological modelling platform. The event was distinctive in that, although at first, relatively warm rain fell onto existing snowdrifts inducing ROS melt; the rainfall turned to snowfall as the air mass cooled and so increased snowcover and snowpacks in alpine regions, which then melted rapidly from ground heat fluxes in the latter part of the event. Melt rates of existing snowpacks were substantially lower during the ROS than during the relatively sunny periods preceding and following the event as a result of low wind speeds, cloud cover and cool temperatures. However, at the basin scale, melt volumes increased during the event as a result of increased snowcover from the fresh snowfall and consequent large ground heat contributions to melt energy, causing snowmelt to enhance rainfall–runoff by one fifth. Flow pathways also shifted during the event from relatively slow sub‐surface flow prior to the flood to an even contribution from sub‐surface and fast overland flow during and immediately after the event. This early summer, high precipitation ROS event was distinctive for the impact of decreased solar irradiance in suppressing melt rates, the contribution of ground heat flux to basin scale snowmelt after precipitation turned to snowfall, the transition from slow sub‐surface to fast overland flow runoff as the sub‐surface storage saturated and streamflow volumes that exceeded precipitation. These distinctions show that summer, mountain ROS events should be considered quite distinct from winter ROS and can be important contributors to catastrophic events. Copyright © 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</abstract>
			<url hash="4178f9e3">G16-1001</url>
			<pages>2899-2914</pages>
			<doi>10.1002/hyp.10905</doi>
			<bibkey>Pomeroy-2016-The</bibkey>
			<project>prj3</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="6">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrological Processes, Volume 30, Issue 26</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>The June 2013 Alberta Catastrophic Flooding Event: Part 1-Climatological aspects and hydrometeorological features</title>
			<author>
				<first>Anling</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Curtis</first>
				<last>Mooney</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kit K.</first>
				<last>Szeto</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Julie M.</first>
				<last>Thériault</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bohdan</first>
				<last>Kochtubajda</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ronald E.</first>
				<last>Stewart</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sudesh</first>
				<last>Boodoo</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ron</first>
				<last>Goodson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yanping</first>
				<last>Li</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>In June 2013, excessive rainfall associated with an intense weather system triggered severe flooding in southern Alberta, which became the costliest natural disaster in Canadian history. This article provides an overview of the climatological aspects and large-scale hydrometeorological features associated with the flooding event based upon information from a variety of sources, including satellite data, upper air soundings, surface observations and operational model analyses. The results show that multiple factors combined to create this unusually severe event. The event was characterized by a slow-moving upper level low pressure system west of Alberta, blocked by an upper level ridge, while an associated well-organized surface low pressure system kept southern Alberta, especially the eastern slopes of the Rocky Mountains, in continuous precipitation for up to two days. Results from air parcel trajectory analysis show that a significant amount of the moisture originated from the central Great Plains, transported into Alberta by a southeasterly low level jet. The event was first dominated by significant thunderstorm activity, and then evolved into continuous precipitation supported by the synoptic-scale low pressure system. Both the thunderstorm activity and upslope winds associated with the low pressure system produced large rainfall amounts. A comparison with previous similar events occurring in the same region suggests that the synoptic-scale features associated with the 2013 rainfall event were not particularly intense; however, its storm environment was the most convectively unstable. The system also exhibited a relatively high freezing level, which resulted in rain, rather than snow, mainly falling over the still snow-covered mountainous areas. Melting associated with this rain-on-snow scenario likely contributed to downstream flooding. Furthermore, above-normal snowfall in the preceding spring helped to maintain snow in the high-elevation areas, which facilitated the rain-on-snow event.</abstract>
			<url hash="53cd560d">G16-2001</url>
			<pages>4899-4916</pages>
			<doi>10.1002/hyp.10906</doi>
			<bibkey>Liu-2016-The</bibkey>
			<project>prj2</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="7">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrological Processes, Volume 30, Issue 16</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Impact of antecedent conditions on simulations of a flood in a mountain headwater basin</title>
			<author>
				<first>Xing</first>
				<last>Fang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>A devastating flood struck Southern Alberta in late June 2013, with much of its streamflow generation in the Front Ranges of the Rocky Mountains, west of Calgary. To better understand streamflow generation processes and their sensitivity to initial conditions, a physically based hydrological model was developed using the Cold Regions Hydrological Modelling platform (CRHM) to simulate the flood for the Marmot Creek Research Basin (~9.4 km2). The modular model includes major cold and warm season hydrological processes including snow redistribution, sublimation, melt, runoff over frozen and unfrozen soils, evapotranspiration, subsurface runoff on hillslopes, groundwater recharge and discharge and streamflow routing. Uncalibrated simulations were conducted for eight hydrological years and generally matched streamflow observations well, with a NRMSD of 52%, small model bias (−3%) and a Nash–Sutcliffe efficiency (NSE) of 0.71. The model was then used to diagnose the responses of hydrological processes in 2013 flood from different ecozones in Marmot Creek: alpine, treeline, montane forest and large and small forest clearings to better understand spatial variations in the flood runoff generation mechanisms. To examine the sensitivity to antecedent conditions, ‘virtual’ flood simulations were conducted using a week (17 to 24 June 2013) of flood meteorology imposed on the meteorology of the same period in other years (2005 to 2012), or switched with the meteorology of one week in different months (May to July) of 2013. Sensitivity to changing precipitation and land cover was assessed by varying the precipitation amount during the flood and forest cover and soil storage capacity in forest ecozone. The results show that runoff efficiency increases rapidly with antecedent snowpack and soil moisture storage with the highest runoff response to rainfall from locations in the basin where there are recently melted or actively melting snowpacks and resulting high soil moisture or frozen soils. The impact of forest canopy on flooding is negligible, but flood peak doubles if forest canopy removal is accompanied by 50% reduction in water storage capacity in the basin. Copyright © 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</abstract>
			<url hash="eb713168">G16-3001</url>
			<pages>2754-2772</pages>
			<doi>10.1002/hyp.10910</doi>
			<bibkey>Fang-2016-Impact</bibkey>
			<project>prj3</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="8">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Earth Sciences, Volume 75, Issue 17</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Description of current and future snow processes in a small basin in the Bavarian Alps</title>
			<author>
				<first>Michael</first>
				<last>Weber</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matthias</first>
				<last>Bernhardt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Xing</first>
				<last>Fang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stefan</first>
				<last>Härer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Karsten</first>
				<last>Schulz</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Snow cover dynamics in alpine regions play a crucial role in view of the water balance of head water catchments. The temporal storage of water in form of snow and ice leads to a decoupling of precipitation and runoff. Changes in the volume and the temporal dynamics of the snow storage lead to modified runoff regimes and can influence the frequency of low flow events and floods. For a better estimation of the possible range and direction of future changes, projection runs can be realized by using process-based models. In this study, the Cold Regions Hydrological Modelling platform (CRHM) is used to compile such a model for simulating the snow cover development within research catchment Zugspitze (RCZ; 11.4 km2/Germany). Therefore, the catchment is divided into four hydrological response units (HRUs), able to cover the physiographic characteristics in four elevation zones. The model is evaluated over snow depth measurements. The range of variability within and differences between the HRUs are analyzed, and future projections (2001–2100) are performed on the basis of three different WETTREG realizations. It could be shown that CRHM is able to reproduce the snow cover dynamics very well and that the ongoing climate change does have an identifiable influence on the average extent and size of the snow storage. Furthermore, it could be shown that variations in snow cover dynamics within the RCZ are strongly connected to NAO.</abstract>
			<url hash="76a609d1">G16-4001</url>
			<doi>10.1007/s12665-016-6027-1</doi>
			<bibkey>Weber-2016-Description</bibkey>
			<project>prj3</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="9">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Hydrometeorology, Volume 17, Issue 8</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Meteorological Society</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Aerodynamic and Radiative Controls on the Snow Surface Temperature</title>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Richard</first>
				<last>Essery</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Warren</first>
				<last>Helgason</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract The snow surface temperature (SST) is essential for estimating longwave radiation fluxes from snow. SST can be diagnosed using finescale multilayer snow physics models that track changes in snow properties and internal energy; however, these models are heavily parameterized, have high predictive uncertainty, and require continuous simulation to estimate prognostic state variables. Here, a relatively simple model to estimate SST that is not reliant on prognostic state variables is proposed. The model assumes that the snow surface is poorly connected thermally to the underlying snowpack and largely transparent for most of the shortwave radiation spectrum, such that a snow surface energy balance among only sensible heat, latent heat, longwave radiation, and near-infrared radiation is possible and is called the radiative psychrometric model (RPM). The RPM SST is sensitive to air temperature, humidity, ventilation, and longwave irradiance and is secondarily affected by absorption of near-infrared radiation at the snow surface that was higher where atmospheric deposition of particulates was more likely to be higher. The model was implemented with neutral stability, an implicit windless exchange coefficient, and constant shortwave absorption factors and aerodynamic roughness lengths. It was evaluated against radiative SST measurements from the Canadian Prairies and Rocky Mountains, French Alps, and Bolivian Andes. With optimized and global shortwave absorption and aerodynamic roughness length parameters, the model is shown to accurately predict SST under a wide range of conditions, providing superior predictions when compared to air temperature, dewpoint, or ice bulb calculation approaches.</abstract>
			<url hash="ce1a6eb4">G16-5001</url>
			<pages>2175-2189</pages>
			<doi>10.1175/jhm-d-15-0226.1</doi>
			<bibkey>Pomeroy-2016-Aerodynamic</bibkey>
			<project>prj3</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="10">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>The Forestry Chronicle, Volume 92, Issue 01</booktitle>
			<publisher>Canadian Institute of Forestry</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Marmot Creek Experimental Watershed Study</title>
			<author>
				<first>R. L.</first>
				<last>Rothwell</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Graham R.</first>
				<last>Hillman</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The origins and results of the scientific experiments in Marmot Creek Experimental Watershed, now the Marmot Creek Research Basin, over more than 50 years are reviewed. Marmot Creek was established to better understand how forest manipulations could be used to manage streamflow hydrographs and was actively manipulated in the 1970s and 1980s. While small forest clearings were shown to increase snow accumulation consistently, the impacts on melt rates depended on clearing size, slope and aspect. As a result, clearing treatments whether through large cutblocks or small clearings had modest impacts on the hydrograph timing and variability and only local impacts on streamflow volume. Changes in climate are primarily manifested as warming which has substantially reduced snowpacks at low elevations. These climate changes have not been evident in hydrograph change and there is no trend to volumes or timing of streamflow over the last 50 years. Overall the basin shows remarkable resiliency to climate and land use change due to its wide range of elevations, slopes, snow environments and sub-surface storage. The basin has become a hydrological process observatory where multi-scale models are developed and evaluated for operation over larger areas. It has served an invaluable role for this and the scientific results from Marmot Creek have supported the development of global climate models and hydrological models that are now applied throughout the world.</abstract>
			<url hash="dcafc15a">G16-6001</url>
			<pages>32-36</pages>
			<doi>10.5558/tfc2016-010</doi>
			<bibkey>Rothwell-2016-Marmot</bibkey>
			<project>prj3</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
</collection>