<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G16"><volume id="1"><meta><booktitle>Global Water Futures 2016</booktitle><publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher><address>Online</address><year>2016</year></meta><frontmatter><url hash="80f01a47">2016.GWF-1.0</url><bibkey>G16-2016-water</bibkey></frontmatter><paper id="1"><title>OpenTrials: towards a collaborative open database of all available information on all clinical trials</title><author><first>B.</first><last>Goldacre</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Gray</last></author><abstract /><url hash="f7f72ad1">2016.GWF-1.1</url><doi>10.1186/s13063-016-1290-8</doi><bibkey>Goldacre-etal-2016-OpenTrials:</bibkey></paper><paper id="2"><title>Response of understory vegetation to salvage logging following a high‐severity wildfire</title><author><first>E.</first><last>Knapp</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Ritchie</last></author><abstract>Timber is frequently salvage-logged following high-severity stand-replacing wildfire, but the practice is controversial. One concern is that compound disturbances could result in more deleterious impacts than either disturbance individually, with mechanical operations having the potential to set back recovering native species and increase invasion by non-native species. Following the 2002 Cone Fire on the Lassen National Forest, three replicates of five salvage treatments were applied to 15 units formerly dominated by ponderosa pine, covering a range of disturbance intensities from unsalvaged to 100% salvaged. Understory species richness and cover data were collected every two years between 2006 and 2012. Richness of both native and non-native species did not differ among salvage treatments, but both showed strong changes over time. While cover of forbs and graminoids did not differ with salvage treatment, cover of shrubs was significantly reduced at the higher salvage intensities. The three main shrub species are all stimulated to germinate by fire, potentially leaving seedlings vulnerable to any mechanical disturbance occurring immediately postgermination. Many other native perennial species emerge from rhizomes or other deeply buried underground structures and appear to be less affected by salvage harvest. Over time, the plant community in all salvage treatments shifted from dominance by shrubs and forbs to shrubs and grasses. Most of the grasses were native, except Bromus tectorum (cheatgrass), which was found in 4% of measurement quadrats in 2006 and 52% in 2012. Our results indicated that understory vegetation change 4–10 years posthigh-severity wildfire appeared to be influenced more strongly by factors other than salvage logging.</abstract><url hash="6efe7b6b">2016.GWF-1.2</url><doi>10.1002/ECS2.1550</doi><bibkey>Knapp-etal-2016-Response</bibkey></paper><paper id="3"><title>The fan of influence of streams and channel feedbacks to simulated land surface water and carbon dynamics</title><author><first>Chaopeng</first><last>Shen</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Riley</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Smithgall</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Melack</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Fang</last></author><abstract>Large‐scale land models assume unidirectional land‐to‐river hydrological interactions, without considering feedbacks between channels and land. Using a tested, physically based model with explicit multiway interactions between overland, channel, wetland, and groundwater flows, we assessed how the representation and properties of channels influence simulated land surface hydrologic, biogeochemical, and ecosystem dynamics. A zone near the channels where various fluxes and states are significantly influenced by the channels, referred to as the fan of influence (FoI) of channels, has been identified. We elucidated two mechanisms inducing the model‐derived FoI: the base flow mechanism, in which incised, gaining streams lower the water table and induce more base flow, and the relatively more efficient conveyance of the channel network compared to overland flow. We systematically varied drainage density and grid resolution to quantify the size of the FoI, which is found to span a large fraction of the watershed (25–50%) for hydrologic variables including depth to water table and recharge, etc. The FoI is more pronounced with low‐resolution simulations but remains noticeable in hyperresolution (25 m) subbasin simulations. The FoI and the channel influence on basin‐average fluxes are also similar in simulations with alternative parameter sets. We found that high‐order, entrenched streams cause larger FoI. In addition, removing the simulated channels has disproportionally large influence on modeled wetland areas and inundation duration, which has implications for coupled biogeochemical or ecological modeling. Our results suggest that explicit channel representation provides important feedbacks to land surface dynamics which should be considered in meso or large‐scale simulations. Since grid refinement incurs prohibitive computational cost, subgrid channel parameterization has advantages in efficiency over grid‐based representations that do not distinguish between overland flow and channel flow.</abstract><url hash="19f94bfd">2016.GWF-1.3</url><doi>10.1002/2015WR018086</doi><bibkey>Shen-etal-2016-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="4"><title>A Numerical Study of the June 2013 Flood-Producing Extreme Rainstorm over Southern Alberta</title><author><first>Yanping</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Szeto</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Stewart</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Thériault</last></author><author><first>Liang</first><last>Chen</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Kochtubajda</last></author><author><first>Anthony</first><last>K. Liu</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Boodoo</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Goodson</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Mooney</last></author><author><first>Sopan</first><last>Kurkute</last></author><abstract>AbstractA devastating, flood-producing rainstorm occurred over southern Alberta, Canada, from 19 to 22 June 2013. The long-lived, heavy rainfall event was a result of complex interplays between topographic, synoptic, and convective processes that rendered an accurate simulation of this event a challenging task. In this study, the Weather Research and Forecasting (WRF) Model was used to simulate this event and was validated against several observation datasets. Both the timing and location of the model precipitation agree closely with the observations, indicating that the WRF Model is capable of reproducing this type of severe event. Sensitivity tests with different microphysics schemes were conducted and evaluated using equitable threat and bias frequency scores. The WRF double-moment 6-class microphysics scheme (WDM6) generally performed better when compared with other schemes. The application of a conventional convective/stratiform separation algorithm shows that convective activity was dominant during ...</abstract><url hash="879dde5e">2016.GWF-1.4</url><doi>10.1175/JHM-D-15-0176.1</doi><bibkey>Li-etal-2016-A</bibkey></paper><paper id="5"><title>Losing Legacies, Ecological Release, and Transient Responses: Key Challenges for the Future of Northern Ecosystem Science</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Turetsky</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Baltzer</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Johnstone</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Mack</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>McCann</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Schuur</last></author><abstract /><url hash="f09aeec8">2016.GWF-1.5</url><doi>10.1007/s10021-016-0055-2</doi><bibkey>Turetsky-etal-2016-Losing</bibkey></paper><paper id="6"><title>Time lags in watershed-scale nutrient transport: an exploration of dominant controls</title><author><first>K.</first><last>V. Van Meter</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Basu</last></author><abstract>Unprecedented decreases in atmospheric nitrogen (N) deposition together with increases in agricultural N-use efficiency have led to decreases in net anthropogenic N inputs in many eastern US and Canadian watersheds as well as in Europe. Despite such decreases, N concentrations in streams and rivers continue to increase, and problems of coastal eutrophication remain acute. Such a mismatch between N inputs and outputs can arise due to legacy N accumulation and subsequent lag times between implementation of conservation measures and improvements in water quality. In the present study, we quantified such lag times by pairing long-term N input trajectories with stream nitrate concentration data for 16 nested subwatersheds in a 6800 km2, Southern Ontario watershed. Our results show significant nonlinearity between N inputs and outputs, with a strong hysteresis effect indicative of decadal-scale lag times. The mean annual lag time was found to be 24.5 years, with lags varying seasonally, likely due to differences in N-delivery pathways. Lag times were found to be negatively correlated with both tile drainage and watershed slope, with tile drainage being a dominant control in fall and watershed slope being significant during the spring snowmelt period. Quantification of such lags will be crucial to policy-makers as they struggle to set appropriate goals for water quality improvement in human-impacted watersheds.</abstract><url hash="6993bf72">2016.GWF-1.6</url><doi>10.1088/1748-9326/aa7bf4</doi><bibkey>V. Van Meter-etal-2016-Time</bibkey></paper><paper id="7"><title>Modelling the impacts of agricultural management practices on river water quality in Eastern England.</title><author><first>Sam</first><last>Taylor</last></author><author><first>Yi</first><last>He</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Hiscock</last></author><abstract /><url hash="1e948fe4">2016.GWF-1.7</url><doi>10.1016/j.jenvman.2016.05.002</doi><bibkey>Taylor-etal-2016-Modelling</bibkey></paper><paper id="8"><title>Cooling on Photovoltaic Panel Using Forced Air Convection Induced by DC Fan</title><author><first>A.</first><last>R. Amelia</last></author><author><first>Y.</first><last>Irwan</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Irwanto</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Leow</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Gomesh</last></author><author><first>I.</first><last>Safwati</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Anuar</last></author><abstract>Photovoltaic (PV) panel is the heart of solar system generally has a low energy conversion efficiency available in the market. PV panel temperature control is the main key to keeping the PV panel operate efficiently. This paper presented the great influenced of the cooling system in reduced PV panel temperature. A cooling system has been developed based on forced convection induced by DC fan as cooling mechanism. DC fan was attached at the back side of PV panel will extract the heat energy distributed and cool down the PV panel. The working operation of DC fan controlled by PIC18F4550 microcontroller which depending on the average value of PV panel temperature. Experiments were performed with and without cooling mechanism attached at the backside PV panel. The whole PV system was subsequently evaluated in outdoor weather conditions. As a result, it is concluded that there is an optimum number of DC fans required as cooling mechanism in producing efficient electrical output from a PV panel. The study clearly shows how cooling mechanism improves the performance of PV panel at the hot climatic weather. In short, the reduction of PV panel temperature is very important to keep its performance operated efficiently.</abstract><url hash="8e2b9275">2016.GWF-1.8</url><doi>10.11591/IJECE.V6I2.PP526-534</doi><bibkey>R. Amelia-etal-2016-Cooling</bibkey></paper><paper id="9"><title>Proceedings of the International Working Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces</title><author><first>P.</first><last>Buono</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Lanzilotti</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Matera</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Costabile</last></author><abstract>AVI 2016 is the 13th edition of the International Working Conferences on Advanced Visual Interfaces, held in Bari, Italy, during June 7-10 2016. 
 
Since 1992, the AVI conferences are held every two years and have become well appreciated by the international community, attracting experts with a broad range of backgrounds, coming from all over the world and sharing a common interest on HCI, with the aim of making technology effective and useful for all people in their daily life. Because of advanced technology and new possibilities for user interaction, AVI has broadened the topics it covers, still keeping its main focus on the conception, design, implementation and evaluation of novel visual interfaces. While rooted in Italy, AVI is a true international conference with respect to nationality of participants, authors of papers, and program committee members. AVI 2016 presents an articulated strong scientific program. A rigorous double-blind reviewing process was carried out, with an acceptance rate of 27% for long papers (96 submissions). The various sessions explore research questions and solutions in several domains, and cover a wide range of topics. World leading researchers, from 22 different countries and 4 continents (Europe, America, Asia, and Australia) will present their work in 26 long papers, 17 short papers, 30 posters, 6 hands-on demos, and 5 workshops.</abstract><url hash="f92ca2e3">2016.GWF-1.9</url><doi>10.1145/2909132</doi><bibkey>Buono-etal-2016-Proceedings</bibkey></paper></volume></collection>