<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G16">
	<volume id="1">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Climate Dynamics, Volume 48, Issue 7-8</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Future changes to drought characteristics over the Canadian Prairie Provinces based on NARCCAP multi-RCM ensemble</title>
			<author>
				<first>M. B.</first>
				<last>Masud</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>M. N.</first>
				<last>Khaliq</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>H. S.</first>
				<last>Wheater</last>
			</author>
			<abstract />
			<url hash="4178f9e3">G16-1001</url>
			<pages>2685-2705</pages>
			<doi>10.1007/s00382-016-3232-2</doi>
			<bibkey>Masud-2016-Future</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="2">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Climate Dynamics, Volume 49, Issue 5-6</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Projected changes to short- and long-duration precipitation extremes over the Canadian Prairie Provinces</title>
			<author>
				<first>M. B.</first>
				<last>Masud</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>M. N.</first>
				<last>Khaliq</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>H. S.</first>
				<last>Wheater</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The effects of climate change on April–October short- and long-duration precipitation extremes over the Canadian Prairie Provinces were evaluated using a multi-Regional Climate Model (RCM) ensemble available through the North American Regional Climate Change Assessment Program. Simulations considered include those performed with six RCMs driven by the National Centre for Environmental Prediction (NCEP) reanalysis II product for the 1981–2000 period and those driven by four Atmosphere–Ocean General Circulation Models (AOGCMs) for the current 1971–2000 and future 2041–2070 periods (i.e. a total of 11 current-to-future period simulation pairs). A regional frequency analysis approach was used to develop 2-, 5-, 10-, 25-, and 50-year return values of precipitation extremes from NCEP and AOGCM-driven current and future period simulations that respectively were used to study the performance of RCMs and projected changes for selected return values at regional, grid-cell and local scales. Performance errors due to internal dynamics and physics of RCMs studied for the 1981–2000 period reveal considerable variation in the performance of the RCMs. However, the performance errors were found to be much smaller for RCM ensemble averages than for individual RCMs. Projected changes in future climate to selected regional return values of short-duration (e.g. 15- and 30-min) precipitation extremes and for longer return periods (e.g. 50-year) were found to be mostly larger than those to the longer duration (e.g. 24- and 48-h) extremes and short return periods (e.g. 2-year). Overall, projected changes in precipitation extremes were larger for southeastern regions followed by southern and northern regions and smaller for southwestern and western regions of the study area. The changes to return values were also found to be statistically significant for the majority of the RCM–AOGCM simulation pairs. These projections might be useful as a key input for the future planning of urban drainage infrastructure and development of strategic climate change adaptation measures.</abstract>
			<url hash="53cd560d">G16-2001</url>
			<pages>1597-1616</pages>
			<doi>10.1007/s00382-016-3404-0</doi>
			<bibkey>Masud-2016-Projected</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="3">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrology Research, Volume 48, Issue 4</booktitle>
			<publisher>IWA Publishing</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>The significance of spatial variability of rainfall on simulated runoff: an evaluation based on the Upper Lee catchment, UK</title>
			<author>
				<first>I. G.</first>
				<last>Pechlivanidis</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>N.</first>
				<last>McIntyre</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>H. S.</first>
				<last>Wheater</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The significance of spatial variability of rainfall on runoff is explored as a function of catchment scale and type, and antecedent conditions via the continuous time, semi-distributed probability distributed model (PDM) hydrological model applied to the Upper Lee catchment, UK. The impact of catchment scale and type is assessed using 11 nested catchments, and further assessed by artificially changing the catchment characteristics and translating these to model parameters (MPs) with uncertainty using model regionalisation. Dry and wet antecedent conditions are represented by ‘warming up’ the model under different rainfall time series. Synthetic rainfall events are introduced to directly relate the change in simulated runoff to the spatial variability of rainfall. Results show that runoff volume and peak are more sensitive to the spatial rainfall for more impermeable catchments; however, this sensitivity is significantly undermined under wet antecedent conditions. Although there is indication that the impact of spatial rainfall on runoff varies as a function of catchment scale, the variability of antecedent conditions between the synthetic catchments seems to mask this significance. Parameter uncertainty analysis highlights the importance of accurately representing the spatial variability of the catchment properties and their translation to MPs when investigating the effects of spatial properties of rainfall on runoff.</abstract>
			<url hash="eb713168">G16-3001</url>
			<pages>1118-1130</pages>
			<doi>10.2166/nh.2016.038</doi>
			<bibkey>Pechlivanidis-2016-The</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="4">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Ecosystems, Volume 20, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2016</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Losing Legacies, Ecological Release, and Transient Responses: Key Challenges for the Future of Northern Ecosystem Science</title>
			<author>
				<first>Merritt R.</first>
				<last>Turetsky</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jennifer L.</first>
				<last>Baltzer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jill F.</first>
				<last>Johnstone</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michelle C.</first>
				<last>Mack</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kevin</first>
				<last>McCann</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Edward A. G.</first>
				<last>Schuur</last>
			</author>
			<abstract />
			<url hash="76a609d1">G16-4001</url>
			<pages>23-30</pages>
			<doi>10.1007/s10021-016-0055-2</doi>
			<bibkey>Turetsky-2016-Losing</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
</collection>