<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G16"><volume id="1"><meta><booktitle>Trials, Volume 17, Issue 1</booktitle><publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher><address /><year>2016</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>OpenTrials: towards a collaborative open database of all available information on all clinical trials</title><author><first>Ben</first><last>Goldacre</last></author><author><first>Jonathan</first><last>Gray</last></author><abstract /><url hash="4178f9e3">G16-1001</url><doi>10.1186/s13063-016-1290-8</doi><bibkey>Goldacre-2016-OpenTrials:</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="2"><meta><booktitle>Ecosphere, Volume 7, Issue 11</booktitle><publisher>Wiley</publisher><address /><year>2016</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Response of understory vegetation to salvage logging following a high‐severity wildfire</title><author><first>Eric E.</first><last>Knapp</last></author><author><first>Martin W.</first><last>Ritchie</last></author><abstract /><url hash="53cd560d">G16-2001</url><doi>10.1002/ecs2.1550</doi><bibkey>Knapp-2016-Response</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="3"><meta><booktitle>Water Resources Research, Volume 52, Issue 2</booktitle><publisher>American Geophysical Union (AGU)</publisher><address /><year>2016</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>The fan of influence of streams and channel feedbacks to simulated land surface water and carbon dynamics</title><author><first>Chaopeng</first><last>Shen</last></author><author><first>William J.</first><last>Riley</last></author><author><first>Kurt R.</first><last>Smithgall</last></author><author><first>John M.</first><last>Melack</last></author><author><first>Kuai</first><last>Fang</last></author><abstract /><url hash="eb713168">G16-3001</url><pages>880-902</pages><doi>10.1002/2015wr018086</doi><bibkey>Shen-2016-The</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="4"><meta><booktitle>Climate Dynamics, Volume 48, Issue 7-8</booktitle><publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher><address /><year>2016</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Future changes to drought characteristics over the Canadian Prairie Provinces based on NARCCAP multi-RCM ensemble</title><author><first>M. B.</first><last>Masud</last></author><author><first>M. N.</first><last>Khaliq</last></author><author><first>H. S.</first><last>Wheater</last></author><abstract /><url hash="76a609d1">G16-4001</url><pages>2685-2705</pages><doi>10.1007/s00382-016-3232-2</doi><bibkey>Masud-2016-Future</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="5"><meta><booktitle>Climate Dynamics, Volume 49, Issue 5-6</booktitle><publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher><address /><year>2016</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Projected changes to short- and long-duration precipitation extremes over the Canadian Prairie Provinces</title><author><first>M. B.</first><last>Masud</last></author><author><first>M. N.</first><last>Khaliq</last></author><author><first>H. S.</first><last>Wheater</last></author><abstract /><url hash="ce1a6eb4">G16-5001</url><pages>1597-1616</pages><doi>10.1007/s00382-016-3404-0</doi><bibkey>Masud-2016-Projected</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="6"><meta><booktitle>Hydrology Research, Volume 48, Issue 4</booktitle><publisher>IWA Publishing</publisher><address /><year>2016</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>The significance of spatial variability of rainfall on simulated runoff: an evaluation based on the Upper Lee catchment, UK</title><author><first>I. G.</first><last>Pechlivanidis</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>McIntyre</last></author><author><first>H. S.</first><last>Wheater</last></author><abstract>&lt;jats:p&gt;The significance of spatial variability of rainfall on runoff is explored as a function of catchment scale and type, and antecedent conditions via the continuous time, semi-distributed probability distributed model (PDM) hydrological model applied to the Upper Lee catchment, UK. The impact of catchment scale and type is assessed using 11 nested catchments, and further assessed by artificially changing the catchment characteristics and translating these to model parameters (MPs) with uncertainty using model regionalisation. Dry and wet antecedent conditions are represented by ‘warming up’ the model under different rainfall time series. Synthetic rainfall events are introduced to directly relate the change in simulated runoff to the spatial variability of rainfall. Results show that runoff volume and peak are more sensitive to the spatial rainfall for more impermeable catchments; however, this sensitivity is significantly undermined under wet antecedent conditions. Although there is indication that the impact of spatial rainfall on runoff varies as a function of catchment scale, the variability of antecedent conditions between the synthetic catchments seems to mask this significance. Parameter uncertainty analysis highlights the importance of accurately representing the spatial variability of the catchment properties and their translation to MPs when investigating the effects of spatial properties of rainfall on runoff.&lt;/jats:p&gt;</abstract><url hash="dcafc15a">G16-6001</url><pages>1118-1130</pages><doi>10.2166/nh.2016.038</doi><bibkey>Pechlivanidis-2016-The</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="7"><meta><booktitle>Ecosystems, Volume 20, Issue 1</booktitle><publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher><address /><year>2016</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Losing Legacies, Ecological Release, and Transient Responses: Key Challenges for the Future of Northern Ecosystem Science</title><author><first>Merritt R.</first><last>Turetsky</last></author><author><first>Jennifer L.</first><last>Baltzer</last></author><author><first>Jill F.</first><last>Johnstone</last></author><author><first>Michelle C.</first><last>Mack</last></author><author><first>Kevin</first><last>McCann</last></author><author><first>Edward A. G.</first><last>Schuur</last></author><abstract /><url hash="6413a63f">G16-7001</url><pages>23-30</pages><doi>10.1007/s10021-016-0055-2</doi><bibkey>Turetsky-2016-Losing</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="8"><meta><booktitle>Journal of Environmental Management, Volume 180</booktitle><publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher><address /><year>2016</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Modelling the impacts of agricultural management practices on river water quality in Eastern England</title><author><first>Sam D.</first><last>Taylor</last></author><author><first>Yi</first><last>He</last></author><author><first>Kevin M.</first><last>Hiscock</last></author><abstract /><url hash="3c70b669">G16-8001</url><pages>147-163</pages><doi>10.1016/j.jenvman.2016.05.002</doi><bibkey>Taylor-2016-Modelling</bibkey></paper></volume><volume id="9"><meta><booktitle>International Journal of Electrical and Computer Engineering (IJECE), Volume 6, Issue 2</booktitle><publisher>Institute of Advanced Engineering and Science</publisher><address /><year>2016</year></meta><paper id="1"><title>Cooling on Photovoltaic Panel Using Forced Air Convection Induced by DC Fan</title><author><first>A.R.</first><last>Amelia</last></author><author><first>Y.M.</first><last>Irwan</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Irwanto</last></author><author><first>W.Z.</first><last>Leow</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Gomesh</last></author><author><first>I.</first><last>Safwati</last></author><author><first>M.A.M.</first><last>Anuar</last></author><abstract>&lt;jats:p&gt;&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;Photovoltaic (PV) panel is the heart of solar system generally has a low energy conversion efficiency available in the market. PV panel temperature control is the main key to keeping the PV panel operate efficiently. This paper presented the great influenced of the cooling system in reduced PV panel temperature. A cooling system has been developed based on forced convection induced by DC fan as cooling mechanism. DC fan was attached at the back side of PV panel will extract the heat energy distributed and cool down the PV panel. The working operation of DC fan controlled by PIC18F4550 microcontroller which depending on the average value of PV panel temperature. Experiments were performed with and without cooling mechanism attached at the backside PV panel. The whole PV system was subsequently evaluated in outdoor weather conditions. As a result, it is concluded that there is an optimum number of DC fans required as cooling mechanism in producing efficient electrical output from a PV panel. The study clearly shows how cooling mechanism improves the performance of PV panel at the hot climatic weather. In short, the reduction of PV panel temperature is very important to keep its performance operated efficiently.&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/jats:p&gt;</abstract><url hash="84ccd10c">G16-9001</url><pages>526</pages><doi>10.11591/ijece.v6i2.pp526-534</doi><bibkey>Amelia-2016-Cooling</bibkey></paper></volume></collection>