<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G18"><volume id="1"><meta><booktitle>Global Water Futures 2018</booktitle><publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher><address>Online</address><year>2018</year></meta><frontmatter><url hash="4832c1d5">2018.GWF-1.0</url><bibkey>G18-2018-water</bibkey></frontmatter><paper id="1"><title>Proceedings of the 9th International Workshop on Physics and Computation</title><author><first>Michael</first><last>E. Cuffaro</last></author><author><first>Philippos</first><last>Papayannopoulos</last></author><abstract>The 9th International Workshop on Physics and Computation (PC 2018) was held as a satellite workshop of the 17th International Conference on Unconventional Computation and Natural Computation (UCNC 2018) in Fontainebleau, France, which was held from 25-29 June 2018. PC 2018 was an interdisciplinary meeting which brought together researchers from various domains with interests in physics and computation. Research and important issues relating to the interface between physics and the theories of computation, computability and information, including their application to physical systems, were presented and discussed.</abstract><url hash="3f35f143">2018.GWF-1.1</url><doi>10.4204/EPTCS.273</doi><bibkey>E. Cuffaro-etal-2018-Proceedings</bibkey></paper><paper id="2"><title>Comment on “Groundwater Pumping Is a Significant Unrecognized Contributor to Global Anthropogenic Element Cycles”</title><author><first>G.</first><last>Ferguson</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>McIntosh</last></author><abstract>The ideas presented by Stahl (2018) are intriguing. There is a wealth of information that supports that groundwater pumping has perturbed the hydrologic cycle at a global scale (Konikow 2011; Rodell et al. 2018) and perturbations to global elemental cycles would not be unexpected. However, the analysis presented by Stahl (2018) is problematic. Stahl assumes that the 45% of produced waters from oil field operations that were not used in enhanced oil recovery (EOR) are released into the more active portion of the hydrological cycle based on 2007 figures for the United States from Clark and Veil (2009). This figure is substantially lower in reality. Clark and Veil (2009) report that 38.2% of produced waters were injected into nonproducing strata. This injection occurs almost exclusively through Class II disposal wells, which are typically installed in saline aquifers (EPA 2018). Similar practices have been noted in Canada, where there has been a net gain in the amount of water in the Western Canada Sedimentary Basin (Ferguson 2015). In addition, Stahl states that 45% of Shell’s produced water is discharged at the surface based on an estimate from Khatib and Verbeek (2003). However, that study also noted that much of this discharge was to the ocean as part of offshore drilling activities. The overestimation of addition of produced water to the active portion of global elemental cycles will have a notable effect on estimates of fluxes of elements such as Li, Na, Cl, and Ca, which are found in high concentrations</abstract><url hash="a63ca0f9">2018.GWF-1.2</url><doi>10.1111/gwat.12840</doi><bibkey>Ferguson-etal-2018-Comment</bibkey></paper><paper id="3"><title>The Persistence of Brines in Sedimentary Basins</title><author><first>G.</first><last>Ferguson</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>McIntosh</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Grasby</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Hendry</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Jasechko</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Lindsay</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Luijendijk</last></author><abstract>Brines are commonly found at depth in sedimentary basins. Many of these brines are known to be connate waters that have persisted since the early Paleozoic Era. Yet questions remain about their distribution and mechanisms for retention at depth in the Earth's crust. Here we demonstrate that there is insufficient topography to drive these dense fluids from the bottom of deep sedimentary basins. Our assessment based on driving force ratio indicates that sedimentary basins with driving force ratio &gt; 1 contain connate waters and frequently host large evaporite deposits. These stagnant conditions appear to be relatively stable over geological time and insensitive to factors such as glaciations, erosion, compaction, and hydrocarbon generation.</abstract><url hash="d13b906f">2018.GWF-1.3</url><doi>10.1029/2018GL078409</doi><bibkey>Ferguson-etal-2018-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="4"><title>Competition for shrinking window of low salinity groundwater</title><author><first>G.</first><last>Ferguson</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>McIntosh</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Perrone</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Jasechko</last></author><abstract>Groundwater resources are being stressed from the top down and bottom up. Declining water tables and near-surface contamination are driving groundwater users to construct deeper wells in many US aquifer systems. This has been a successful short-term mitigation measure where deep groundwater is fresh and free of contaminants. Nevertheless, vertical salinity profiles are not well-constrained at continental-scales. In many regions, oil and gas activities use pore spaces for energy production and waste disposal. Here we quantify depths that aquifer systems transition from fresh-to-brackish and where oil and gas activities are widespread in sedimentary basins across the United States. Fresh-brackish transitions occur at relatively shallow depths of just a few hundred meters, particularly in eastern US basins. We conclude that fresh groundwater is less abundant in several key US basins than previously thought; therefore drilling deeper wells to access fresh groundwater resources is not feasible extensively across the continent. Our findings illustrate that groundwater stores are being depleted not only by excessive withdrawals, but due to injection, and potentially contamination, from the oil and gas industry in areas of deep fresh and brackish groundwater.</abstract><url hash="4f5f05cc">2018.GWF-1.4</url><doi>10.1088/1748-9326/aae6d8</doi><bibkey>Ferguson-etal-2018-Competition</bibkey></paper><paper id="5"><title>Salt dissolution and permeability in the Western Canada Sedimentary Basin</title><author><first>Blake</first><last>Woroniuk</last></author><author><first>Kristl</first><last>J Tipton</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Grasby</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>McIntosh</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Ferguson</last></author><abstract /><url hash="3858355a">2018.GWF-1.5</url><doi>10.1007/s10040-018-1871-6</doi><bibkey>Woroniuk-etal-2018-Salt</bibkey></paper><paper id="6"><title>A solar powered long range real-time water quality monitoring system by LoRaWAN</title><author><first>Yan-Ting</first><last>Liu</last></author><author><first>Bill</first><last>Y. Lin</last></author><author><first>X.</first><last>Yue</last></author><author><first>Zong-Xuan</first><last>Cai</last></author><author><first>Zi-Xian</first><last>Yang</last></author><author><first>Wei-Hong</first><last>Liu</last></author><author><first>Song-Yi</first><last>Huang</last></author><author><first>Jun-Lin</first><last>Lu</last></author><author><first>Jing-Wen</first><last>Peng</last></author><author><first>Jen-Yeu</first><last>Chen</last></author><abstract>In order to maintain the quality of water resources in the global environment, we must conduct water quality monitoring. With the evolution of technology, we can improve the management of water quality by the IoT(Internet of Things) system. Therefore, this paper provides a real-time water quality monitoring system by the Internet of Things system. We selected Dong Lake in National Dong Hwa University as a test field to monitor water temperature, turbidity, conductivity, and pH. After that, the various water quality data will be transmitted to the database via wireless transmission. Finally, these data will be displayed on the web page immediately. And, it is very important to select what kind of wireless communication technique. For the long-range application in the field, we used Low-Power Wide-Area Network (LPWAN)-Long Range Wide Area Network (LoRaWAN) for data transmission. To extend the system life, a solar panel is adapted to recharge battery.</abstract><url hash="a15164e0">2018.GWF-1.6</url><doi>10.1109/WOCC.2018.8373792</doi><bibkey>Liu-etal-2018-A</bibkey></paper><paper id="7"><title>Alpine Hydrogeology: The Critical Role of Groundwater in Sourcing the Headwaters of the World</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Hayashi</last></author><abstract>Groundwater discharge in alpine headwaters sustains baseflow in rivers originating in mountain ranges of the world, which is critically important for aquatic habitats, run‐of‐river hydropower generation, and downstream water supply. Groundwater storage in alpine watersheds was long considered negligible, but recent field‐based studies have shown that aquifers are ubiquitous in the alpine zone with no soil and vegetation. Talus, moraine, and rock glacier aquifers are common in many alpine regions of the world, although bedrock aquifers occur in some geological settings. Alpine aquifers consisting of coarse sediments have a fast recession of discharge after the recharge season (e.g., snowmelt) or rainfall events, followed by a slow recession that sustains discharge over a long period. The two‐phase recession is likely controlled by the internal structure of the aquifers. Spatial extent and distribution of individual aquifers determine the groundwater storage‐discharge characteristics in first‐ and second‐order watersheds in the alpine zone, which in turn govern baseflow characteristics in major rivers. Similar alpine landforms appear to have similar hydrogeological characteristics in many mountain ranges across the world, suggesting that a common conceptual framework can be used to understand alpine aquifers based on geological and geomorphological settings. Such a framework will be useful for parameterizing storage‐discharge characteristics in large river hydrological models.</abstract><url hash="d6565476">2018.GWF-1.7</url><doi>10.1111/gwat.12965</doi><bibkey>Hayashi-etal-2018-Alpine</bibkey></paper><paper id="8"><title>Storage, mixing, and fluxes of water in the critical zone across northern environments inferred by stable isotopes of soil water</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Sprenger</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Tetzlaff</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Buttle</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Carey</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>McNamara</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Laudon</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Shatilla</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Soulsby</last></author><abstract>Quantifying soil water storage, mixing, and release via recharge, transpiration, and evaporation is essential for a better understanding of critical zone processes. Here, we integrate stable isotope (2H and 18O of soil water, precipitation, and groundwater) and hydrometric (soil moisture) data from 5 long‐term experimental catchments along a hydroclimatic gradient across northern latitudes: Dry Creek (USA), Bruntland Burn (Scotland), Dorset (Canada), Krycklan (Sweden), and Wolf Creek (Canada). Within each catchment, 6 to 11 isotope sampling campaigns occurred at 2 to 4 sampling locations over at least 1 year. Analysis for 2H and 18O in the bulk pore water was done for &gt;2,500 soil samples either by cryogenic extraction (Dry Creek) or by direct equilibration (other sites). The results showed a similar general pattern that soil water isotope variability reflected the seasonality of the precipitation input signal. However, pronounced differences among sampling locations occurred regarding the isotopic fractionation due to evaporation. We found that antecedent precipitation volumes mainly governed the fractionation signal, temperature and evaporation rates were of secondary importance, and soil moisture played only a minor role in the variability of soil water evaporation fractionation across the hydroclimatic gradient. We further observed that soil waters beneath conifer trees were more fractionated than beneath heather shrubs or red oak trees, indicating higher soil evaporation rates in coniferous forests. Sampling locations closer to streams were more damped and depleted in their stable isotopic composition than hillslope sites, revealing increased subsurface mixing towards the saturated zone and a preferential recharge of winter precipitation. Bulk soil waters generally comprised a high share of waters older than 14 days, which indicates that the water in soil pores are usually not fully replaced by recent infiltration events. The presented stable isotope data of soil water were, thus, a useful tool to track the spatial variability of water fluxes within and from the critical zone. Such data provide invaluable information to improve the representation of critical zone processes in spatially distributed hydrological models.</abstract><url hash="46e949e7">2018.GWF-1.8</url><doi>10.1002/hyp.13135</doi><bibkey>Sprenger-etal-2018-Storage,</bibkey></paper><paper id="9"><title>Using stable isotopes to estimate travel times in a data‐sparse Arctic catchment: Challenges and possible solutions</title><author><first>D.</first><last>Tetzlaff</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Piovano</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Ala‐aho</last></author><author><first>Aaron</first><last>A. Smith</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Carey</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Marsh</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Wookey</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Street</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Soulsby</last></author><abstract>Use of isotopes to quantify the temporal dynamics of the transformation of precipitation into run‐off has revealed fundamental new insights into catchment flow paths and mixing processes that influence biogeochemical transport. However, catchments underlain by permafrost have received little attention in isotope‐based studies, despite their global importance in terms of rapid environmental change. These high‐latitude regions offer limited access for data collection during critical periods (e.g., early phases of snowmelt). Additionally, spatio‐temporal variable freeze–thaw cycles, together with the development of an active layer, have a time variant influence on catchment hydrology. All of these characteristics make the application of traditional transit time estimation approaches challenging. We describe an isotope‐based study undertaken to provide a preliminary assessment of travel times at Siksik Creek in the western Canadian Arctic. We adopted a model–data fusion approach to estimate the volumes and isotopic characteristics of snowpack and meltwater. Using samples collected in the spring/summer, we characterize the isotopic composition of summer rainfall, melt from snow, soil water, and stream water. In addition, soil moisture dynamics and the temporal evolution of the active layer profile were monitored. First approximations of transit times were estimated for soil and streamwater compositions using lumped convolution integral models and temporally variable inputs including snowmelt, ice thaw, and summer rainfall. Comparing transit time estimates using a variety of inputs revealed that transit time was best estimated using all available inflows (i.e., snowmelt, soil ice thaw, and rainfall). Early spring transit times were short, dominated by snowmelt and soil ice thaw and limited catchment storage when soils are predominantly frozen. However, significant and increasing mixing with water in the active layer during the summer resulted in more damped steam water variation and longer mean travel times (~1.5 years). The study has also highlighted key data needs to better constrain travel time estimates in permafrost catchments.</abstract><url hash="31ee7971">2018.GWF-1.9</url><doi>10.1002/hyp.13146</doi><bibkey>Tetzlaff-etal-2018-Using</bibkey></paper><paper id="10"><title>Global Estimates of River Flow Wave Travel Times and Implications for Low‐Latency Satellite Data</title><author><first>G.</first><last>Allen</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>David</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Andreadis</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Hossain</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Famiglietti</last></author><abstract>Earth‐orbiting satellites provide valuable observations of upstream river conditions worldwide. These observations can be used in real‐time applications like early flood warning systems and reservoir operations, provided they are made available to users with sufficient lead time. Yet the temporal requirements for access to satellite‐based river data remain uncharacterized for time‐sensitive applications. Here we present a global approximation of flow wave travel time to assess the utility of existing and future low‐latency/near‐real‐time satellite products, with an emphasis on the forthcoming SWOT satellite mission. We apply a kinematic wave model to a global hydrography data set and find that global flow waves traveling at their maximum speed take a median travel time of 6, 4, and 3 days to reach their basin terminus, the next downstream city, and the next downstream dam, respectively. Our findings suggest that a recently proposed ≤2‐day data latency for a low‐latency SWOT product is potentially useful for real‐time river applications.</abstract><url hash="1b31fafa">2018.GWF-1.10</url><doi>10.1029/2018GL077914</doi><bibkey>Allen-etal-2018-Global</bibkey></paper><paper id="11"><title>Biological and geophysical feedbacks with fire in the Earth system</title><author><first>S.</first><last>Archibald</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Lehmann</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Belcher</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>J. Bond</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Bradstock</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Daniau</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Dexter</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Forrestel</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Greve</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>He</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Higgins</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Hoffmann</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Lamont</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>McGlinn</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Moncrieff</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Osborne</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pausas</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Price</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Ripley</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Rogers</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Schwilk</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Simon</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Turetsky</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>R. van der Werf</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Zanne</last></author><abstract>Roughly 3% of the Earth’s land surface burns annually, representing a critical exchange of energy and matter between the land and atmosphere via combustion. Fires range from slow smouldering peat fires, to low-intensity surface fires, to intense crown fires, depending on vegetation structure, fuel moisture, prevailing climate, and weather conditions. While the links between biogeochemistry, climate and fire are widely studied within Earth system science, these relationships are also mediated by fuels—namely plants and their litter—that are the product of evolutionary and ecological processes. Fire is a powerful selective force and, over their evolutionary history, plants have evolved traits that both tolerate and promote fire numerous times and across diverse clades. Here we outline a conceptual framework of how plant traits determine the flammability of ecosystems and interact with climate and weather to influence fire regimes. We explore how these evolutionary and ecological processes scale to impact biogeochemical and Earth system processes. Finally, we outline several research challenges that, when resolved, will improve our understanding of the role of plant evolution in mediating the fire feedbacks driving Earth system processes. Understanding current patterns of fire and vegetation, as well as patterns of fire over geological time, requires research that incorporates evolutionary biology, ecology, biogeography, and the biogeosciences.</abstract><url hash="6c36ca6c">2018.GWF-1.11</url><doi>10.1088/1748-9326/aa9ead</doi><bibkey>Archibald-etal-2018-Biological</bibkey></paper><paper id="12"><title>Modeling the exposure of wild fish to endocrine active chemicals: Potential linkages of total estrogenicity to field-observed intersex.</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Arlos</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Parker</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Bicudo</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Law</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Hicks</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Fuzzen</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Andrews</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Servos</last></author><abstract /><url hash="f53f9bd6">2018.GWF-1.12</url><doi>10.1016/j.watres.2018.04.005</doi><bibkey>Arlos-etal-2018-Modeling</bibkey></paper><paper id="13"><title>Multi-year prediction of estrogenicity in municipal wastewater effluents.</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Arlos</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Parker</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Bicudo</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Law</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Marjan</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Andrews</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Servos</last></author><abstract /><url hash="8238ab40">2018.GWF-1.13</url><doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.08.171</doi><bibkey>Arlos-etal-2018-Multi-year</bibkey></paper><paper id="14"><title>Spatial variability of mean daily estimates of actual evaporation from remotely sensed imagery and surface reference data</title><author><first>R.</first><last>Armstrong</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pomeroy</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Martz</last></author><abstract>Abstract. Land surface evaporation has considerable spatial variability that
is not captured by point-scale estimates calculated from meteorological data
alone. Knowing how evaporation varies spatially remains an important issue
for improving parameterisations of land surface schemes and hydrological
models and various land management practices. Satellite-based and aerial
remote sensing has been crucial for capturing moderate- to larger-scale
surface variables to indirectly estimate evaporative fluxes. However, more
recent advances for field research via unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) now allow
for the acquisition of more highly detailed surface data. Integrating models that can estimate “actual” evaporation from higher-resolution imagery and surface reference data would be valuable to better examine potential impacts of local variations in evaporation on upscaled estimates. This study introduces a novel approach for computing a normalised ratiometric index from surface variables that can be used to obtain more-realistic distributed estimates of actual evaporation. For demonstration purposes the Granger–Gray evaporation model (Granger and Gray, 1989) was applied at a rolling prairie agricultural site in central Saskatchewan, Canada. Visible and thermal images and meteorological reference data required to parameterise the model were obtained at midday. Ratiometric indexes were computed for the key surface variables albedo and
net radiation at midday. This allowed point observations of albedo and mean
daily net radiation to be scaled across high-resolution images over a large
study region. Albedo and net radiation estimates were within 5 %–10 % of measured values. A daily evaporation estimate for a grassed surface was 0.5 mm (23 %) larger than eddy covariance measurements. Spatial variations in key factors driving evaporation and their impacts on upscaled evaporation estimates are also discussed. The methods applied have two key advantages for estimating evaporation over previous remote-sensing approaches: (1) detailed daily estimates of actual evaporation can be directly obtained using a physically based evaporation model, and
(2) analysis of more-detailed and more-reliable evaporation estimates may lead to improved methods for upscaling evaporative fluxes to larger areas.
</abstract><url hash="1c5c3ee3">2018.GWF-1.14</url><doi>10.5194/HESS-23-4891-2019</doi><bibkey>Armstrong-etal-2018-Spatial</bibkey></paper><paper id="15"><title>Historical drought patterns over Canada and their teleconnections with large-scale climate signals</title><author><first>Z.</first><last>E. Asong</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Wheater</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Bonsal</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Razavi</last></author><author><first>Sopan</first><last>Kurkute</last></author><abstract>Abstract. Drought is a recurring extreme climate event and among the most
costly natural disasters in the world. This is particularly true over Canada,
where drought is both a frequent and damaging phenomenon with impacts on
regional water resources, agriculture, industry, aquatic ecosystems, and
health. However, nationwide drought assessments are currently lacking and
impacted by limited ground-based observations. This study provides a
comprehensive analysis of historical droughts over the whole of Canada,
including the role of large-scale teleconnections. Drought events are
characterized by the Standardized Precipitation Evapotranspiration Index
(SPEI) over various temporal scales (1, 3, 6, and 12 consecutive months,
6 months from April to September, and 12 months from October to September)
applied to different gridded monthly data sets for the period 1950–2013.
The Mann–Kendall test, rotated empirical orthogonal function, continuous
wavelet transform, and wavelet coherence analyses are used, respectively, to
investigate the trend, spatio-temporal patterns, periodicity, and
teleconnectivity of drought events. Results indicate that southern (northern)
parts of the country experienced significant trends towards drier (wetter)
conditions although substantial variability exists. Two spatially
well-defined regions with different temporal evolution of droughts were
identified – the Canadian Prairies and northern central Canada. The analyses
also revealed the presence of a dominant periodicity of between 8 and 32 months in the Prairie region and between 8 and 40 months in the northern central
region. These cycles of low-frequency variability are found to be associated
principally with the Pacific–North American (PNA) and Multivariate El
Niño/Southern Oscillation Index (MEI) relative to other considered
large-scale climate indices. This study is the first of its kind to identify
dominant periodicities in drought variability over the whole of Canada in
terms of when the drought events occur, their duration, and how often they occur.
</abstract><url hash="6b5b0e75">2018.GWF-1.15</url><doi>10.5194/HESS-22-3105-2018</doi><bibkey>E. Asong-etal-2018-Historical</bibkey></paper><paper id="16"><title>Potential impacts of climate change on the habitat of boreal woodland caribou</title><author><first>Quinn</first><last>E. Barber</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Parisien</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Whitman</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Stralberg</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Johnson</last></author><author><first>Martin‐Hugues</first><last>St‐Laurent</last></author><author><first>Evan</first><last>R. DeLancey</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Price</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Arseneault</last></author><author><first>Xianli</first><last>Wang</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Flannigan</last></author><abstract /><url hash="f2525fcf">2018.GWF-1.16</url><doi>10.1002/ECS2.2472</doi><bibkey>E. Barber-etal-2018-Potential</bibkey></paper><paper id="17"><title>Improving the Explicit Prediction of Freezing Rain in a Kilometer-Scale Numerical Weather Prediction Model</title><author><first>A.</first><last>Barszcz</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Milbrandt</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Thériault</last></author><abstract>AbstractA freezing rain event, in which the Meteorological Centre of Canada’s 2.5-km numerical weather prediction system significantly underpredicted the quantity of freezing rain, is examined. The prediction system models precipitation types explicitly, directly from the Milbrandt–Yau microphysics scheme. It was determined that the freezing rain underprediction for this case was due primarily to excessive refreezing of rain, originating from melting snow and graupel, in and under the temperature inversion of the advancing warm front ultimately depleting the supply of rain reaching the surface. The refreezing was caused from excessive collisional freezing between rain and graupel. Sensitivity experiments were conducted to examine the effects of a temperature threshold for collisional freezing and on varying the values of the collection efficiencies between rain and ice-phase hydrometeors. It was shown that by reducing the rain–graupel collection efficiency and by imposing a temperature threshold of −5°C, ...</abstract><url hash="85556f59">2018.GWF-1.17</url><doi>10.1175/WAF-D-17-0136.1</doi><bibkey>Barszcz-etal-2018-Improving</bibkey></paper><paper id="18"><title>Probable Maximum Precipitation: Its Estimation and Uncertainty Quantification Using Bivariate Extreme Value Analysis</title><author><first>M.</first><last>B. Alaya</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Zwiers</last></author><author><first>Xuebin</first><last>Zhang</last></author><abstract>AbstractProbable maximum precipitation (PMP) is the key parameter used to estimate the probable maximum flood (PMF), both of which are important for dam safety and civil engineering purposes. The u...</abstract><url hash="15ea72c8">2018.GWF-1.18</url><doi>10.1175/JHM-D-17-0110.1</doi><bibkey>B. Alaya-etal-2018-Probable</bibkey></paper><paper id="19"><title>Contributions of Geophysical and C-Band SAR Data for Estimation of Field Scale Soil Moisture</title><author><first>A.</first><last>Berg</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Krafczek</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Clewley</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Whitcomb</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Akbar</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Moghaddam</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Mcnairn</last></author><abstract>In this study we evaluate a Random Forest (RF) model for characterizing the spatial variability of soil moisture based on model derived from in situ soil moisture samples, geophysical data and RADAR observations. The RF model is run with and without C-band SAR backscatter to understand the importance of the inclusion of SAR data for mapping of soil moisture at field scale. The inclusion of SAR data in the RF resulted in a modest improvement however the geophysical parameters (e.g. soil types and terrain properties) were of greater importance.</abstract><url hash="62ed425e">2018.GWF-1.19</url><doi>10.1109/IGARSS.2018.8517551</doi><bibkey>Berg-etal-2018-Contributions</bibkey></paper><paper id="20"><title>Quantifying the effect of forest age in annual net forest carbon balance</title><author><first>S.</first><last>Besnard</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Carvalhais</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>A. Arain</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Black</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>de Bruin</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Buchmann</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Cescatti</last></author><author><first>Jiquan</first><last>Chen</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Clevers</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Desai</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Gough</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Havránková</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Herold</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Hörtnagl</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Jung</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Knohl</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Kruijt</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Křupková</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Law</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Lindroth</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Noormets</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Roupsard</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Steinbrecher</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Varlagin</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Vincke</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Reichstein</last></author><abstract>Forests dominate carbon (C) exchanges between the terrestrial biosphere and the atmosphere on land. In the long term, the net carbon flux between forests and the atmosphere has been significantly impacted by changes in forest cover area and structure due to ecological disturbances and management activities. Current empirical approaches for estimating net ecosystem productivity (NEP) rarely consider forest age as a predictor, which represents variation in physiological processes that can respond differently to environmental drivers, and regrowth following disturbance. Here, we conduct an observational synthesis to empirically determine to what extent climate, soil properties, nitrogen deposition, forest age and management influence the spatial and interannual variability of forest NEP across 126 forest eddy-covariance flux sites worldwide. The empirical models explained up to 62% and 71% of spatio-temporal and across-site variability of annual NEP, respectively. An investigation of model structures revealed that forest age was a dominant factor of NEP spatio-temporal variability in both space and time at the global scale as compared to abiotic factors, such as nutrient availability, soil characteristics and climate. These findings emphasize the importance of forest age in quantifying spatio-temporal variation in NEP using empirical approaches.</abstract><url hash="301ca939">2018.GWF-1.20</url><doi>10.1088/1748-9326/aaeaeb</doi><bibkey>Besnard-etal-2018-Quantifying</bibkey></paper><paper id="21"><title>Enlargement and evolution of a semi‐alluvial creek in response to urbanization</title><author><first>V.</first><last>Bevan</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>MacVicar</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Chapuis</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Ghunowa</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Papangelakis</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Parish</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Snodgrass</last></author><abstract>The impact of urbanization on stream channels is of interest due to the growth of cities and the sensitivity of stream morphology and ecology to hydrologic change. Channel enlargement is a commonly observed effect and channel evolution models can help guide management efforts, but the models must be used in the proper geologic and climatic context. Semi‐alluvial channels characterized by a relatively thin alluvial layer over clay till and a convex channel profile in a temperate climate are not represented in currently available models. In this study we: (i) assess channel enlargement; and (ii) propose a channel evolution model for an urban semi‐alluvial creek in Toronto, Canada. The system is 90% developed with an imperviousness of approximately 47%. Channel enlargement is assessed by comparing 50 year old construction surveys, a recent survey of a relic channel, low‐precision surveys of channel change over a 15 year period, and high‐precision surveys over a three year period. The enlargement ratio of the channel since 1958 is 2.6, but could be as high 8.2 in comparison with the pre‐urban channel. When the increase in flow capacity is considered, the enlargement ratio is 1.9 since 1958 and up to 6.0 in comparison with the pre‐urban channel. Channel enlargement continues in the contemporary channel at an estimated rate of 0.23 m2/year. A five stage model is presented to describe channel evolution in the lower reaches. In this model the coarse lag material from glacial sources provides a natural resilience to the bed and incision occurs only after the increased flows from urbanization are combined with higher slopes as a result of channel straightening or avulsions. Further research should be done to assess stream behaviour close to an identified geologic control point. Copyright © 2018 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</abstract><url hash="471b99af">2018.GWF-1.21</url><doi>10.1002/esp.4391</doi><bibkey>Bevan-etal-2018-Enlargement</bibkey></paper><paper id="22"><title>Monitoring ecosystem reclamation recovery using optical remote sensing: Comparison with field measurements and eddy covariance.</title><author><first>L.</first><last>Chasmer</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Baker</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Carey</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Straker</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Strilesky</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Petrone</last></author><abstract /><url hash="de12c815">2018.GWF-1.22</url><doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.06.039</doi><bibkey>Chasmer-etal-2018-Monitoring</bibkey></paper><paper id="23"><title>Nutrient Loss Rates in Relation to Transport Time Scales in a Large Shallow Lake (Lake St. Clair, USA—Canada): Insights From a Three‐Dimensional Model</title><author><first>Serghei</first><last>A. Bocaniov</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Scavia</last></author><abstract>A nutrient mass balance and a three‐dimensional, coupled hydrodynamic‐ecological model, calibrated and validated for Lake St. Clair with observations from 2009 and 2010, were integrated to estimate monthly lake‐scale nutrient loss rates, and to calculate 3 monthly transport time scales: flushing time, water age, and water residence time. While nutrient loss rates had statistically significant relationships with all transport time scale measures, water age had the strongest explanatory power, with water age and nutrient loss rates both smaller in spring and fall and larger in summer. We show that Lake St. Clair is seasonally divided into two discrete regions of contrasting water age and productivity. The north‐western region is dominated by oligotrophic waters from the St. Clair River, and south‐eastern region is dominated by the nutrient enriched, more productive waters from the Thames‐Sydenham River complex. The spatial and temporal variations in local transport scales and nutrient loss rates, coupled with strong seasonal variations in discharge and nutrient loads from the major tributaries, suggest the need for different load reduction strategies for different tributaries.</abstract><url hash="a915f883">2018.GWF-1.23</url><doi>10.1029/2017WR021876</doi><bibkey>A. Bocaniov-etal-2018-Nutrient</bibkey></paper><paper id="24"><title>Co-design of water services and infrastructure for Indigenous Canada: A scoping review</title><author><first>L.</first><last>Bradford</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Vogel</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Lindenschmidt</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>McPhedran</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Strickert</last></author><author><first>Terrence</first><last>A. Fonstad</last></author><author><first>Lalita</first><last>Bharadwaj</last></author><abstract>There is movement in engineering fields and in Indigenous communities for enhancement of local participation in the design of community infrastructure. Inclusion of community priorities and unique cultural, spiritual, and traditional values harmonize the appearance, location, and functionality of developments with the social and cultural context in which they are built and contribute to holistic wellness. However, co-design processes that align community values and the technical needs of water facilities are difficult to find. A scoping review was conducted to explore the state of knowledge on co-design of water infrastructure in Indigenous Canada to build a knowledge base from which practices and processes could emerge. The scoping results revealed that articles and reports emerged only in recent years, contained case studies and meta-reviews with primary (qualitative) data, and involved community members in various capacities. Overall, 13 articles were reviewed that contributed to understanding co-design for water infrastructure in Indigenous Canada. Barriers to co-design included funding models for Indigenous community infrastructure, difficulties in engineers and designers understanding Indigenous worldviews and paradigms, and a lack of cooperation among stakeholders that contribute to ongoing design failures. A working definition of co-design for Indigenous water infrastructure is presented.</abstract><url hash="37716d20">2018.GWF-1.24</url><doi>10.1139/FACETS-2017-0124</doi><bibkey>Bradford-etal-2018-Co-design</bibkey></paper><paper id="25"><title>When a Water Problem Is More Than a Water Problem: Fragmentation, Framing, and the Case of Agricultural Wetland Drainage</title><author><first>S.</first><last>Breen</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Loring</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Baulch</last></author><abstract>Complex interactions between water, society, the economy, and the environment necessitate attention to how water issues are framed, and the limitations of a water-centric framework for analyzing or solving problems. We explore this complexity through an example of an existing complex, or wicked, policy problem - the case of agricultural wetland drainage in the Canadian Prairies. Agricultural wetland drainage expands the amount of productive agricultural land, increasing agricultural efficiency and productivity. Drainage is also one of the primary drivers of the loss of Canada’s wetlands and is a hotly contentious issue between actors with divergent views and values in the Canadian Prairies. Using the nuances of drainage as an exemplar, we discuss how fragmented framings of water foster perspectives and solutions that fail to consider the full range of aspects and interactions, and contribute to the enduring conflicts that accompany drainage debates in many regions. First, we discuss agricultural wetland drainage as practiced in the province of Saskatchewan, where significant regulatory and governance changes are in progress. Next, we discuss the challenges of policy and governance fragmentation, both specific to water and to the surrounding system. Finally, we note potential alternative framings that, while specific to prairie water governance, provide guidance for how other complex social-ecological challenges might be approached.</abstract><url hash="40765db6">2018.GWF-1.25</url><doi>10.3389/fenvs.2018.00129</doi><bibkey>Breen-etal-2018-When</bibkey></paper><paper id="26"><title>A global meta-analysis of groundwater quality valuation studies</title><author><first>R.</first><last>Brouwer</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Neverre</last></author><abstract>
 A global meta-analysis consisting of almost three decades of groundwater quality valuation studies is presented. New in this study is the focus on the uncertainties surrounding different groundwater quality levels and the control included for groundwater contaminants originating from agriculture and other sources. Separate meta-regression models are estimated for the USA, Europe and the World, detecting sensitivity to scope and reference dependence. Public willingness to pay appears more sensitive to uncertainty in the baseline scenario than in the policy scenario. The high explanatory power of the estimated meta-regression models and low prediction errors provide confidence in their usefulness for reliable benefits transfer.</abstract><url hash="d97f0c0c">2018.GWF-1.26</url><doi>10.1093/ERAE/JBY043</doi><bibkey>Brouwer-etal-2018-A</bibkey></paper><paper id="27"><title>Economic valuation of groundwater protection using a groundwater quality ladder based on chemical threshold levels</title><author><first>R.</first><last>Brouwer</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>M. Ordens</last></author><author><first>Rutte</first><last>Pinto</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>T. C. Melo</last></author><abstract /><url hash="ae783c9a">2018.GWF-1.27</url><doi>10.1016/J.ECOLIND.2018.01.041</doi><bibkey>Brouwer-etal-2018-Economic</bibkey></paper><paper id="28"><title>Temporal Patterns of Wildfire Activity in Areas of Contrasting Human Influence in the Canadian Boreal Forest</title><author><first>Rodrigo</first><last>Campos-Ruiz</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Parisien</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Flannigan</last></author><abstract>The influence of humans on the boreal forest has altered the temporal and spatial patterns of wildfire activity through modification of the physical environment and through fire management for the protection of human and economic values. Wildfires are actively suppressed in areas with higher human influence, but, paradoxically, these areas have more numerous ignitions than low-impact ones because of the high rates of human-ignited fires, especially during the springtime. The aim of this study is to evaluate how humans have altered the temporal patterns of wildfire activity in the Canadian boreal forest by comparing two adjacent areas of low and high human influence, respectively: Wood Buffalo National Park (WBNP) and the Lower Athabasca Plains (LAP). We carried out Singular Spectrum Analysis to identify trends and cycles in wildfires from 1970 to 2015 for the two areas and examined their association with climate conditions. We found human influence to be reflected in wildfire activity in multiple ways: (1) by dampening (i.e., for area burned)—and even reversing (i.e., for the number of fires)—the increasing trends of fire activity usually associated with drier and warmer conditions; (2) by shifting the peak of fire activity from the summer to the spring; (3) by altering the fire-climate association; and (4) by exhibiting more recurrent ( 9 years).</abstract><url hash="3ec7210b">2018.GWF-1.28</url><doi>10.3390/F9040159</doi><bibkey>Campos-Ruiz-etal-2018-Temporal</bibkey></paper><paper id="29"><title>Global sea-level budget 1993–present</title><author><first>A.</first><last>Cazenave</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Meyssignac</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Ablain</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Balmaseda</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Bamber</last></author><author><first>V.</first><last>Barletta</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Beckley</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Benveniste</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Berthier</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Blazquez</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Boyer</last></author><author><first>Denise</first><last>Cáceres</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Chambers</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Champollion</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Chao</last></author><author><first>Jianli</first><last>Chen</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Cheng</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Church</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Chuter</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Cogley</last></author><author><first>Soenke</first><last>Dangendorf</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Desbruyères</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Döll</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Domingues</last></author><author><first>U.</first><last>Falk</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Famiglietti</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Fenoglio-Marc</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Forsberg</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Galassi</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Gardner</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Groh</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Hamlington</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Hogg</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Horwath</last></author><author><first>V.</first><last>Humphrey</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Husson</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Ishii</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Jaeggi</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Jevrejeva</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Johnson</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Kolodziejczyk</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Kusche</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Lambeck</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Landerer</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Leclercq</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Legrésy</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Leuliette</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Llovel</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Longuevergne</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Loomis</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Luthcke</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Marcos</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Marzeion</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Merchant</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Merrifield</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Milne</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Mitchum</last></author><author><first>Yara</first><last>Mohajerani</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Monier</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Monselesan</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Nerem</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Palanisamy</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Paul</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Pérez</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Piecuch</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Ponte</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Purkey</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Reager</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Rietbroek</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Rignot</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Riva</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Roemmich</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Sørensen</last></author><author><first>I.</first><last>Sasgen</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Schram</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Seneviratne</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Shum</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Spada</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Stammer</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>V. D. Wal</last></author><author><first>I.</first><last>Velicogna</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Schuckmann</last></author><author><first>Y.</first><last>Wada</last></author><author><first>Yiguo</first><last>Wang</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Watson</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Wiese</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Wijffels</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Westaway</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Wöppelmann</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Wouters</last></author><abstract>Abstract. Global mean sea level is an integral of changes occurring in the climate system in response to unforced climate variability as well as natural and anthropogenic forcing factors. Its temporal evolution allows changes (e.g., acceleration) to be detected in one or more components. Study of the sea-level budget provides constraints on missing or poorly known contributions, such as the unsurveyed deep ocean or the still uncertain land water component. In the context of the World Climate Research Programme Grand Challenge entitled Regional Sea Level and Coastal Impacts, an international effort involving the sea-level community worldwide has been recently initiated with the objective of assessing the various datasets used to estimate components of the sea-level budget during the altimetry era (1993 to present). These datasets are based on the combination of a broad range of space-based and in situ observations, model estimates, and algorithms. Evaluating their quality, quantifying uncertainties and identifying sources of discrepancies between component estimates is extremely useful for various applications in climate research. This effort involves several tens of scientists from about 50 research teams/institutions worldwide (www.wcrp-climate.org/grand-challenges/gc-sea-level, last access: 22 August 2018). The results presented in this paper are a synthesis of the first assessment performed during 2017–2018. We present estimates of the altimetry-based global mean sea level (average rate of 3.1 ± 0.3 mm yr−1 and acceleration of 0.1 mm yr−2 over 1993–present), as well as of the different components of the sea-level budget (http://doi.org/10.17882/54854, last access: 22 August 2018). We further examine closure of the sea-level budget, comparing the observed global mean sea level with the sum of components. Ocean thermal expansion, glaciers, Greenland and Antarctica contribute 42 %, 21 %, 15 % and 8 % to the global mean sea level over the 1993–present period. We also study the sea-level budget over 2005–present, using GRACE-based ocean mass estimates instead of the sum of individual mass components. Our results demonstrate that the global mean sea level can be closed to within 0.3 mm yr−1 (1σ). Substantial uncertainty remains for the land water storage component, as shown when examining individual mass contributions to sea level.
</abstract><url hash="49c0119d">2018.GWF-1.29</url><doi>10.5194/ESSD-10-1551-2018</doi><bibkey>Cazenave-etal-2018-Global</bibkey></paper><paper id="30"><title>Optimized Storing of Workflow Outputs through Mining Association Rules</title><author><first>Debasish</first><last>Chakroborti</last></author><author><first>Manishankar</first><last>Mondal</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>Kevin</first><last>A. Schneider</last></author><abstract>Workflows are frequently built and used to systematically process large datasets using workflow management systems (WMS). A workflow (i.e., a pipeline) is a finite set of processing modules organized as a series of steps that is applied to an input dataset to produce a desired output. In a workflow management system, users generally create workflows manually for their own investigations. However, workflows can sometimes be lengthy and the constituent processing modules might often be computationally expensive. In this situation, it would be beneficial if users could reuse intermediate stage results generated by previously executed workflows for executing their current workflow.In this paper, we propose a novel technique based on association rule mining for suggesting which intermediate stage results from a workflow that a user is going to execute should be stored for reusing in the future. We call our proposed technique, RISP (Recommending Intermediate States from Pipelines). According to our investigation on hundreds of workflows from two scientific workflow management systems, our proposed technique can efficiently suggest intermediate state results to store for future reuse. The results that are suggested to be stored have a high reuse frequency. Moreover, for creating around 51% of the entire pipelines, we can reuse results suggested by our technique. Finally, we can achieve a considerable gain (74% gain) in execution time by reusing intermediate results stored by the suggestions provided by our proposed technique. We believe that our technique (RISP) has the potential to have a significant positive impact on Big-Data systems, because it can considerably reduce execution time of the workflows through appropriate reuse of intermediate state results, and hence, can improve the performance of the systems.</abstract><url hash="29079878">2018.GWF-1.30</url><doi>10.1109/BigData.2018.8622351</doi><bibkey>Chakroborti-etal-2018-Optimized</bibkey></paper><paper id="31"><title>Carbon, water and energy exchange dynamics of a young pine plantation forest during the initial fourteen years of growth</title><author><first>Felix</first><last>Chan</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>A. Arain</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Khomik</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Brodeur</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Peichl</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Restrepo-Coupe</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Thorne</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Beamesderfer</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>McKenzie</last></author><author><first>Bing-Cheng</first><last>Xu</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Croft</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Pejam</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Trant</last></author><author><first>Michelle</first><last>Kula</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Skubel</last></author><abstract /><url hash="5e00a8ee">2018.GWF-1.31</url><doi>10.1016/J.FORECO.2017.12.024</doi><bibkey>Chan-etal-2018-Carbon,</bibkey></paper><paper id="32"><title>Remote sensing of ecosystem trajectories as a proxy indicator for watershed water balance</title><author><first>L.</first><last>Chasmer</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Devito</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Hopkinson</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Petrone</last></author><abstract>Ecosystem trajectories are inextricably linked to hydrology; however, water availability is not easily observed within the landscape. The response of vegetation to soil water availability may provide an indicator of local hydrology and the resilience or sensitivity of ecosystems to long‐term changes in water balance. In this study, vegetation trajectories derived from Landsat Modified Soil Adjusted Vegetation Index over a 22‐year period are used as an indicator of spatio‐temporal changes of watershed water balance and surface water storage within 6 proximal watersheds of the Boreal Plains ecozone of Alberta, Canada. The interactions between hydrology, topography, geology, and land cover type are examined as they relate to vegetation change.</abstract><url hash="c709f954">2018.GWF-1.32</url><doi>10.1002/eco.1987</doi><bibkey>Chasmer-etal-2018-Remote</bibkey></paper><paper id="33"><title>Perfluorobutanesulfonate Exposure Causes Durable and Transgenerational Dysbiosis of Gut Microbiota in Marine Medaka</title><author><first>Lianguo</first><last>Chen</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Lam</last></author><author><first>Chenyan</first><last>Hu</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>M. Tsui</last></author><author><first>Qi</first><last>Wang</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Giesy</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Lam</last></author><abstract>Environmental pollutants are known as disruptors of gut microbiota. However, it remains unexplored whether the dysbiosis of gut microbiota by pollutants is durable and transgenerational in teleost. Therefore, this study exposed eggs of marine medaka to environmentally realistic concentrations (0, 1.0, 2.9, or 9.5 μg/L) of perfluorobutanesulfonate (PFBS), a persistent organic pollutant of emerging concern, until sexual maturity. A proportion of F0 adults was dissected after exposure (F0-exposed). Remaining fish were depurated in clean seawater (F0-depurated). F1 offspring were also cultured in clean seawater for a complete life-cycle. Substantial amounts of PFBS were accumulated in F0-exposed intestines, while F1 intestines contained no PFBS. Significant alterations were observed in physiological activities of F0-exposed and F1 medaka. The gut microbial community in F0-exposed, F0-depurated, and F1 medaka were restructured in a concentration-dependent manner by PFBS exposure. Dysbiosis of gut microbiota ca...</abstract><url hash="b00ec9c2">2018.GWF-1.33</url><doi>10.1021/ACS.ESTLETT.8B00597</doi><bibkey>Chen-etal-2018-Perfluorobutanesulfonate</bibkey></paper><paper id="34"><title>Temporal Dynamics of Aerodynamic Canopy Height Derived From Eddy Covariance Momentum Flux Data Across North American Flux Networks</title><author><first>H.</first><last>Chu</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Baldocchi</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Poindexter</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Abraha</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Desai</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Bohrer</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>A. Arain</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Griffis</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Blanken</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>O'Halloran</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Q. Thomas</last></author><author><first>Quan</first><last>Zhang</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Burns</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Frank</last></author><author><first>Dold</first><last>Christian</last></author><author><first>Shannon</first><last>Brown</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>A. Black</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Gough</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Law</last></author><author><first>X.</first><last>Lee</last></author><author><first>Jiquan</first><last>Chen</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Reed</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Massman</last></author><author><first>Kenneth</first><last>Clark</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Hatfield</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Prueger</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Bracho</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Baker</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Martin</last></author><abstract>Aerodynamic canopy height (ha) is the effective height of vegetation canopy for its influence on atmospheric fluxes and is a key parameter of surface‐atmosphere coupling. However, methods to estimate ha from data are limited. This synthesis evaluates the applicability and robustness of the calculation of ha from eddy covariance momentum‐flux data. At 69 forest sites, annual ha robustly predicted site‐to‐site and year‐to‐year differences in canopy heights (R2 = 0.88, 111 site‐years). At 23 cropland/grassland sites, weekly ha successfully captured the dynamics of vegetation canopies over growing seasons (R2 &gt; 0.70 in 74 site‐years). Our results demonstrate the potential of flux‐derived ha determination for tracking the seasonal, interannual, and/or decadal dynamics of vegetation canopies including growth, harvest, land use change, and disturbance. The large‐scale and time‐varying ha derived from flux networks worldwide provides a new benchmark for regional and global Earth system models and satellite remote sensing of canopy structure.</abstract><url hash="2e6a5c61">2018.GWF-1.34</url><doi>10.1029/2018GL079306</doi><bibkey>Chu-etal-2018-Temporal</bibkey></paper><paper id="35"><title>Nutrient Release from Living and Terminated Cover Crops Under Variable Freeze–Thaw Cycles</title><author><first>James</first><last>R. Cober</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Macrae</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>V. Eerd</last></author><abstract>Agronomy Journa l • Volume 110 , I s sue 3 • 2018 Elevated levels of P transported into aquatic ecosystems from agricultural watersheds have contributed to the eutrophication of surface water bodies in Canada as well as freshwater habitats around the world (Smith et al., 1998; Schindler et al., 2012; Michalak et al., 2013; Jarvie et al., 2017). In salt water environments, eutrophication has been linked to anthropogenic N inputs (Gruber and Galloway, 2008; Congreves and Van Eerd, 2015). Eutrophication is problematic as it impacts both ecosystem and human health (Anderson et al., 2002), which reduces the recreational value of lakes as well as their potential use as drinking water sources (Smith et al., 1998, 2015). Consequently, there is significant pressure to reduce the export of P and N from surrounding watersheds (International Joint Commission, 2014). Although researchers and environmental managers have attempted to manage nutrient export for decades (Sharpley et al., 1994), the occurrence of large algal blooms has increased due to a combination of climate drivers as well as the large intensity of agricultural land use in surrounding watersheds (e.g. Michalak et al., 2013; Smith et al., 2015). There is also evidence that the elevated P loads from agricultural systems may be an unintended consequence of conservation practices (Jarvie et al., 2017). Thus, an improved understanding of the efficacy of best management practices (BMPs) is needed, and potential unintended consequences must be identified and quantified. The use of CC is a conservation practice that is growing in popularity (Wayman et al., 2016; Statistics Canada, 2017). Cover crops are plants grown by farmers for their benefits to the soil, environment, and future crop yields (Snapp et al., 2005; Blanco-Canqui et al., 2015). Cover crops have the benefit of reducing particulate P losses associated with soil erosion; however, concern has been raised about their potential to release dissolved reactive P (Tukey, 1970; Sharpley et al., 1994; Sturite et al., 2007; Liu et al., 2014). Phosphorus loss through leaching is typically minor; however, certain conditions and mechanical processes have been found to increase the concentration of nutrients in leachate (Tukey and Morgan, 1963; Bechmann et al., 2005; Lozier and Macrae, 2017; Lozier et al., 2017). Of particular importance for northern temperate regions is the effect of freezing on P release from plants, Nutrient Release from Living and Terminated Cover Crops Under Variable Freeze–Thaw Cycles</abstract><url hash="596d6cf7">2018.GWF-1.35</url><doi>10.2134/AGRONJ2017.08.0449</doi><bibkey>R. Cober-etal-2018-Nutrient</bibkey></paper><paper id="36"><title>Using Snowfall Intensity to Improve the Correction of Wind-Induced 
Undercatch in Solid Precipitation Measurements</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Colli</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Stagnaro</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Lanza</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Rasmussen</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Thériault</last></author><abstract>Abstract. Transfer functions are generally used to adjust for the wind-induced undercatch of solid precipitation measurements. These functions are derived based on the variation of the collection efficiency with wind speed for a particular type of gauge, either using field experiments or based on numerical simulation. Most studies use the wind speed alone, while others also include surface air temperature and/or precipitation type to try to reduce the scatter of the residuals at a given wind speed. In this study, we propose the use of the measured precipitation intensity to improve the effectiveness of the transfer function. This is achieved by applying optimized curve fitting to field measurements from the Marshall field-test site (CO, USA). The use of a non-gradient optimization algorithm ensures optimal binning of experimental data according to the parameter under test. The results reveal that using precipitation intensity as an explanatory variable significantly reduce the scatter of the residuals. The scatter reduction as indicated by the Root Mean Square Error (RMSE) is confirmed by the analysis of the recent quality controlled data from the WMO/SPICE campaign, showing that this approach can be applied to a variety of locations and catching-type gauges. We demonstrate the physical basis of the relationship between the collection efficiency and the measured precipitation intensity, due to the correlation of large particles with high intensities, by conducting a Computational Fluid-Dynamics (CFD) simulation. We use a Reynolds Averaged Navier-Stokes SST k-ω model coupled with a Lagrangian particle-tracking model. Results validate the hypothesis of using the measured precipitation intensity as a key parameter to improve the correction of wind-induced undercatch. Findings have the potential to improve operational measurements since no additional instrument other than a wind sensor is required to apply the correction. This improves the accuracy of precipitation measurements without the additional cost of ancillary instruments such as particle counters.
</abstract><url hash="c0643d4d">2018.GWF-1.36</url><doi>10.5194/HESS-2018-447</doi><bibkey>Colli-etal-2018-Using</bibkey></paper><paper id="37"><title>The Influence of Shallow Taliks on Permafrost Thaw and Active Layer Dynamics in Subarctic Canada</title><author><first>R.</first><last>Connon</last></author><author><first>É.</first><last>Devoie</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Hayashi</last></author><author><first>Tyler</first><last>Veness</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Quinton</last></author><abstract>Measurements of active layer thickness (ALT) are typically taken at the end of summer, a time synonymous with maximum thaw depth. By definition, the active layer is the layer above permafrost that freezes and thaws annually. This study, conducted in peatlands of subarctic Canada, in the zone of thawing discontinuous permafrost, demonstrates that the entire thickness of ground atop permafrost does not always refreeze over winter. In these instances, a talik exists between the permafrost and active layer, and ALT must therefore be measured by the depth of refreeze at the end of winter. As talik thickness increases at the expense of the underlying permafrost, ALT is shown to simultaneously decrease. This suggests that the active layer has a maximum thickness that is controlled by the amount of energy lost from the ground to the atmosphere during winter. The taliks documented in this study are relatively thin (&lt;2 m) and exist on forested peat plateaus. The presence of taliks greatly affects the stability of the underlying permafrost. Vertical permafrost thaw was found to be significantly greater in areas with taliks (0.07 m year−1) than without (0.01 m year−1). Furthermore, the spatial distribution of areas with taliks increased between 2011 and 2015 from 20% to 48%, a phenomenon likely caused by an anomalously large ground heat flux input in 2012. Rapid talik development and accelerated permafrost thaw indicates that permafrost loss may exhibit a nonlinear response to warming temperatures. Documentation of refreeze depths and talik development is needed across the circumpolar north.</abstract><url hash="b7630ddb">2018.GWF-1.37</url><doi>10.1002/2017JF004469</doi><bibkey>Connon-etal-2018-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="38"><title>Challenges in Modeling Turbulent Heat Fluxes to Snowpacks in Forest Clearings</title><author><first>J.</first><last>Conway</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pomeroy</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Helgason</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Kinar</last></author><abstract>
 Forest clearings are common features of evergreen forests and produce snowpack accumulation and melt differing from that in adjacent forests and open terrain. This study has investigated the challenges in specifying the turbulent fluxes of sensible and latent heat to snowpacks in forest clearings. The snowpack in two forest clearings in the Canadian Rockies was simulated using a one-dimensional (1D) snowpack model. A trade-off was found between optimizing against measured snow surface temperature or snowmelt when choosing how to specify the turbulent fluxes. Schemes using the Monin–Obukhov similarity theory tended to produce negatively biased surface temperature, while schemes that enhanced turbulent fluxes, to reduce the surface temperature bias, resulted in too much melt. Uncertainty estimates from Monte Carlo experiments showed that no realistic parameter set could successfully remove biases in both surface temperature and melt. A simple scheme that excludes atmospheric stability correction was required to successfully simulate surface temperature under low wind speed conditions. Nonturbulent advective fluxes and/or nonlocal sources of turbulence are thought to account for the maintenance of heat exchange in low-wind conditions. The simulation of snowmelt was improved by allowing enhanced latent heat fluxes during low-wind conditions. Caution is warranted when snowpack models are optimized on surface temperature, as model tuning may compensate for deficiencies in conceptual and numerical models of radiative, conductive, and turbulent heat exchange at the snow surface and within the snowpack. Such model tuning could have large impacts on the melt rate and timing of the snow-free transition in simulations of forest clearings within hydrological and meteorological models.</abstract><url hash="27dc104a">2018.GWF-1.38</url><doi>10.1175/JHM-D-18-0050.1</doi><bibkey>Conway-etal-2018-Challenges</bibkey></paper><paper id="39"><title>A numerical model for the simulation of snowpack solute dynamics to capture runoff ionic pulses during snowmelt: The PULSE model</title><author><first>D.</first><last>Costa</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pomeroy</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Wheater</last></author><abstract /><url hash="50db20dc">2018.GWF-1.39</url><doi>10.1016/J.ADVWATRES.2018.09.008</doi><bibkey>Costa-etal-2018-A</bibkey></paper><paper id="40"><title>Sustainable Ice-Jam Flood Management for Socio-Economic and Socio-Ecological Systems</title><author><first>A.</first><last>Das</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Reed</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Lindenschmidt</last></author><abstract>Ice jams are critical components of the hydraulic regimes of rivers in cold regions. In addition to contributing to the maintenance of wetland ecology, including aquatic animals and waterfowl, ice jams provide essential moisture and nutrient replenishment to perched lakes and ponds in northern inland deltas. However, river ice-jam flooding can have detrimental impacts on in-stream aquatic ecosystems, cause damage to property and infrastructure, and present hazards to riverside communities. In order to maintain sustainable communities and ecosystems, ice-jam flooding must be both mitigated and promoted. This study reviews various flood management strategies used worldwide, and points to the knowledge gaps in these strategies. The main objective of the paper is to provide a framework for a sustainable ice-jam flood management strategy in order to better protect riverine socio-economic and socio-ecological systems. Sustainable flood management must be a carefully adopted and integrated strategy that includes both economic and ecological perspectives in order to mitigate ice-jam flooding in riverside socio-economic systems, while at the same time promoting ice-jam flooding of riverine socio-ecological systems such as inland deltas.</abstract><url hash="66460ebf">2018.GWF-1.40</url><doi>10.3390/W10020135</doi><bibkey>Das-etal-2018-Sustainable</bibkey></paper><paper id="41"><title>Current inventory approach overestimates the effect of irrigated crop management on soil-derived greenhouse gas emissions in the semi-arid Canadian Prairies</title><author><first>C.</first><last>David</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Lemke</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Helgason</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Farrell</last></author><abstract /><url hash="11413e29">2018.GWF-1.41</url><doi>10.1016/J.AGWAT.2018.06.006</doi><bibkey>David-etal-2018-Current</bibkey></paper><paper id="42"><title>Potential influence of nutrient availability along a hillslope: Peatland gradient on aspen recovery following fire</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Depante</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Petrone</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Devito</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Kettridge</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Macrae</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Mendoza</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Waddington</last></author><abstract>The Boreal Plains (BP) of Western Canada have been exposed to increasing disturbance by wildfire and host a mixture of upland‐wetland‐pond complexes with substantial quantities of trembling aspen (Populus tremuloides Michx.) throughout the terrestrial areas. The ability of these tree species to regenerate within both upland and wetland areas of the BP following wildfire is unclear. The purpose of this study was to investigate the influence of fire on nutrient dynamics in soil and water in peatlands and forested landscapes in the BP and relate this to aspen regeneration. Nutrient concentrations, nutrient supply rates, and net nutrient mineralization rates were determined in burned and unburned sections of a peatland and forest and compared with the regeneration of aspen. NO3−, NH4+, and P varied spatially throughout the landscape, and differences were observed between peatland and upland areas. In general, differences in nutrient dynamics were not observed between burned and unburned areas, with the exception of P. Nutrient and growth data suggest that aspen do not require nutrient‐rich conditions for regeneration and instead relied on forest litter to satisfy nutrient demands. Although the peatlands contained high nutrients, aspen did not flourish in the combination of anoxic and aerobic organic‐rich soils present in this area. Although aspen may use peat water and nutrients through their rooting zones, peatlands are unsuitable for aspen re‐establishment in the long‐term. However, the combination of abundant nutrients in surface mineral soils in peat margins may indicate the vulnerability of margins to upland transformations in later successional stages.</abstract><url hash="88486f93">2018.GWF-1.42</url><doi>10.1002/eco.1955</doi><bibkey>Depante-etal-2018-Potential</bibkey></paper><paper id="43"><title>Missing pieces to modeling the Arctic-Boreal puzzle</title><author><first>J.</first><last>Fisher</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Hayes</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Schwalm</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Huntzinger</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Stofferahn</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Schaefer</last></author><author><first>Yiqi</first><last>Luo</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Wullschleger</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Goetz</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Miller</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Griffith</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Chadburn</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Chatterjee</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Ciais</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Douglas</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Genet</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Ito</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Neigh</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Poulter</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Rogers</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Sonnentag</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Tian</last></author><author><first>Weile</first><last>Wang</last></author><author><first>Yong-Lai</first><last>Xue</last></author><author><first>Zong‐Liang</first><last>Yang</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Zeng</last></author><author><first>Zhen</first><last>Zhang</last></author><abstract>NASA has launched the decade-long Arctic-Boreal Vulnerability Experiment (ABoVE). While the initial phases focus on field and airborne data collection, early integration with modeling activities is important to benefit future modeling syntheses. We compiled feedback from ecosystem modeling teams on key data needs, which encompass carbon biogeochemistry, vegetation, permafrost, hydrology, and disturbance dynamics. A suite of variables was identified as part of this activity with a critical requirement that they are collected concurrently and representatively over space and time. Individual projects in ABoVE may not capture all these needs, and thus there is both demand and opportunity for the augmentation of field observations, and synthesis of the observations that are collected, to ensure that science questions and integrated modeling activities are successfully implemented.</abstract><url hash="ff4f5f05">2018.GWF-1.43</url><doi>10.1088/1748-9326/aa9d9a</doi><bibkey>Fisher-etal-2018-Missing</bibkey></paper><paper id="44"><title>A review and synthesis of hysteresis in hydrology and hydrological modeling: Memory, path-dependency, or missing physics?</title><author><first>S.</first><last>Gharari</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Razavi</last></author><abstract /><url hash="612bcaa6">2018.GWF-1.44</url><doi>10.1016/J.JHYDROL.2018.06.037</doi><bibkey>Gharari-etal-2018-A</bibkey></paper><paper id="45"><title>Wildfire as a major driver of recent permafrost thaw in boreal peatlands</title><author><first>C.</first><last>Gibson</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Chasmer</last></author><author><first>Dan</first><last>K. Thompson</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Quinton</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Flannigan</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Olefeldt</last></author><abstract /><url hash="162cfa30">2018.GWF-1.45</url><doi>10.1038/s41467-018-05457-1</doi><bibkey>Gibson-etal-2018-Wildfire</bibkey></paper><paper id="46"><title>Ecohydrological functioning of an upland undergoing reclamation on post‐mining landscape of the Athabasca oil sands region, Canada</title><author><first>T.</first><last>Gingras-Hill</last></author><author><first>Felix</first><last>C. Nwaishi</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Macrae</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Price</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Petrone</last></author><abstract>Ecohydrological functioning of natural Boreal forest in Canada's Boreal Plains is a product of interactions between soil hydrophysical characteristics and hydrogeochemical processes. These interactions create a moisture–nutrient gradient within the surface soils, increasing along low‐relief transitions from upland to riparian zone, and in turn influence the distribution of vegetation communities. It is not yet known if/when analogous ecohydrological functions can be achieved in constructed uplands following industrial disturbance, such as that following oil sands development. Hence, to assess this, we studied interactions between hydrogeochemical processes and vegetation colonization in a constructed upland relative to hydrophysical properties of 2 reclamation cover substrates during a typical continental climate's growing season. Our results indicated that in 3 years of postconstruction, the establishment of a moisture–nutrient gradient that supports vegetation colonization along slope positions was still limited by heterogeneity of cover substrates. Portions of the upland under peat–mineral mix were characterized by lower nutrient availability, high moisture content, and establishment of planted shrubs and trees. In contrast, forest floor materials plots were characterized by poor soil quality, but higher nutrient availability and greater colonization of invasive grasses and native shrubs. We suggest that the colonization of underdeveloped soils by invasive grasses may facilitate pedogenic processes and thus should be accepted by reclamation managers as a successional milestone in the recovery of ecohydrological functioning of constructed uplands. Poor soil structure under forest floor materials could not support edaphic conditions required by plants to efficiently utilize fertilizer, making this practise futile at the early stage of soil development.</abstract><url hash="8f25ab8a">2018.GWF-1.46</url><doi>10.1002/eco.1941</doi><bibkey>Gingras-Hill-etal-2018-Ecohydrological</bibkey></paper><paper id="47"><title>Reselection Yielding a Smaller and More Active Silver-Specific DNAzyme</title><author><first>Lide</first><last>Gu</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Saran</last></author><author><first>Wanli</first><last>Yan</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>J. Huang</last></author><author><first>Shujun</first><last>Wang</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Lyu</last></author><author><first>Juewen</first><last>Liu</last></author><abstract>Ag10c is a recently reported RNA-cleaving DNAzyme obtained from in vitro selection. Its cleavage activity selectively requires Ag+ ions, and thus it has been used as a sensor for Ag+ detection. However, the previous selection yielded very limited information regarding its sequence requirement, since only ∼0.1% of the population in the final library were related to Ag10c and most other sequences were inactive. In this work, we performed a reselection by randomizing the 19 important nucleotides in Ag10c in such a way that a purine has an equal chance of being A or G, whereas a pyrimidine has an equal chance of being T or C. The round 3 library of the reselection was carefully analyzed and a statistic understanding of the relative importance of each nucleotide was obtained. At the same time, a more active mutant was identified, containing two mutated nucleotides. Further analysis indicated new base pairs leading to an enzyme with smaller catalytic loops but with ∼200% activity of the original Ag10c, and also excellent selectivity for Ag+. Therefore, a more active mutant of Ag10c was obtained and further truncations were successfully performed, which might be better candidates for developing new biosensors for silver. A deeper biochemical understanding was also obtained using this reselection method.</abstract><url hash="f8229b1c">2018.GWF-1.47</url><doi>10.1021/acsomega.8b02039</doi><bibkey>Gu-etal-2018-Reselection</bibkey></paper><paper id="48"><title>Observing Scattering Mechanisms of Bubbled Freshwater Lake Ice Using Polarimetric RADARSAT-2 (C-Band) and UW-Scat (X- and Ku-Bands)</title><author><first>G.</first><last>Gunn</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Duguay</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Atwood</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>King</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Toose</last></author><abstract>A winter time series of ground-based (X- and Ku-bands) scatterometer and spaceborne synthetic aperture radar (SAR) (C-band) fully polarimetric observations coincident with in situ snow and ice measurements are used to identify the dominant scattering mechanism in bubbled freshwater lake ice in the Hudson Bay Lowlands near Churchill, Manitoba. Scatterometer observations identify two physical sources of backscatter from the ice cover: the snow–ice and ice–water interfaces. Backscatter time series at all frequencies show increases from the ice–water interface prior to the inclusion of tubular bubbles in the ice column based on in situ observations, indicating scattering mechanisms independent of double-bounce scatter. The co-polarized phase difference of interactions at the ice–water interface from both scatterometer and SAR observations is centered at 0° during the time series, also indicating a scattering regime other than double bounce. A Yamaguchi three-component decomposition of the RADARSAT-2 C-band time series is presented, which suggests the dominant scattering mechanism to be single-bounce off the ice–water interface with appreciable surface roughness or preferentially oriented facets, regardless of the presence, absence, or density of tubular bubble inclusions. This paper builds on newly established evidence of single-bounce scattering mechanism for freshwater lake ice and is the first to present a winter time series of ground-based and spaceborne fully polarimetric active microwave observations with polarimetric decompositions for bubbled freshwater lake ice.</abstract><url hash="689d868d">2018.GWF-1.48</url><doi>10.1109/TGRS.2017.2786158</doi><bibkey>Gunn-etal-2018-Observing</bibkey></paper><paper id="49"><title>Revisiting the Basis of Sensitivity Analysis for Dynamical Earth System Models</title><author><first>H.</first><last>Gupta</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Razavi</last></author><abstract>This paper investigates the problem of global sensitivity analysis (GSA) of Dynamical Earth System Models and proposes a basis for how such analyses should be performed. We argue that (a) performance metric‐based approaches to parameter GSA are actually identifiability analyses, (b) the use of a performance metric to assess sensitivity unavoidably distorts the information provided by the model about relative parameter importance, and (c) it is a serious conceptual flaw to interpret the results of such an analysis as being consistent and accurate indications of the sensitivity of the model response to parameter perturbations. Further, because such approaches depend on availability of system state/output observational data, the analysis they provide is necessarily incomplete. Here we frame the GSA problem from first principles, using trajectories of the partial derivatives of model outputs with respect to controlling factors as the theoretical basis for sensitivity, and construct a global sensitivity matrix from which statistical indices of total period time‐aggregate parameter importance, and time series of time‐varying parameter importance, can be inferred. We demonstrate this framework using the HBV‐SASK conceptual hydrologic model applied to the Oldman basin in Canada and show that it disagrees with performance metric‐based methods regarding which parameters exert the strongest controls on model behavior. Further, it is highly efficient, requiring less than 1,000 base samples to obtain stable and robust parameter importance assessments for our 10‐parameter example.</abstract><url hash="1f9ab61b">2018.GWF-1.49</url><doi>10.1029/2018WR022668</doi><bibkey>Gupta-etal-2018-Revisiting</bibkey></paper><paper id="50"><title>Reframing the Challenge of Global Wildfire Threats to Water Supplies</title><author><first>D.</first><last>Hallema</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Robinne</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Bladon</last></author><abstract>The timing, extent, and severity of forest wildfires have increased in many parts of the world in recent decades. These wildfires can have substantial and devastating impacts on water supply, ecohydrological systems, and sociohydrosystems. Existing frameworks to assess the magnitude and spatial extent of these effects generally focus on local processes or services and are not readily transferable to other regions. However, there is a growing need for regional, continental, and global scale indices to assess the potential effect of wildfires on freshwater availability and water supply resilience. Such indices must consider both the individual and compound effects of wildfires. In so doing, this will enable comprehensive insights on the water security paradigm and the value of hydrological services in fire‐affected areas around the globe.</abstract><url hash="7f5d3ffe">2018.GWF-1.50</url><doi>10.1029/2018EF000867</doi><bibkey>Hallema-etal-2018-Reframing</bibkey></paper><paper id="51"><title>Adapting forest management to climate change: The state of science and applications in Canada and the United States</title><author><first>J.</first><last>Halofsky</last></author><author><first>Sheri</first><last>A. Andrews-Key</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>E. Edwards</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Johnston</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Nelson</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Peterson</last></author><author><first>Kristen</first><last>Schmitt</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Swanston</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Williamson</last></author><abstract /><url hash="085a0f68">2018.GWF-1.51</url><doi>10.1016/J.FORECO.2018.02.037</doi><bibkey>Halofsky-etal-2018-Adapting</bibkey></paper><paper id="52"><title>Modeling the Snowpack Energy Balance during Melt under Exposed Crop Stubble</title><author><first>P.</first><last>Harder</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Helgason</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pomeroy</last></author><abstract>
 On the Canadian Prairies, agricultural practices result in millions of hectares of standing crop stubble that gradually emerges during snowmelt. The importance of stubble in trapping wind-blown snow and retaining winter snowfall has been well demonstrated. However, stubble is not explicitly accounted for in hydrological or energy balance snowmelt models. This paper relates measurable stubble parameters (height, width, areal density, and albedo) to the snowpack energy balance and snowmelt with the new, physically based Stubble–Snow–Atmosphere Model (SSAM). Novel process representations of SSAM quantify the attenuation of shortwave radiation by exposed stubble, the sky and vegetation view factors needed to solve longwave radiation terms, and a resistance scheme for stubble–snow–atmosphere fluxes to solve for surface temperatures and turbulent fluxes. SSAM results were compared to observations of radiometric snow-surface temperature, stubble temperature, snow-surface solar irradiance, areal-average turbulent fluxes, and snow water equivalent from two intensive field campaigns during snowmelt in 2015 and 2016 over wheat and canola stubble in Saskatchewan, Canada. Uncalibrated SSAM simulations compared well with these observations, providing confidence in the model structure and parameterization. A sensitivity analysis conducted using SSAM revealed compensatory relationships in energy balance terms that result in a small increase in net snowpack energy as stubble exposure increases.</abstract><url hash="91535ed2">2018.GWF-1.52</url><doi>10.1175/JHM-D-18-0039.1</doi><bibkey>Harder-etal-2018-Modeling</bibkey></paper><paper id="53"><title>Groundwater flow and storage processes in an inactive rock glacier</title><author><first>Jordan</first><last>S. Harrington</last></author><author><first>Alexandra</first><last>Mozil</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Hayashi</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Bentley</last></author><abstract>Groundwater flow through coarse blocky landforms contributes to streamflow in mountain watersheds, yet its role in the alpine hydrologic cycle has received relatively little attention. This study examines the internal structure and hydrogeological characteristics of an inactive rock glacier in the Canadian Rockies using geophysical imaging techniques, analysis of the discharge hydrograph of the spring draining the rock glacier, and chemical and stable isotopic compositions of source waters. The results show that the coarse blocky sediments forming the rock glacier allow the rapid infiltration of snowmelt and rain water to an unconfined aquifer above the bedrock surface. The water flowing through the aquifer is eventually routed via an internal channel parallel to the front of the rock glacier to a spring, which provides baseflow to a headwater stream designated as a critical habitat for an at‐risk cold‐water fish species. Discharge from the rock glacier spring contributes up to 50% of basin streamflow during summer baseflow periods and up to 100% of basin streamflow over winter, despite draining less than 20% of the watershed area. The rock glacier contains patches of ground ice even though it may have been inactive for thousands of years, suggesting the resiliency of the ground thermal regime under a warming climate.</abstract><url hash="e6546e44">2018.GWF-1.53</url><doi>10.1002/hyp.13248</doi><bibkey>S. Harrington-etal-2018-Groundwater</bibkey></paper><paper id="54"><title>Simulation of Nitrate‐N Leaching in No‐Till Fields with DRAINMOD‐N II in a Cold‐Humid Region</title><author><first>S.</first><last>E. Hashemi Garmdareh</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Malekian</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Madani</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Gordon</last></author><abstract>Conservation agriculture, especially no‐tillage, has proven to become sustainable farming in many agricultural environments globally. In spite of advantages of no‐till systems, this practice may result in excess infiltration into the soil and can enhance the movement of mobile nutrients and some pesticides to subsurface drains and groundwater along preferential pathways. The goal of this study was to evaluate the capacity of DRAINMOD‐N II to simulate subsurface nitrate‐N leaching in no‐till fields in Truro, Nova Scotia, Canada, from 2003 to 2006. The model performance was first evaluated by comparing observed and simulated drain outflow data that is an essential prerequisite for the model to obtain a proper prediction of NO3‐N movement, and then by comparing observed and simulated NO3‐N concentration in no‐till fields using three statistical indices, relative root mean square error (RRMSE), average absolute deviation (AAD) and the correlation coefficient (R2). The RRMSE, AAD and R2 for the validation period were determined to be 1.09, 1.85 and 0.83 mm for drain outflow, and 1.43, 0.51 and 0.79 mg l−1 for NO3‐N concentration respectively. The results showed that DRAINMOD‐N II predicted NO3‐N leaching reasonably well in drainage outflow of no‐till fields over the whole period. Copyright © 2018 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</abstract><url hash="7830fbe7">2018.GWF-1.54</url><doi>10.1002/ird.2200</doi><bibkey>E. Hashemi Garmdareh-etal-2018-Simulation</bibkey></paper><paper id="55"><title>Lake O'Hara alpine hydrological observatory: hydrological and meteorological dataset, 2004–2017</title><author><first>Jesse</first><last>He</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Hayashi</last></author><abstract>Abstract. The Lake O'Hara watershed in the Canadian Rockies has been the site of several hydrological
investigations. It has been instrumented to a degree uncommon for many alpine
study watersheds. Air temperature, relative humidity, wind, precipitation,
radiation, and snow depth are measured at two meteorological stations near
Lake O'Hara and in the higher elevation Opabin Plateau. Water levels at Lake
O'Hara, Opabin Lake, and several stream gauging stations are recorded using
pressure transducers and validated against manual measurements.
Stage–discharge rating curves were determined at gauging stations and used
to calculate discharge from stream stage. The database includes additional
data such as water chemistry (temperature, electrical conductivity, and
stable isotope abundance) and snow survey (snow depth and density) for select
years, as well as geospatial data (elevation and land cover). This dataset
will be useful for the future study of alpine regions, where substantial and
long-term hydrological datasets are scarce due to difficult field conditions.
The dataset can be accessed at https://doi.org/10.20383/101.035.
</abstract><url hash="0f37cb71">2018.GWF-1.55</url><doi>10.5194/ESSD-11-111-2019</doi><bibkey>He-etal-2018-Lake</bibkey></paper><paper id="56"><title>Misfolding of a DNAzyme for ultrahigh sodium selectivity over potassium</title><author><first>Yanping</first><last>He</last></author><author><first>Da</first><last>Chen</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>J. Huang</last></author><author><first>Yibo</first><last>Zhou</last></author><author><first>Lingzi</first><last>Ma</last></author><author><first>Kexin</first><last>Xu</last></author><author><first>Ronghua</first><last>Yang</last></author><author><first>Juewen</first><last>Liu</last></author><abstract>Abstract Herein, the excellent Na+ selectivity of a few RNA-cleaving DNAzymes was exploited, where Na+ can be around 3000-fold more effective than K+ for promoting catalysis. By using a double mutant based on the Ce13d DNAzyme, and by lowering the temperature, increased 2-aminopurine (2AP) fluorescence was observed with addition of both Na+ and K+. The fluorescence increase was similar for these two metals at below 10 mM, after which K+ took a different pathway. Since 2AP probes its local base stacking environment, K+ can be considered to induce misfolding. Binding of both Na+ and K+ was specific, since single base mutations could fully inhibit 2AP fluorescence for both metals. The binding thermodynamics was measured by temperature-dependent experiments revealing enthalpy-driven binding for both metals and less coordination sites compared to G-quadruplex DNA. Cleavage activity assays indicated a moderate cleavage activity with 10 mM K+, while further increase of K+ inhibited the activity, also supporting its misfolding of the DNAzyme. For comparison, a G-quadruplex DNA was also studied using the same system, where Na+ and K+ led to the same final state with only around 8-fold difference in Kd. This study provides interesting insights into strategies for discriminating Na+ and K+.</abstract><url hash="963e9acb">2018.GWF-1.56</url><doi>10.1093/nar/gky807</doi><bibkey>He-etal-2018-Misfolding</bibkey></paper><paper id="57"><title>The Cariboo Alpine Mesonet: sub-hourly hydrometeorological observations of British Columbia's Cariboo Mountains and surrounding area since 2006</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Hernández-Henríquez</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Sharma</last></author><author><first>Mark</first><last>E. Taylor</last></author><author><first>Hadleigh</first><last>D. Thompson</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Déry</last></author><abstract>Abstract. This article presents the development of a sub-hourly database of
hydrometeorological conditions collected in British Columbia's (BC's) Cariboo
Mountains and surrounding area extending from 2006 to present. The Cariboo
Alpine Mesonet (CAMnet) forms a network of 11 active hydrometeorological
stations positioned at strategic locations across mid- to high elevations of
the Cariboo Mountains. This mountain region spans 44 150 km2, forming the
northern extension of the Columbia Mountains. Deep fjord lakes along with
old-growth western redcedar and hemlock forests reside in the lower valleys,
montane forests of Engelmann spruce, lodgepole pine and subalpine fir
permeate the mid-elevations, while alpine tundra, glaciers and several
large ice fields cover the higher elevations. The automatic weather stations
typically measure air and soil temperature, relative humidity, atmospheric
pressure, wind speed and direction, rainfall and snow depth at 15 min
intervals. Additional measurements at some stations include shortwave and
longwave radiation, near-surface air, skin, snow, or water temperature, and
soil moisture, among others. Details on deployment sites, the
instrumentation used and its precision, the collection and quality control
process are provided. Instructions on how to access the database at Zenodo,
an online public data repository, are also furnished
(https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1195043). Information on some of the
challenges and opportunities encountered in maintaining continuous and
homogeneous time series of hydrometeorological variables and remote field
sites is provided. The paper also summarizes ongoing plans to expand CAMnet
to better monitor atmospheric conditions in BC's mountainous terrain,
efforts to push data online in (near-)real time, availability of ancillary
data and lessons learned thus far in developing this mesoscale network of
hydrometeorological stations in the data-sparse Cariboo Mountains.
</abstract><url hash="e139aa5d">2018.GWF-1.57</url><doi>10.5194/ESSD-10-1655-2018</doi><bibkey>Hernández-Henríquez-etal-2018-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="58"><title>Criteria-based ranking (CBR): A comprehensive process for selecting and prioritizing monitoring indicators</title><author><first>Elaine</first><last>Ho</last></author><abstract /><url hash="7186b7cc">2018.GWF-1.58</url><doi>10.1016/j.mex.2018.10.015</doi><bibkey>Ho-etal-2018-Criteria-based</bibkey></paper><paper id="59"><title>Assessing current monitoring indicators and reporting for cumulative effects integration: A case study in Muskoka, Ontario, Canada</title><author><first>Elaine</first><last>Ho</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Eger</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Courtenay</last></author><abstract /><url hash="0681875a">2018.GWF-1.59</url><doi>10.1016/J.ECOLIND.2018.08.017</doi><bibkey>Ho-etal-2018-Assessing</bibkey></paper><paper id="60"><title>A hydrogeological landscape framework to identify peatland wildfire smouldering hot spots</title><author><first>K.</first><last>Hokanson</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Moore</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Lukenbach</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Devito</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Kettridge</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Petrone</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Mendoza</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Waddington</last></author><abstract>Northern peatlands are important global carbon stores, but there is concern that these boreal peat reserves are at risk due to increased fire frequency and severity as predicted by climate change models. In a subhumid climate, hydrogeological position is an important control on peatland hydrology and wildfire vulnerability. Consequently, we hypothesized that in a coarse‐textured glaciofluvial outwash, isolated peatlands lacking the moderating effect of large‐scale groundwater flow would have greater water table (WT) variability and would also be more vulnerable to deep WT drawdown and wildfire during dry climate cycles. A holistic approach was taken to evaluate 3 well‐accepted factors that are associated with smouldering in boreal peatlands: hollow microform coverage, peatland margin morphometry, and gravimetric water content. Using a combination of field measurements (bulk density, humification, WT position, hummock–hollow distribution, and margin width) and modelling (1‐D vertical unsaturated flow coupled with a simple peat–fuel energy balance equation), we assessed the vulnerability of peat to smouldering. We found that a peatland in the regionally intermediate topographic position is the most vulnerable to smouldering due to the interaction of variable connectivity to large‐scale groundwater flow and the absence of mineral stratigraphy for limiting WT declines during dry conditions. Our findings represent a novel assessment framework and tool for fire managers by providing a priori knowledge of potential peat smouldering hot spot locations in the landscape to efficiently allocate resources and reduce emergency response time to smouldering events.</abstract><url hash="54706c3d">2018.GWF-1.60</url><doi>10.1002/eco.1942</doi><bibkey>Hokanson-etal-2018-A</bibkey></paper><paper id="61"><title>The Groundwater Recovery Paradox in South India</title><author><first>T.</first><last>Hora</last></author><author><first>V.</first><last>Srinivasan</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Basu</last></author><abstract>Reported groundwater recovery in South India has been attributed to both increasing rainfall and political interventions. Findings of increasing groundwater levels, however, are at odds with reports of well failure and decreases in the land area irrigated from shallow wells. We argue that recently reported results are skewed by the problem of survivor bias, with dry or defunct wells being systematically excluded from trend analyses due to missing data. We hypothesize that these dry wells carry critical information about groundwater stress that is missed when data are filtered. Indeed, we find strong correlations between missing well data and metrics related to climate stress and groundwater development, indicative of a systemic bias. Using two alternative metrics, which take into account information from dry and defunct wells, our results demonstrate increasing groundwater stress in South India. Our refined approach for identifying groundwater depletion hot spots is critical for policy interventions and resource allocation.</abstract><url hash="23775cab">2018.GWF-1.61</url><doi>10.1029/2019GL083525</doi><bibkey>Hora-etal-2018-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="62"><title>[Research Paper] Detecting Evolutionary Coupling Using Transitive Association Rules</title><author><first>Md.</first><last>Anaytul Islam</last></author><author><first>Md.</first><last>Moksedul Islam</last></author><author><first>Manishankar</first><last>Mondal</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>Kevin</first><last>A. Schneider</last></author><abstract>If two or more program entities (such as files, classes, methods) co-change (i.e., change together) frequently during software evolution, then it is likely that these two entities are coupled (i.e., the entities are related). Such a coupling is termed as evolutionary coupling in the literature. The concept of traditional evolutionary coupling restricts us to assume coupling among only those entities that changed together in the past. The entities that did not co-change in the past might also have coupling. However, such couplings can not be retrieved using the current concept of detecting evolutionary coupling in the literature. In this paper, we investigate whether we can detect such couplings by applying transitive rules on the evolutionary couplings detected using the traditional mechanism. We call these couplings that we detect using our proposed mechanism as transitive evolutionary couplings. According to our research on thousands of revisions of four subject systems, transitive evolutionary couplings combined with the traditional ones provide us with 13.96% higher recall and 5.56% higher precision in detecting future co-change candidates when compared with a state-of-the-art technique.</abstract><url hash="ba7e0d11">2018.GWF-1.62</url><doi>10.1109/SCAM.2018.00020</doi><bibkey>Anaytul Islam-etal-2018-[Research</bibkey></paper><paper id="63"><title>A comparative analysis of practitioners' experience in sediment remediation projects to highlight best practices</title><author><first>Zobia</first><last>Jawed</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Krantzberg</last></author><abstract>
 The Randle Reef contaminated site, located in the southwest corner of Hamilton Harbour, is approximately 60 hectares in size. This site contains approximately 695,000 m3 of sediment contaminated with polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) and metals. The complex Randle Reef sediment remediation project is finally coming to fruition after more than 30 years of study, discussion, collaborations, stakeholder consensus-building, and debate. This paper unravels the reasons behind the delays associated with implementing sediment management at the Randle Reef site. In-depth interviews with experts and professionals from organizations who are/were involved in the project were conducted to identify the nature of performance in five theme areas that are important for successful action namely: (1) participation of appropriate actors with common objectives; (2) funding and resources; (3) decision-making process; (4) research and technology development; and (5) public and political support. It is evident from this study that the hurdles to progress with addressing contaminated sediment sites involve technical, political, regulatory as well as social challenges. We offer potential solutions and a series of recommendations based on experts' first-hand experience with the management of such complex sites to inform how future remediation projects can overcome obstacles.
 This article has been made Open Access thanks to the kind support of CAWQ/ACQE (https://www.cawq.ca).</abstract><url hash="cd793d87">2018.GWF-1.63</url><doi>10.2166/WQRJ.2018.020</doi><bibkey>Jawed-etal-2018-A</bibkey></paper><paper id="64"><title>Instantaneous Iodine-Assisted DNAzyme Cleavage of Phosphorothioate RNA.</title><author><first>Po-Jung</first><last>Jimmy Huang</last></author><author><first>Woohyun</first><last>J. Moon</last></author><author><first>Juewen</first><last>Liu</last></author><abstract>Metal ions play a critical role in the RNA-cleavage reaction by interacting with the scissile phosphate and stabilizing the highly negatively charged transition state. Many metal-dependent DNAzymes have been selected for RNA cleavage. Herein, we report that the Ce13d DNAzyme can use nonmetallic iodine (I2) to cleave a phosphorothioate (PS)-modified substrate. The cleavage yield exceeded 60% for both the Rp and Sp stereoisomers in 10 s, while the yield without the enzyme strand was only ∼10%. The Ce13d cleavage with I2 also required Na+, consistent with the property of Ce13d and confirming the similar role of I2 as a metal ion. Ce13d had the highest yield among eight tested DNAzymes, with the second highest DNAzyme showing only 20% cleavage. The incomplete cleavage was due to competition from desulfurization and isomerization reactions. This DNAzyme was engineered for fluorescence-based I2 detection. With EDTA for masking metal ions, I2 was selectively detected down to 4.7 nM. Oxidation of I- with Fe3+ produced I2 in situ, allowing detection of Fe3+ down to 78 nM. By harnessing nonelectrostatic interactions, such as the I2/sulfur interaction observed here, more nonmetal species might be discovered to assist DNAzyme-based RNA cleavage.</abstract><url hash="531da824">2018.GWF-1.64</url><doi>10.1021/acs.biochem.8b00900</doi><bibkey>Jimmy Huang-etal-2018-Instantaneous</bibkey></paper><paper id="65"><title>The Transboundary Impacts of Trade Liberalization and Climate Change on the Nile Basin Economies and Water Resource Availability</title><author><first>T.</first><last>Kahsay</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Kuik</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Brouwer</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Zaag</last></author><abstract /><url hash="241a98b2">2018.GWF-1.65</url><doi>10.1007/s11269-017-1847-7</doi><bibkey>Kahsay-etal-2018-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="66"><title>Beaver‐mediated water table dynamics in a Rocky Mountain fen</title><author><first>D.</first><last>Karran</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Westbrook</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Bedard-Haughn</last></author><abstract>Beaver dams are known to raise water tables in mineral soil environments, but very little is known about their impact in wetlands, such as peatlands. Peatlands tend to have shallow water tables, and the position and tendency of the water table to fluctuate (i.e., stability) is a factor controlling the system's ability to store carbon and water. Many peatland environments, especially fens, offer ideal habitat for beaver, and the potential for beaver dams to influence this link by manipulating water tables requires investigation. Our objective was to determine the influence of beaver dams on the water table dynamics of a Rocky Mountain fen. We monitored water tables in the peatland for 4 years while beaver dams were intact and 2 years after they were breached by an extreme flood event. We found that, because of the unique way in which dams were built, they connected the peatland to the stream and raised and stabilized already high water tables within a 150‐m radius. Beaver‐mediated changes to peatland water table regimes have the potential to enhance carbon sequestration and the peatland's ability to respond to external pressures such as climate change. Furthermore, beaver dams increased surface and groundwater storage, which has implications for regional water balances, especially in times of drought.</abstract><url hash="bd13c908">2018.GWF-1.66</url><doi>10.1002/eco.1923</doi><bibkey>Karran-etal-2018-Beaver‐mediated</bibkey></paper><paper id="67"><title>Risks from Climate Extremes Change Differently from 1.5°C to 2.0°C Depending on Rarity</title><author><first>V.</first><last>Kharin</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Flato</last></author><author><first>X.</first><last>Zhang</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Gillett</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Zwiers</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Anderson</last></author><abstract>Parties to the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change have agreed to hold the “increase in global average temperature to well below 2°C above preindustrial levels and to pursue efforts to limit the temperature increase to 1.5°C.” Comparison of the costs and benefits for different warming limits requires an understanding of how risks vary between warming limits. As changes in risk are often associated with changes in exposure due to projected changes in local or regional climate extremes, we analyze differences in the risks of extreme daily temperatures and extreme daily precipitation amounts under different warming limits. We show that global warming of 2°C would result in substantially larger changes in the probabilities of the extreme events than global warming of 1.5°C. For example, over the global land area, the probability of a warm extreme that occurs once every 20 years on average in the current climate is projected to increase 130% and 340% at the 1.5°C and 2.0°C warming levels, respectively (median values). Moreover, the relative changes in probability are larger for rarer, more extreme events, implying that risk assessments need to carefully consider the extreme event thresholds at which vulnerabilities occur.</abstract><url hash="ca14f99e">2018.GWF-1.67</url><doi>10.1002/2018EF000813</doi><bibkey>Kharin-etal-2018-Risks</bibkey></paper><paper id="68"><title>The influence of snow microstructure on dual-frequency radar measurements in a tundra environment</title><author><first>J.</first><last>King</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Derksen</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Toose</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Langlois</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Larsen</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Lemmetyinen</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Marsh</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Montpetit</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Rutter</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Sturm</last></author><abstract /><url hash="5aabe40f">2018.GWF-1.68</url><doi>10.1016/J.RSE.2018.05.028</doi><bibkey>King-etal-2018-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="69"><title>Hydroclimatic controls on runoff activation in an artificially drained, near‐level vertisolic clay landscape in a Prairie climate</title><author><first>V.</first><last>Kokulan</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Macrae</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Ali</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Lobb</last></author><abstract>Water quality problems are frequently influenced by hydrological processes, particularly in landscapes in which land drainage has been modified. The expansion of agricultural tile drainage in the Northern Great Plains of North America is occurring, yet is controversial due to persistent water quality problems such as eutrophication. Runoff‐generating mechanisms in North American tile‐drained landscapes in vertisolic soils have not been investigated but are important for understanding the impacts of tile drainage on water quantity and quality. This study evaluated the role of climate drivers on the activation of overland (OF) and tile (TF) flow and groundwater flow responses (GWT) on tile‐drained and nontile‐drained farm fields in Southern Manitoba, Canada. The response times of different flow paths (OF, TF, and GWT) were compared for 23 hydrological events (April–September 2015, 2016) to infer dominant runoff generation processes. Runoff responses (all pathways) were more rapid following higher intensity rainfall. Subsurface responses were hastened by wetter antecedent conditions in spring and delayed by the seasonal soil–ice layer. The activation of OF did not differ between the tiled and nontiled fields, suggesting that tile drains do little to reduce the occurrence of OF in this landscape. Rapid vertical preferential flow into tiles via preferential flow pathways was uncommon at our site, and the soil profile instead wet up from the top down. These conclusions have implications for the expansion of tile drainage and the impact of such an expansion on hydrological and biogeochemical processes in agricultural landscapes.</abstract><url hash="2dacd499">2018.GWF-1.69</url><doi>10.1002/hyp.13347</doi><bibkey>Kokulan-etal-2018-Hydroclimatic</bibkey></paper><paper id="70"><title>Effect of climate change and mining on hydrological connectivity of surficial layers in the Athabasca Oil Sands Region</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Kompanizare</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Petrone</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Shafii</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Robinson</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Rooney</last></author><abstract>This research analyses the impact of climate change and surface mining activities on the hydrologic connectivity of surficial (soil and geological) layers located in a watershed in the Athabasca Oil Sands Region. Surface water and groundwater flow are simulated for the period 2014–2080 under four climate scenarios: median (M), double precipitation (DP), no change in precipitation (NP), and double temperature (DT) and with the assumption of no change in the extent of mine activities after 2013. The results demonstrate that the annual growing season duration is longer and snowmelt happens earlier in the year 2080. During the growing season, the daily proportion of connected hydrologic units (DPCUs) remains approximately the same in the future under the different climate scenarios. It appears that around 68% of watershed area, mostly in western and central eastern portions, will be frequently connected (annual proportion of connected days [APCD] ≥ 20%) in the future. This area remains hydrologically connected for more than 20–50% of the year. Results also show that mining areas are located in infrequently connected areas (APCD &lt; 20%), where DPCU values are significantly lower than other areas. DPCUs in forestlands are more stable with a growing season, that is, ~15 days longer than in wetlands. Comparisons between hydrologic responses in 2016 and 2080 show that, in 2080, maximum snow depths are about 0.7 times smaller, evapotranspiration is ~0.05 mm higher, capillary soil moisture in DT and NP scenarios are 1.01–1.52 mm lower, and the ratio of precipitation to potential evapotranspiration is almost the same during the growing season. However, at the end of growing season, the ratio is ~1 unit less in 2080 in DT and NP scenarios. Results also demonstrate that thinner surficial geological layers in the mining areas (located mostly in downstream part of the watershed) lead to their lower hydrologic connectivities. Therefore, these areas are more vulnerable to mining activity impacts, and their hydrologic response under a changing climate should be considered in reclamation planning.</abstract><url hash="4d6b5d7c">2018.GWF-1.70</url><doi>10.1002/hyp.13292</doi><bibkey>Kompanizare-etal-2018-Effect</bibkey></paper><paper id="71"><title>Prairie water: a global water futures project to enhance the resilience of prairie communities through sustainable water management</title><author><first>C.</first><last>Spence</last></author><author><first>Jared</first><last>D. Wolfe</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Whitfield</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Baulch</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Basu</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Bedard-Haughn</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Belcher</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Clark</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Ferguson</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Hayashi</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Liber</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>McDonnell</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Morrissey</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pomeroy</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Reed</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Strickert</last></author><abstract>Christopher Spence, Jared D. Wolfe, Colin J. Whitfield, Helen Margaret Baulch, Nandita B. Basu, Angela K. Bedard-Haughn, Ken W. Belcher, Robert G. Clark, Grant A. Ferguson, Masaki Hayashi, Karsten Liber, Jeff J. McDonnell, Christy A. Morrissey, John W. Pomeroy, Maureen G. Reed and Graham Strickert Environment and Climate Change Canada, Saskatoon, Canada; School of Environment and Sustainability, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Canada; Earth and Environmental Sciences, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Canada; College of Agriculture and Bioresources, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Canada; College of Engineering, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Canada; Department of Geoscience, University of Calgary, Calgary, Canada; Toxicology Centre, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, Canada; College of Arts and Science, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, Canada; Department of Geography and Planning, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Canada</abstract><url hash="3a6c6dea">2018.GWF-1.71</url><doi>10.1080/07011784.2018.1527256</doi><bibkey>Spence-etal-2018-Prairie</bibkey></paper><paper id="72"><title>Disturbance Impacts on Thermal Hot Spots and Hot Moments at the Peatland‐Atmosphere Interface</title><author><first>R.</first><last>Leonard</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Kettridge</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Devito</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Petrone</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Mendoza</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Waddington</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Krause</last></author><abstract>Soil‐surface temperature acts as a master variable driving nonlinear terrestrial ecohydrological, biogeochemical, and micrometeorological processes, inducing short‐lived or spatially isolated extremes across heterogeneous landscape surfaces. However, subcanopy soil‐surface temperatures have been, to date, characterized through isolated, spatially discrete measurements. Using spatially complex forested northern peatlands as an exemplar ecosystem, we explore the high‐resolution spatiotemporal thermal behavior of this critical interface and its response to disturbances by using Fiber‐Optic Distributed Temperature Sensing. Soil‐surface thermal patterning was identified from 1.9 million temperature measurements under undisturbed, trees removed and vascular subcanopy removed conditions. Removing layers of the structurally diverse vegetation canopy not only increased mean temperatures but it shifted the spatial and temporal distribution, range, and longevity of thermal hot spots and hot moments. We argue that linking hot spots and/or hot moments with spatially variable ecosystem processes and feedbacks is key for predicting ecosystem function and resilience.</abstract><url hash="a3653c50">2018.GWF-1.72</url><doi>10.1002/2017GL075974</doi><bibkey>Leonard-etal-2018-Disturbance</bibkey></paper><paper id="73"><title>How Much Information Is Required to Well Constrain Local Estimates of Future Precipitation Extremes?</title><author><first>Chao</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Zwiers</last></author><author><first>Xuebin</first><last>Zhang</last></author><author><first>Guilong</first><last>Li</last></author><abstract>Global warming is expected to increase the amount of atmospheric moisture, resulting in heavier extreme precipitation. Various studies have used the historical relationship between extreme precipitation and temperature (temperature scaling) to provide guidance about precipitation extremes in a future warmer climate. Here we assess how much information is required to robustly identify temperature scaling relationships, and whether these relationships are equally effective at different times in the future in estimating precipitation extremes everywhere across North America. Using a large ensemble of 35 North American regional climate simulations of the period 1951–2100, we show that individual climate simulations of length comparable to that of typical instrumental records are unable to constrain temperature scaling relationships well enough to reliably estimate future extremes of local precipitation accumulation for hourly to daily durations in the model's climate. Hence, temperature scaling relationships estimated from the limited historical observations are unlikely to be able to provide reliable guidance for future adaptation planning at local spatial scales. In contrast, well‐constrained temperature scaling relations based on multiple regional climate simulations do provide a feasible basis for accurately projecting precipitation extremes of hourly to daily durations in different future periods over more than 90% of the North American land area.</abstract><url hash="d4620cc6">2018.GWF-1.73</url><doi>10.1029/2018EF001001</doi><bibkey>Li-etal-2018-How</bibkey></paper><paper id="74"><title>Highly active fluorogenic oxidase-mimicking NiO nanozymes.</title><author><first>Dai</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>Biwu</first><last>Liu</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>J. Huang</last></author><author><first>Zijie</first><last>Zhang</last></author><author><first>Juewen</first><last>Liu</last></author><abstract>Oxidase-mimicking nanozymes are attractive since they do not require H2O2, but such examples are quite rare. In particular, few can catalyze oxidation of fluorogenic substrates. We herein communicate that NiO nanoparticles are an oxidase nanozyme at physiological pH for fluorogenic Amplex red. Its activity is much higher than that of the commonly used nanoceria. This finding fills an urgent gap for biosensor development and intracellular imaging for the nanozyme field.</abstract><url hash="4a069965">2018.GWF-1.74</url><doi>10.1039/c8cc07062h</doi><bibkey>Li-etal-2018-Highly</bibkey></paper><paper id="75"><title>Application of Environmental DNA Metabarcoding for Predicting Anthropogenic Pollution in Rivers.</title><author><first>Feilong</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>Ying</first><last>Peng</last></author><author><first>Wendi</first><last>Fang</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Altermatt</last></author><author><first>Yuwei</first><last>Xie</last></author><author><first>Jianghu</first><last>Yang</last></author><author><first>Xiaowei</first><last>Zhang</last></author><abstract>Rivers are among the most threatened freshwater ecosystems, and anthropogenic activities are affecting both river structures and water quality. While assessing the organisms can provide a comprehensive measure of a river's ecological status, it is limited by the traditional morphotaxonomy-based biomonitoring. Recent advances in environmental DNA (eDNA) metabarcoding allow to identify prokaryotes and eukaryotes in one sequencing run, and could thus allow unprecedented resolution. Whether such eDNA-based data can be used directly to predict the pollution status of rivers as a complementation of environmental data remains unknown. Here we used eDNA metabarcoding to explore the main stressors of rivers along which community structure changes, and to identify the method's potential for predicting pollution status based on eDNA data. We showed that a broad range of taxa in bacterial, protistan, and metazoan communities could be profiled with eDNA. Nutrients were the main driving stressor affecting communities' structure, alpha diversity, and the ecological network. We specifically observed that the relative abundance of indicative OTUs was significantly correlated with nutrient levels. These OTUs data could be used to predict the nutrient status up to 79% accuracy on testing data sets. Thus, our study gives a novel approach to predicting the pollution status of rivers by eDNA data.</abstract><url hash="3d01a9f3">2018.GWF-1.75</url><doi>10.1021/acs.est.8b03869</doi><bibkey>Li-etal-2018-Application</bibkey></paper><paper id="76"><title>Indices of Canada’s future climate for general and agricultural adaptation applications</title><author><first>Guilong</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>Xuebin</first><last>Zhang</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Cannon</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Murdock</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Sobie</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Zwiers</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Anderson</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Qian</last></author><abstract /><url hash="a408f849">2018.GWF-1.76</url><doi>10.1007/s10584-018-2199-x</doi><bibkey>Li-etal-2018-Indices</bibkey></paper><paper id="77"><title>Solar‐induced chlorophyll fluorescence is strongly correlated with terrestrial photosynthesis for a wide variety of biomes: First global analysis based on OCO‐2 and flux tower observations</title><author><first>Xing</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>Jingfeng</first><last>Xiao</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>He</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Altaf Arain</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Beringer</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Desai</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Emmel</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Hollinger</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Krasnova</last></author><author><first>I.</first><last>Mammarella</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Noe</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>S. Ortiz</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>C. Rey-Sanchez</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Rocha</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Varlagin</last></author><abstract>Solar‐induced chlorophyll fluorescence (SIF) has been increasingly used as a proxy for terrestrial gross primary productivity (GPP). Previous work mainly evaluated the relationship between satellite‐observed SIF and gridded GPP products both based on coarse spatial resolutions. Finer resolution SIF (1.3 km × 2.25 km) measured from the Orbiting Carbon Observatory‐2 (OCO‐2) provides the first opportunity to examine the SIF–GPP relationship at the ecosystem scale using flux tower GPP data. However, it remains unclear how strong the relationship is for each biome and whether a robust, universal relationship exists across a variety of biomes. Here we conducted the first global analysis of the relationship between OCO‐2 SIF and tower GPP for a total of 64 flux sites across the globe encompassing eight major biomes. OCO‐2 SIF showed strong correlations with tower GPP at both midday and daily timescales, with the strongest relationship observed for daily SIF at the 757 nm (R2 = 0.72, p &lt; 0.0001). Strong linear relationships between SIF and GPP were consistently found for all biomes (R2 = 0.57–0.79, p &lt; 0.0001) except evergreen broadleaf forests (R2 = 0.16, p &lt; 0.05) at the daily timescale. A higher slope was found for C4 grasslands and croplands than for C3 ecosystems. The generally consistent slope of the relationship among biomes suggests a nearly universal rather than biome‐specific SIF–GPP relationship, and this finding is an important distinction and simplification compared to previous results. SIF was mainly driven by absorbed photosynthetically active radiation and was also influenced by environmental stresses (temperature and water stresses) that determine photosynthetic light use efficiency. OCO‐2 SIF generally had a better performance for predicting GPP than satellite‐derived vegetation indices and a light use efficiency model. The universal SIF–GPP relationship can potentially lead to more accurate GPP estimates regionally or globally. Our findings revealed the remarkable ability of finer resolution SIF observations from OCO‐2 and other new or future missions (e.g., TROPOMI, FLEX) for estimating terrestrial photosynthesis across a wide variety of biomes and identified their potential and limitations for ecosystem functioning and carbon cycle studies.</abstract><url hash="d30fc8df">2018.GWF-1.77</url><doi>10.1111/gcb.14297</doi><bibkey>Li-etal-2018-Solar‐induced</bibkey></paper><paper id="78"><title>Coherence of Radarsat-2, Sentinel-1, and ALOS-1 PALSAR for monitoring spatiotemporal variations of river ice covers</title><author><first>Zhaoqin</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Lindenschmidt</last></author><abstract>ABSTRACT Monitoring spatiotemporal variations of river ice covers is critical for selecting safe ice transportation routes. The coherence of synthetic aperture radar (SAR) interferometry (InSAR) conveys important information on variations of river ice characteristics. However, limited research has been conducted to determine the coherence of multi-frequency L-band ALOS-1 PALSAR, C-band Sentinel-1, and Radarsat-2 images, for such applications. This study was piloted using imagery acquired from the Slave River Delta, Canada, to fill this knowledge gap. The findings were validated using ice core data extracted near Fort Smith. The results indicate that the revisit interval of the satellite is a governing factor of InSAR coherence loss. The ALOS-1 PALSAR images have the smallest coherence mainly due to the 46-day revisit interval and are the least promising for monitoring spatiotemporal variations of river ice covers. Coherence of both Sentinel-1A with a 12-day revisit interval and Radarsat-2 images with a 24-day revisit interval is an important aid for determining safe ice crossings.</abstract><url hash="43b0d54e">2018.GWF-1.78</url><doi>10.1080/07038992.2018.1419424</doi><bibkey>Li-etal-2018-Coherence</bibkey></paper><paper id="79"><title>Combined Impacts of ENSO and MJO on the 2015 Growing 1 Season Drought on the Canadian Prairies 2</title><author><first>Zhenhua</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>Yanping</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Bonsal</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Manson</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Scaff</last></author><abstract>1Global Institute for Water Security, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, Canada S7N3H5 4 2Institute of Space and Atmospheric Studies, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, Canada 5 3National Hydrology Research Center, Environment and Climate Change Canada, Saskatoon, SK, Canada 6 Correspondence to: Dr. Yanping Li (yanping.li@usask.ca); Dr. Zhenhua Li (zhenhua.li@usask.ca) 7 Abstract 8</abstract><url hash="34b7e5d8">2018.GWF-1.79</url><doi>10.5194/hess-2018-56</doi><bibkey>Li-etal-2018-Combined</bibkey></paper><paper id="80"><title>Monitoring river ice cover development using the Freeman–Durden decomposition of quad-pol Radarsat-2 images</title><author><first>K.</first><last>Lindenschmidt</last></author><author><first>Zhaoqin</first><last>Li</last></author><abstract>Abstract. The monitoring of river ice development is a crucial guidance indicator to establish safe crossings along river ice covers. This is the first study, based on our knowledge, to understand the interactions between river ice cover structures and radar signals and to further monitor ice development using C-band synthetic aperture radar images. The study was applied to the Slave River, Canada, using the Freeman–Durden decomposition of quad-pol C-band Radarsat-2 FQ14W images and ice core crystallography analysis. Results demonstrate that the combination of volume and surface scattering can be used to monitor ice cover development that cannot be interpreted from single polarization images, such as Radarsat-2 spotlight images used in this study. These results indicate that the decomposed quad-pol Radarsat-2 images can provide a more effective guide than the single-pol Radarsat-2 SLA images to select safe ice transportation routes. This decomposition approach can be extended to other snow and ice covered rivers.</abstract><url hash="caf341b3">2018.GWF-1.80</url><doi>10.1117/1.JRS.12.026014</doi><bibkey>Lindenschmidt-etal-2018-Monitoring</bibkey></paper><paper id="81"><title>Contributions of catchment and in-stream processes to suspended sediment transport in a dominantly groundwater-fed catchment</title><author><first>Yan</first><last>Liu</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Zarfl</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Basu</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Schwientek</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Cirpka</last></author><abstract>Abstract. Suspended sediments impact stream water quality by increasing the
turbidity and acting as a vector for strongly sorbing pollutants.
Understanding their sources is of great importance to developing appropriate
river management strategies. In this study, we present an integrated sediment
transport model composed of a catchment-scale hydrological model to predict
river discharge, a river-hydraulics model to obtain shear stresses in the
channel, a sediment-generating model, and a river sediment-transport model.
We use this framework to investigate the sediment contributions from
catchment and in-stream processes in the Ammer catchment close to
Tübingen in southwestern Germany. The model is calibrated to stream flow
and suspended-sediment concentrations. We use the monthly mean
suspended-sediment load to analyze seasonal variations of different
processes. The contributions of catchment and in-stream processes to the
total loads are demonstrated by model simulations under different flow
conditions. The evaluation of shear stresses by the river-hydraulics model
allows the identification of hotspots and hot moments of bed erosion for the main stem
of the Ammer River. The results suggest that the contributions of
suspended-sediment loads from urban areas and in-stream processes are higher
in the summer months, while deposition has small variations with a slight
increase in summer months. The sediment input from agricultural land and
urban areas as well as bed and bank erosion increase with an increase in flow
rates. Bed and bank erosion are negligible when flow is smaller than the
corresponding thresholds of 1.5 and 2.5 times the mean discharge,
respectively. The bed-erosion rate is higher during the summer months and
varies along the main stem. Over the simulated time period, net sediment
trapping is observed in the Ammer River. The present work is the basis to
study particle-facilitated transport of pollutants in the system, helping to
understand the fate and transport of sediments and sediment-bound pollutants.
</abstract><url hash="bdf47125">2018.GWF-1.81</url><doi>10.5194/HESS-22-3903-2018</doi><bibkey>Liu-etal-2018-Contributions</bibkey></paper><paper id="82"><title>Reviews and syntheses: Changing ecosystem influences on soil thermal regimes in northern high-latitude permafrost regions</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Loranty</last></author><author><first>Benjamin</first><last>W. Abbott</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Blok</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Douglas</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Epstein</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Forbes</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Jones</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Kholodov</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Kropp</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Malhotra</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Mamet</last></author><author><first>I.</first><last>Myers-Smith</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Natali</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>O’Donnell</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Phoenix</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Rocha</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Sonnentag</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Tape</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Walker</last></author><abstract>Abstract. Soils in Arctic and boreal ecosystems store twice as much carbon as the atmosphere, a portion of which may be released as high-latitude soils warm. Some of the uncertainty in the timing and magnitude of the permafrost–climate feedback stems from complex interactions between ecosystem properties and soil thermal dynamics. Terrestrial ecosystems fundamentally regulate the response of permafrost to climate change by influencing surface energy partitioning and the thermal properties of soil itself. Here we review how Arctic and boreal ecosystem processes influence thermal dynamics in permafrost soil and how these linkages may evolve in response to climate change. While many of the ecosystem characteristics and processes affecting soil thermal dynamics have been examined individually (e.g., vegetation, soil moisture, and soil structure), interactions among these processes are less understood. Changes in ecosystem type and vegetation characteristics will alter spatial patterns of interactions between climate and permafrost. In addition to shrub expansion, other vegetation responses to changes in climate and rapidly changing disturbance regimes will affect ecosystem surface energy partitioning in ways that are important for permafrost. Lastly, changes in vegetation and ecosystem distribution will lead to regional and global biophysical and biogeochemical climate feedbacks that may compound or offset local impacts on permafrost soils. Consequently, accurate prediction of the permafrost carbon climate feedback will require detailed understanding of changes in terrestrial ecosystem distribution and function, which depend on the net effects of multiple feedback processes operating across scales in space and time.
</abstract><url hash="24fd209f">2018.GWF-1.82</url><doi>10.5194/BG-15-5287-2018</doi><bibkey>Loranty-etal-2018-Reviews</bibkey></paper><paper id="83"><title>Comparison of big-leaf, two-big-leaf and two-leaf upscaling schemes for evapotranspiration estimation using coupled carbon-water modelling: Comparison of big-leaf, two-big-leaf and two-leaf upscaling schemes for evapotranspiration estimation using coupled carbon-water modelling</title><author><first>Xiangzhong</first><last>Luo</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Chen</last></author><author><first>Jane</first><last>Liu</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>A. Black</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Croft</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Staebler</last></author><author><first>Liming</first><last>He</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>A. Arain</last></author><author><first>Bin</first><last>Chen</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Mo</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Gonsamo</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>McCaughey</last></author><abstract /><url hash="53fa1009">2018.GWF-1.83</url><doi>10.1002/2017JG003978</doi><bibkey>Luo-etal-2018-Comparison</bibkey></paper><paper id="84"><title>The role of groundwater discharge fluxes on Si:P ratios in a major tributary to Lake Erie.</title><author><first>T.</first><last>Maavara</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Slowinski</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Rezanezhad</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>V. Van Meter</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Van Cappellen</last></author><abstract /><url hash="cd9e85aa">2018.GWF-1.84</url><doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.12.024</doi><bibkey>Maavara-etal-2018-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="85"><title>Water and energy fluxes over northern prairies as affected by chinook winds and winter precipitation</title><author><first>M.</first><last>MacDonald</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pomeroy</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Essery</last></author><abstract /><url hash="ba99b53c">2018.GWF-1.85</url><doi>10.1016/J.AGRFORMET.2017.10.025</doi><bibkey>MacDonald-etal-2018-Water</bibkey></paper><paper id="86"><title>The spatial and temporal distribution of metals in an urban stream: A case study of the Don River in Toronto, Canada</title><author><first>Sannan</first><last>Zahid Mansoor</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Louie</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>T. Lima</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Van Cappellen</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>MacVicar</last></author><abstract /><url hash="2390e486">2018.GWF-1.86</url><doi>10.1016/J.JGLR.2018.08.010</doi><bibkey>Zahid Mansoor-etal-2018-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="87"><title>Assessing recovery of in vitro steroid production in male rainbow darter (Etheostoma caeruleum) in response to municipal wastewater treatment plant infrastructure changes</title><author><first>P.</first><last>Marjan</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>J. Van Der Kraak</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Maclatchy</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Fuzzen</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Bragg</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Mcmaster</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Tetreault</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Servos</last></author><abstract>The present study examined in vitro 11‐ketotestosterone and testosterone production by the testes of rainbow darter (Etheostoma caeruleum) collected from selected reference sites and downstream of 2 municipal wastewater treatment plants (MWWTPs; Waterloo and Kitchener) on the central Grand River (Ontario, Canada), over a 6‐yr period (2011–2016). The main objective was to investigate if infrastructure upgrades at the Kitchener MWWTP in 2012 resulted in a recovery of this response in the post‐upgrade period (2013–2016). Two supporting studies showed that the fall season is appropriate for measuring in vitro sex steroid production because it provides stable detection of steroid patterns, and that the sample handling practiced in the present study did not introduce a bias. Infrastructure upgrades of the Kitchener MWWTP resulted in significant reductions in ammonia and estrogenicity. After the upgrades, 11‐ketotestosterone production by MWWTP‐exposed fish increased in 2013 and it continued to recover throughout the study period of 2014 through 2016, returning to levels measured in reference fish. Testosterone production was less sensitive and it lacked consistency. The Waterloo MWWTP underwent some minor upgrades but the level of ammonia and estrogenicity remained variable over time. The production of 11‐ketotestosterone and testosterone in rainbow darter below the Waterloo MWWTP was variable and without a clear recovery pattern over the course of the present study. The results of the present study demonstrated that measuring production of sex steroids (especially 11‐ketotestosterone) over multiple years can be relevant for assessing responses in fish to environmental changes such as those resulting from major infrastructure upgrades. Environ Toxicol Chem 2018;37:501–514. © 2017 SETAC</abstract><url hash="5497d410">2018.GWF-1.87</url><doi>10.1002/etc.3986</doi><bibkey>Marjan-etal-2018-Assessing</bibkey></paper><paper id="88"><title>Multi-objective unstructured triangular mesh generation for use in hydrological and land surface models</title><author><first>C.</first><last>Marsh</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Spiteri</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pomeroy</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Wheater</last></author><abstract /><url hash="c428c981">2018.GWF-1.88</url><doi>10.1016/j.cageo.2018.06.009</doi><bibkey>Marsh-etal-2018-Multi-objective</bibkey></paper><paper id="89"><title>Prioritizing recovery funding to maximize conservation of endangered species</title><author><first>T.</first><last>Martin</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Kehoe</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Mantyka‐Pringle</last></author><author><first>I.</first><last>Chades</last></author><author><first>Scott</first><last>Wilson</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Bloom</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>K. Davis</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Fisher</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Keith</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Mehl</last></author><author><first>Beatriz</first><last>Prieto Diaz</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Wayland</last></author><author><first>Troy</first><last>I. Wellicome</last></author><author><first>Karl</first><last>P. Zimmer</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Smith</last></author><abstract>The absence of a rigorous mechanism for prioritizing investment in endangered species management is a major implementation hurdle affecting recovery. Here, we present a method for prioritizing strategies for endangered species management based on the likelihood of achieving species’ recovery goals per dollar invested. We demonstrate our approach for 15 species listed under Canada's Species at Risk Act that co‐occur in Southwestern Saskatchewan. Without management, only two species have &gt;50% probability of meeting recovery objectives; whereas, with management, 13 species exceed the &gt;50% threshold with the implementation of just five complementary strategies at a cost of $126m over 20 years. The likelihood of meeting recovery objectives rarely exceeded 70% and two species failed to reach the &gt;50% threshold. Our findings underscore the need to consider the cost, benefit, and feasibility of management strategies when developing recovery plans in order to prioritize implementation in a timely and cost‐effective manner.</abstract><url hash="b32ff917">2018.GWF-1.89</url><doi>10.1111/conl.12604</doi><bibkey>Martin-etal-2018-Prioritizing</bibkey></paper><paper id="90"><title>Projecting groundwater storage changes in California’s Central Valley</title><author><first>E.</first><last>Massoud</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>J. Purdy</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Miro</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Famiglietti</last></author><abstract /><url hash="d3e870f2">2018.GWF-1.90</url><doi>10.1038/s41598-018-31210-1</doi><bibkey>Massoud-etal-2018-Projecting</bibkey></paper><paper id="91"><title>Dielectric characterization of vegetation at L band using an open-ended coaxial probe</title><author><first>A.</first><last>Mavrovic</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Royer</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Filali</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Boone</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Pappas</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Sonnentag</last></author><abstract>Abstract. Decoupling the integrated microwave signal originating from soil
and vegetation remains a challenge for all microwave remote sensing
applications. To improve satellite and airborne microwave data products in
forest environments, a precise and reliable estimation of the relative
permittivity (ε=ε′-iε′′) of trees is required. We
developed an open-ended coaxial probe suitable for in situ
permittivity measurements of tree trunks at L-band frequencies (1–2 GHz).
The probe is characterized by uncertainty ratios under 3.3 % for a broad
range of relative permittivities (unitless), [2–40] for
ε′ and [0.1–20] for ε′′. We quantified
the complex number describing the permittivity of seven different tree
species in both frozen and thawed states: black spruce, larch, red spruce,
balsam fir, red pine, aspen and black cherry. Permittivity variability is
substantial and can range up to 300 % for certain species. Our results
show that the permittivity of wood is linked to the freeze–thaw state of
vegetation and that even short winter thaw events can lead to an increase in
vegetation permittivity. The open-ended coaxial probe proved to be precise
enough to capture the diurnal cycle of water storage inside the trunk for the
length of the growing season.
</abstract><url hash="a4ef4064">2018.GWF-1.91</url><doi>10.5194/GI-7-195-2018</doi><bibkey>Mavrovic-etal-2018-Dielectric</bibkey></paper><paper id="92"><title>Delineating boreal plains bog margin ecotones across hydrogeological settings for wildfire risk management</title><author><first>Kristyn</first><last>M. Mayner</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Moore</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Wilkinson</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Petrone</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Waddington</last></author><abstract /><url hash="3de611de">2018.GWF-1.92</url><doi>10.1007/s11273-018-9636-5</doi><bibkey>M. Mayner-etal-2018-Delineating</bibkey></paper><paper id="93"><title>Influence of seasonal temperature on tree-ring δ13C in different-aged temperate pine forests</title><author><first>S.</first><last>McKenzie</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Slater</last></author><author><first>Sang-Tae</first><last>Kim</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Pisaric</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>A. Arain</last></author><abstract /><url hash="4ae12148">2018.GWF-1.93</url><doi>10.1016/J.FORECO.2018.03.042</doi><bibkey>McKenzie-etal-2018-Influence</bibkey></paper><paper id="94"><title>Downscaling GRACE Remote Sensing Datasets to High-Resolution Groundwater Storage Change Maps of California's Central Valley</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Miro</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Famiglietti</last></author><abstract>NASA’s Gravity Recovery and Climate Experiment (GRACE) has already proven to be a powerful data source for regional groundwater assessments in many areas around the world. However, the applicability of GRACE data products to more localized studies and their utility to water management authorities have been constrained by their limited spatial resolution (~200,000 km2). Researchers have begun to address these shortcomings with data assimilation approaches that integrate GRACE-derived total water storage estimates into complex regional models, producing higher-resolution estimates of hydrologic variables (~2500 km2). Here we take those approaches one step further by developing an empirically based model capable of downscaling GRACE data to a high-resolution (~16 km2) dataset of groundwater storage changes over a portion of California’s Central Valley. The model utilizes an artificial neural network to generate a series of high-resolution maps of groundwater storage change from 2002 to 2010 using GRACE estimates of variations in total water storage and a series of widely available hydrologic variables (PRISM precipitation and temperature data, digital elevation model (DEM)-derived slope, and Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS) soil type). The neural network downscaling model is able to accurately reproduce local groundwater behavior, with acceptable Nash-Sutcliffe efficiency (NSE) values for calibration and validation (ranging from 0.2445 to 0.9577 and 0.0391 to 0.7511, respectively). Ultimately, the model generates maps of local groundwater storage change at a 100-fold higher resolution than GRACE gridded data products without the use of computationally intensive physical models. The model’s simulated maps have the potential for application to local groundwater management initiatives in the region.</abstract><url hash="d485b4eb">2018.GWF-1.94</url><doi>10.3390/rs10010143</doi><bibkey>Miro-etal-2018-Downscaling</bibkey></paper><paper id="95"><title>A framework for quantifying sustainable yield under California’s Sustainable Groundwater Management Act (SGMA)</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Miro</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Famiglietti</last></author><abstract /><url hash="a382847d">2018.GWF-1.95</url><doi>10.1007/s40899-018-0283-z</doi><bibkey>Miro-etal-2018-A</bibkey></paper><paper id="96"><title>Snowmelt Infiltration and Macropore Flow in Frozen Soils: Overview, Knowledge Gaps, and a Conceptual Framework</title><author><first>A.</first><last>Mohammed</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Kurylyk</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Cey</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Hayashi</last></author><abstract>Review highlights the hydrological importance of macropore flow in frozen soils. Governing flow mechanisms and infiltration and refreezing dynamics are discussed. Research is needed to integrate macropore flow and soil freeze–thaw theory. Dual‐domain models of macropore flow should be adapted to frozen ground. A conceptual framework for modeling frozen macroporous soils is proposed.</abstract><url hash="3a8bd5c7">2018.GWF-1.96</url><doi>10.2136/vzj2018.04.0084</doi><bibkey>Mohammed-etal-2018-Snowmelt</bibkey></paper><paper id="97"><title>Improving revisitation in long documents with two-level artificial-landmark scrollbars</title><author><first>Ehsan</first><last>Sotoodeh Mollashahi</last></author><author><first>Md.</first><last>Sami Uddin</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Gutwin</last></author><abstract>Document readers with linear navigation controls do not work well when users need to navigate to previously-visited locations, particularly when documents are long. Existing solutions - bookmarks, search, history, and read wear - are valuable but limited in terms of effort, clutter, and interpretability. In this paper, we investigate artificial landmarks as a way to improve support for revisitation in long documents - inspired by visual augmentations seen in physical books such as coloring on page edges or indents cut into pages. We developed several artificial-landmark visualizations that can represent locations even in documents that are many hundreds of pages long, and tested them in studies where participants visited multiple locations in long documents. Results show that providing two columns of landmark icons led to significantly better performance and user preference. Artificial landmarks provide a new mechanism to build spatial memory of long documents - and can be used either alone or with existing techniques like bookmarks, read wear, and search.</abstract><url hash="4d8ce551">2018.GWF-1.97</url><doi>10.1145/3206505.3206554</doi><bibkey>Sotoodeh Mollashahi-etal-2018-Improving</bibkey></paper><paper id="98"><title>Potential Changes of Annual-Averaged Nutrient Export in the South Saskatchewan River Basin under Climate and Land-Use Change Scenarios</title><author><first>L.</first><last>Morales-Marín</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Wheater</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Lindenschmidt</last></author><abstract>Climate and land-use changes modify the physical functioning of river basins and, in particular, influence the transport of nutrients from land to water. In large-scale basins, where a variety of climates, topographies, soil types and land uses co-exist to form a highly heterogeneous environment, a more complex nutrient dynamic is imposed by climate and land-use changes. This is the case of the South Saskatchewan River (SSR) that, along with the North Saskatchewan River, forms one of the largest river systems in western Canada. The SPAtially Referenced Regression On Watershed (SPARROW) model is therefore implemented to assess water quality in the basin, in order to describe spatial and temporal patterns and identify those factors and processes that affect water quality. Forty-five climate and land-use change scenarios comprehended by five General Circulation Models (GCMs) and three Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs) were incorporated into the model to explain how total nitrogen (TN) and total phosphorus (TP) export could vary across the basin in 30, 60 and 90 years from now. According to model results, annual averages of TN and TP export in the SSR are going to increase in the range 0.9–1.28 kg km − 2 year − 1 and 0.12–0.17 kg km − 2 year − 1 , respectively, by the end of the century, due to climate and land-use changes. Higher increases of TP compared to TN are expected since TP and TN are going to increase ∼36% and ∼21%, respectively, by the end of the century. This research will support management plans in order to mitigate nutrient export under future changes of climate and land use.</abstract><url hash="dd33f8c0">2018.GWF-1.98</url><doi>10.3390/W10101438</doi><bibkey>Morales-Marín-etal-2018-Potential</bibkey></paper><paper id="99"><title>Flood risk management in the Canadian prairie provinces: Defaulting towards flood resistance and recovery versus resilience</title><author><first>Alasdair</first><last>Morrison</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Noble</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Westbrook</last></author><abstract>Major flood events are likely to happen more frequently and be more severe under changing land use and climatic conditions. Adapting to floods using resilience-based flood risk management (FRM) policies and initiatives is a more appropriate solution than relying solely on flood defence structures or disaster recovery programmes. The primary authority for FRM in Canada is the provinces, but in practice, the policies and responsibilities are distributed across complex, multi-departmental, multi-scalar systems of government. To examine the extent to which institutional arrangements for FRM facilitate or constrain FRM resilience, this paper uses a case study of FRM policies, instruments and practices in the three Canadian prairie provinces where floods have been particularly severe in recent years. Document analysis provided insights into current FRM policies and instruments while semi-structured interviews with 34 individuals working in an FRM capacity informed the roles and responsibilities for FRM implementation. Results indicate that the current FRM policies and instruments across the prairie region have the basic requirements for flood resilience. However, flood resilience is inherently challenged by institutional fragmentation, lack of clarity of FRM roles and responsibilities, and policy layering and competing mandates, which biases FRM towards resistance and recovery solutions. To go beyond solely coordinating flood emergency response and recovery, the paper suggests an overarching regional or national FRM strategy and boundary organisation to coordinate roles and responsibilities for the specific purpose of flood resilience. This requires an agency with the mandate to manage FRM policy instruments, and clearly allocate decision authority amongst the multiple levels and layers of FRM governance.</abstract><url hash="aa34c856">2018.GWF-1.99</url><doi>10.1080/07011784.2018.1428501</doi><bibkey>Morrison-etal-2018-Flood</bibkey></paper><paper id="100"><title>Fine-Grained Attribute Level Locking Scheme for Collaborative Scientific Workflow Development</title><author><first>Golam</first><last>Mostaeen</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>Kevin</first><last>A. Schneider</last></author><abstract>Scientific Workflow Management Systems are being widely used in recent years for data-intensive analysis tasks or domain-specific discoveries. It often becomes challenging for an individual to effectively analyze the large scale scientific data of relatively higher complexity and dimensions, and requires a collaboration of multiple members of different disciplines. Hence, researchers have focused on designing collaborative workflow management systems. However, consistency management in the face of conflicting concurrent operations of the collaborators is a major challenge in such systems. In this paper, we propose a locking scheme (e.g., collaborator gets write access to non-conflicting components of the workflow at a given time) to facilitate consistency management in collaborative scientific workflow management systems. The proposed method allows locking workflow components at a granular level in addition to supporting locks on a targeted part of the collaborative workflow. We conducted several experiments to analyze the performance of the proposed method in comparison to related existing methods. Our studies show that the proposed method can reduce the average waiting time of a collaborator by up to 36.19% in comparison to existing descendent modular level locking techniques for collaborative scientific workflow management systems.</abstract><url hash="a9a8f5d9">2018.GWF-1.100</url><doi>10.1109/SCC.2018.00047</doi><bibkey>Mostaeen-etal-2018-Fine-Grained</bibkey></paper><paper id="101"><title>[Research Paper] On the Use of Machine Learning Techniques Towards the Design of Cloud Based Automatic Code Clone Validation Tools</title><author><first>Golam</first><last>Mostaeen</last></author><author><first>Jeffrey</first><last>Svajlenko</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>Kevin</first><last>A. Schneider</last></author><abstract>A code clone is a pair of code fragments, within or between software systems that are similar. Since code clones often negatively impact the maintainability of a software system, a great many numbers of code clone detection techniques and tools have been proposed and studied over the last decade. To detect all possible similar source code patterns in general, the clone detection tools work on syntax level (such as texts, tokens, AST and so on) while lacking user-specific preferences. This often means the reported clones must be manually validated prior to any analysis in order to filter out the true positive clones from task or user-specific considerations. This manual clone validation effort is very time-consuming and often error-prone, in particular for large-scale clone detection. In this paper, we propose a machine learning based approach for automating the validation process. In an experiment with clones detected by several clone detectors in several different software systems, we found our approach has an accuracy of up to 87.4% when compared against the manual validation by multiple expert judges. The proposed method shows promising results in several comparative studies with the existing related approaches for automatic code clone validation. We also present our experimental results in terms of different code clone detection tools, machine learning algorithms and open source software systems.</abstract><url hash="deafc54f">2018.GWF-1.101</url><doi>10.1109/SCAM.2018.00025</doi><bibkey>Mostaeen-etal-2018-[Research</bibkey></paper><paper id="102"><title>[Research Paper] CroLSim: Cross Language Software Similarity Detector Using API Documentation</title><author><first>Kawser</first><last>Wazed Nafi</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>Kevin</first><last>A. Schneider</last></author><abstract>In today's open source era, developers look forsimilar software applications in source code repositories for anumber of reasons, including, exploring alternative implementations, reusing source code, or looking for a better application. However, while there are a great many studies for finding similarapplications written in the same programming language, there isa marked lack of studies for finding similar software applicationswritten in different languages. In this paper, we fill the gapby proposing a novel modelCroLSimwhich is able to detectsimilar software applications across different programming lan-guages. In our approach, we use the API documentation tofind relationships among the API calls used by the differentprogramming languages. We adopt a deep learning based word-vector learning method to identify semantic relationships amongthe API documentation which we then use to detect cross-language similar software applications. For evaluating CroLSim, we formed a repository consisting of 8,956 Java, 7,658 C#, and 10,232 Python applications collected from GitHub. Weobserved thatCroLSimcan successfully detect similar softwareapplications across different programming languages with a meanaverage precision rate of 0.65, an average confidence rate of3.6 (out of 5) with 75% high rated successful queries, whichoutperforms all related existing approaches with a significantperformance improvement.</abstract><url hash="47a694f5">2018.GWF-1.102</url><doi>10.1109/SCAM.2018.00023</doi><bibkey>Wazed Nafi-etal-2018-[Research</bibkey></paper><paper id="103"><title>Revising Return Periods for Record Events in a Climate Event Attribution Context</title><author><first>P.</first><last>Naveau</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Ribes</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Zwiers</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Hannart</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Tuel</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Yiou</last></author><abstract>AbstractBoth climate and statistical models play an essential role in the process of demonstrating that the distribution of some atmospheric variable has changed over time and in establishing the most likely causes for the detected change. One statistical difficulty in the research field of Detection and Attribution resides in defining events that can be easily compared and accurately inferred from reasonable sample sizes. As many impacts studies focus on extreme events, the inference of small probabilities and the computation of their associated uncertainties quickly become challenging. In the particular context of event attribution, we address the question of how to compare records between the so-called world as “it might have been been without anthropogenic forcings” and the “world that is”. Records are often the most important events in terms of impact and get much media attention. We will show how to efficiently estimate the ratio of two small probability of records. The inferential gain is particula...</abstract><url hash="30a1a463">2018.GWF-1.103</url><doi>10.1175/JCLI-D-16-0752.1</doi><bibkey>Naveau-etal-2018-Revising</bibkey></paper><paper id="104"><title>A Coupled Soil Water Balance Model for Simulating Depression‐Focused Groundwater Recharge</title><author><first>S.</first><last>Noorduijn</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Hayashi</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Mohammed</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Mohammed</last></author><abstract>Ephemeral ponds in depressions are the foci of groundwater recharge in the Canadian Prairies. Freeze–thaw processes influence snowmelt runoff and depression‐focused recharge. A new water balance model was developed to represent these processes. The water balance model successfully simulated the observed soil processes. This model will provide a tool to estimate recharge in the prairie landscape.</abstract><url hash="aec531c0">2018.GWF-1.104</url><doi>10.2136/vzj2017.10.0176</doi><bibkey>Noorduijn-etal-2018-A</bibkey></paper><paper id="105"><title>Boreal tree hydrodynamics: asynchronous, diverging, yet complementary</title><author><first>C.</first><last>Pappas</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Matheny</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Baltzer</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Barr</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>A. Black</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Bohrer</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Detto</last></author><author><first>Jason</first><last>Maillet</last></author><author><first>Alexandre</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Sonnentag</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Stephens</last></author><abstract>Water stress has been identified as a key mechanism of the contemporary increase in tree mortality rates in northwestern North America. However, a detailed analysis of boreal tree hydrodynamics and their interspecific differences is still lacking. Here we examine the hydraulic behaviour of co-occurring larch (Larix laricina) and black spruce (Picea mariana), two characteristic boreal tree species, near the southern limit of the boreal ecozone in central Canada. Sap flux density (Js), concurrently recorded stem radius fluctuations and meteorological conditions are used to quantify tree hydraulic functioning and to scrutinize tree water-use strategies. Our analysis revealed asynchrony in the diel hydrodynamics of the two species with the initial rise in Js occurring 2 h earlier in larch than in black spruce. Interspecific differences in larch and black spruce crown architecture explained the observed asynchrony in their hydraulic functioning. Furthermore, the two species exhibited diverging stomatal regulation strategies with larch and black spruce employing relatively isohydric and anisohydric behaviour, respectively. Such asynchronous and diverging tree-level hydrodynamics provide new insights into the ecosystem-level complementarity in tree form and function, with implications for understanding boreal forests' water and carbon dynamics and their resilience to environmental stress.</abstract><url hash="d9c20156">2018.GWF-1.105</url><doi>10.1093/treephys/tpy043</doi><bibkey>Pappas-etal-2018-Boreal</bibkey></paper><paper id="106"><title>Scénarios de probabilité et puissance potentielle des feux de végétation dans le département des Landes, France</title><author><first>Marc</first><last>Parisien</last></author><author><first>François</first><last>Robinne</last></author><author><first>Jean-Yves</first><last>Perez</last></author><author><first>Bruno</first><last>Denave</last></author><author><first>Evan</first><last>R. DeLancey</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Doche</last></author><abstract>Le sud-ouest de la France n’a pas connu d’incendie majeur depuis plusieurs decennies, mais il presente un fort potentiel de feu de grande ampleur. Cette menace concerne la securite de la population...</abstract><url hash="40cb50ec">2018.GWF-1.106</url><doi>10.1139/CJFR-2018-0223</doi><bibkey>Parisien-etal-2018-Scénarios</bibkey></paper><paper id="107"><title>Wetlands, flood control and ecosystem services in the Smith Creek drainage basin: a case study in Saskatchewan, Canada.</title><author><first>John</first><last>K. Pattison-Williams</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pomeroy</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Badiou</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Gabor</last></author><abstract /><url hash="37cc607a">2018.GWF-1.107</url><doi>10.1016/J.ECOLECON.2017.12.026</doi><bibkey>K. Pattison-Williams-etal-2018-Wetlands,</bibkey></paper><paper id="108"><title>Effects of midwinter snowmelt on runoff generation and
groundwater recharge in the Canadian prairies</title><author><first>I.</first><last>Pavlovskii</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Hayashi</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Itenfisu</last></author><abstract>Abstract. Snowpack accumulation and depletion are important elements of the hydrological cycle in the prairies. The surface runoff generated during snowmelt is transformed into streamflow or fills numerous depressions driving the focused recharge of groundwater in this dry setting. The snowpack in the prairies can undergo several cycles of accumulation and depletion in a winter. The timing of the melt affects the mechanisms of snowpack depletion and their hydrological implications. The effects of midwinter melt were investigated at three sites in the Canadian prairies. Unlike net radiation-driven snowmelt during spring melt, turbulent sensible heat fluxes were the dominant source of energy inputs for midwinter melt occurring in the period with low solar radiation inputs. Midwinter melt events had lower runoff ratios than subsequent spring melt events and had strong impacts on the timing of the focussed recharge. Remote sensing data have shown that midwinter melt events regularly occur under the present climate throughout the Canadian prairies.
</abstract><url hash="a7737deb">2018.GWF-1.108</url><doi>10.5194/HESS-2018-423</doi><bibkey>Pavlovskii-etal-2018-Effects</bibkey></paper><paper id="109"><title>Quantification of uncertainties in conifer sap flow measured with the thermal dissipation method.</title><author><first>R.</first><last>L. Peters</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Fonti</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Frank</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Poyatos</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Pappas</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Kahmen</last></author><author><first>V.</first><last>Carraro</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Prendin</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Schneider</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Baltzer</last></author><author><first>Greg</first><last>A Baron-Gafford</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Dietrich</last></author><author><first>I.</first><last>Heinrich</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Minor</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Sonnentag</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Matheny</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Wightman</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Steppe</last></author><abstract>Trees play a key role in the global hydrological cycle and measurements performed with the thermal dissipation method (TDM) have been crucial in providing whole-tree water-use estimates. Yet, different data processing to calculate whole-tree water use encapsulates uncertainties that have not been systematically assessed. We quantified uncertainties in conifer sap flux density (Fd ) and stand water use caused by commonly applied methods for deriving zero-flow conditions, dampening and sensor calibration. Their contribution has been assessed using a stem segment calibration experiment and 4 yr of TDM measurements in Picea abies and Larix decidua growing in contrasting environments. Uncertainties were then projected on TDM data from different conifers across the northern hemisphere. Commonly applied methods mostly underestimated absolute Fd . Lacking a site- and species-specific calibrations reduced our stand water-use measurements by 37% and induced uncertainty in northern hemisphere Fd . Additionally, although the interdaily variability was maintained, disregarding dampening and/or applying zero-flow conditions that ignored night-time water use reduced the correlation between environment and Fd . The presented ensemble of calibration curves and proposed dampening correction, together with the systematic quantification of data-processing uncertainties, provide crucial steps in improving whole-tree water-use estimates across spatial and temporal scales.</abstract><url hash="d0744d7d">2018.GWF-1.109</url><doi>10.1111/nph.15241</doi><bibkey>L. Peters-etal-2018-Quantification</bibkey></paper><paper id="110"><title>Pointing All Around You: Selection Performance of Mouse and Ray-Cast Pointing in Full-Coverage Displays</title><author><first>Julian</first><last>Petford</last></author><author><first>Miguel</first><last>A. Nacenta</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Gutwin</last></author><abstract>As display environments become larger and more diverse - now often encompassing multiple walls and room surfaces - it is becoming more common that users must find and manipulate digital artifacts not directly in front of them. There is little understanding, however, about what techniques and devices are best for carrying out basic operations above, behind, or to the side of the user. We conducted an empirical study comparing two main techniques that are suitable for full-coverage display environments: mouse-based pointing, and ray-cast 'laser' pointing. Participants completed search and pointing tasks on the walls and ceiling, and we measured completion time, path lengths and perceived effort. Our study showed a strong interaction between performance and target location: when the target position was not known a priori the mouse was fastest for targets on the front wall, but ray-casting was faster for targets behind the user. Our findings provide new empirical evidence that can help designers choose pointing techniques for full-coverage spaces.</abstract><url hash="b0b3c498">2018.GWF-1.110</url><doi>10.1145/3173574.3174107</doi><bibkey>Petford-etal-2018-Pointing</bibkey></paper><paper id="111"><title>Data synergy between leaf area index and clumping index Earth Observation products using photon recollision probability theory</title><author><first>J.</first><last>Pisek</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Buddenbaum</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Camacho</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Hill</last></author><author><first>Jennifer</first><last>L. R. Jensen</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Lange</last></author><author><first>Zhili</first><last>Liu</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Piayda</last></author><author><first>Y.</first><last>Qu</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Roupsard</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Serbin</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Solberg</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Sonnentag</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Thimonier</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Vuolo</last></author><abstract /><url hash="c7b4f40e">2018.GWF-1.111</url><doi>10.1016/J.RSE.2018.05.026</doi><bibkey>Pisek-etal-2018-Data</bibkey></paper><paper id="112"><title>Supply and Transport Limitations on Phosphorus Losses from Agricultural Fields in the Lower Great Lakes Region, Canada.</title><author><first>J.</first><last>Plach</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Macrae</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Ali</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Brunke</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>English</last></author><author><first>Gabrielle</first><last>M. Ferguson</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>V. Lam</last></author><author><first>Tatianna</first><last>M. Lozier</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>McKague</last></author><author><first>I.</first><last>O’halloran</last></author><author><first>Gilian</first><last>Opolko</last></author><author><first>C.J.</first><last>Van Esbroeck</last></author><abstract>Phosphorus (P) mobilization in agricultural landscapes is regulated by both hydrologic (transport) and biogeochemical (supply) processes interacting within soils; however, the dominance of these controls can vary spatially and temporally. In this study, we analyzed a 5-yr dataset of stormflow events across nine agricultural fields in the lower Great Lakes region of Ontario, Canada, to determine if edge-of-field surface runoff and tile drainage losses (total and dissolved reactive P) were limited by transport mechanisms or P supply. Field sites ranged from clay loam, silt loam, to sandy loam textures. Findings indicate that biogeochemical processes (P supply) were more important for tile drain P loading patterns (i.e., variable flow-weighted mean concentrations ([]) across a range of flow regimes) relative to surface runoff, which trended toward a more chemostatic or transport-limited response. At two sites with the same soil texture, higher tile [] and greater transport limitations were apparent at the site with higher soil available P (STP); however, STP did not significantly correlate with tile [] or P loading patterns across the nine sites. This may reflect that the fields were all within a narrow STP range and were not elevated in STP concentrations (Olsen-P, ≤25 mg kg). For the study sites where STP was maintained at reasonable concentrations, hydrology was less of a driving factor for tile P loadings, and thus management strategies that limit P supply may be an effective way to reduce P losses from fields (e.g., timing of fertilizer application).</abstract><url hash="5ebda5b4">2018.GWF-1.112</url><doi>10.2134/jeq2017.06.0234</doi><bibkey>Plach-etal-2018-Supply</bibkey></paper><paper id="113"><title>Dominant glacial landforms of the lower Great Lakes region exhibit different soil phosphorus chemistry and potential risk for phosphorus loss</title><author><first>J.</first><last>Plach</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Macrae</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Williams</last></author><author><first>Brad</first><last>D. Lee</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>King</last></author><abstract /><url hash="29ba9522">2018.GWF-1.113</url><doi>10.1016/J.JGLR.2018.07.005</doi><bibkey>Plach-etal-2018-Dominant</bibkey></paper><paper id="114"><title>Phosphorus and nitrogen trajectories in the Mediterranean Sea (1950–2030): Diagnosing basin-wide anthropogenic nutrient enrichment</title><author><first>H.</first><last>Powley</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Krom</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Cappellen</last></author><abstract /><url hash="b7de0081">2018.GWF-1.114</url><doi>10.1016/J.POCEAN.2018.03.003</doi><bibkey>Powley-etal-2018-Phosphorus</bibkey></paper><paper id="115"><title>SMAP soil moisture improves global evapotranspiration</title><author><first>A.</first><last>J. Purdy</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Fisher</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Goulden</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Colliander</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Halverson</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Tu</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Famiglietti</last></author><abstract /><url hash="c0d93017">2018.GWF-1.115</url><doi>10.1016/J.RSE.2018.09.023</doi><bibkey>J. Purdy-etal-2018-SMAP</bibkey></paper><paper id="116"><title>Integrated water quality monitoring system with pH, free chlorine, and temperature sensors</title><author><first>Yiheng</first><last>Qin</last></author><author><first>Arif</first><last>Ul Alam</last></author><author><first>Si</first><last>Pan</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Howlader</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Ghosh</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Hu</last></author><author><first>Hao</first><last>Jin</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Dong</last></author><author><first>Chih-Hung</first><last>Chen</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Deen</last></author><abstract /><url hash="59d061ad">2018.GWF-1.116</url><doi>10.1016/J.SNB.2017.07.188</doi><bibkey>Qin-etal-2018-Integrated</bibkey></paper><paper id="117"><title>Design of a human biomonitoring community-based project in the Northwest Territories Mackenzie Valley, Canada, to investigate the links between nutrition, contaminants and country foods</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Ratelle</last></author><author><first>Matthew</first><last>J. Laird</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Majowicz</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Skinner</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Swanson</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Laird</last></author><abstract>ABSTRACT Community-based projects place emphasis on a collaborative approach and facilitate research among Indigenous populations regarding local issues and challenges, such as traditional foods consumption, climate change and health safety. Country foods (locally harvested fish, game birds, land animals and plants), which contribute to improved food security, can also be a primary route of contaminant exposure among populations in remote regions. A community-based project was launched in the Dehcho and Sahtù regions of the Northwest Territories (Canada) to: 1) assess contaminants exposure and nutrition status; 2) investigate the role of country food on nutrient and contaminant levels and 3) understand the determinants of message perception on this issue. Consultation with community members, leadership, local partners and researchers was essential to refine the design of the project and implement it in a culturally relevant way. This article details the design of a community-based biomonitoring study that investigates country food use, contaminant exposure and nutritional status in Canadian subarctic First Nations in the Dehcho and Sahtù regions. Results will support environmental health policies in the future for these communities. The project was designed to explore the risks and benefits of country foods and to inform the development of public health strategies.</abstract><url hash="2ed7513b">2018.GWF-1.117</url><doi>10.1080/22423982.2018.1510714</doi><bibkey>Ratelle-etal-2018-Design</bibkey></paper><paper id="118"><title>Cadmium exposure in First Nations communities of the Northwest Territories, Canada: smoking is a greater contributor than consumption of cadmium-accumulating organ meats.</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Ratelle</last></author><author><first>Xinci</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Laird</last></author><abstract>Traditional food consumption among northern populations is associated with improved nutrition but occasionally can also increase contaminant exposure. High levels of cadmium in the organs of moose from certain regions of the Northwest Territories, Canada, led to the release of consumption notices. These notices recommended that individuals limit their consumption of kidney and liver from moose harvested from the Southern Mackenzie Mountain. A human biomonitoring project was designed to better characterize exposure and risks from contaminants, including cadmium, among Dene/Métis communities of the Northwest Territories Mackenzie Valley, Canada. The project included a dietary assessment (food frequency questionnaire) to estimate moose and caribou organ (kidney and liver) consumption, as well as urine and blood sampling for the measurement of cadmium concentration using mass spectrometry. For a subset of the samples, urine cotinine was also quantified. The results from this biomonitoring research show that cadmium levels in urine (GM = 0.32 μg L-1) and blood (GM = 0.58 μg L-1) are similar to those observed in other populations in Canada. For the 38% of participants reporting eating game organs, current traditional food consumption patterns were not associated with cadmium biomarker levels. Instead, smoking appeared to be the main determinant of cadmium exposure. These results are supporting ongoing efforts at the community and territorial level to identify health priorities and design follow up plans in response to environmental monitoring data.</abstract><url hash="be684caa">2018.GWF-1.118</url><doi>10.1039/c8em00232k</doi><bibkey>Ratelle-etal-2018-Cadmium</bibkey></paper><paper id="119"><title>Implementation of human biomonitoring in the Dehcho region of the Northwest Territories, Canada (2016–2017)</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Ratelle</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Skinner</last></author><author><first>Matthew</first><last>J. Laird</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Majowicz</last></author><author><first>Danielle</first><last>Brandow</last></author><author><first>Sara</first><last>Packull-McCormick</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Bouchard</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Dieme</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Stark</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>J. A. Henao</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Hanning</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Laird</last></author><abstract /><url hash="c96f7c3c">2018.GWF-1.119</url><doi>10.1186/s13690-018-0318-9</doi><bibkey>Ratelle-etal-2018-Implementation</bibkey></paper><paper id="120"><title>Prewhitening of hydroclimatic time series? Implications for inferred change and variability across time scales</title><author><first>S.</first><last>Razavi</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Vogel</last></author><abstract /><url hash="9b9e975b">2018.GWF-1.120</url><doi>10.1016/J.JHYDROL.2017.11.053</doi><bibkey>Razavi-etal-2018-Prewhitening</bibkey></paper><paper id="121"><title>Inconsequential effects of flooding in 2014 on lakes in the Peace‐Athabasca Delta (Canada) due to long‐term drying</title><author><first>C.</first><last>Remmer</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Klemt</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Wolfe</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Hall</last></author><abstract>Climate‐driven decline in freshwater supplied by rivers draining the hydrographic apex of western North America has ramifications for downstream ecosystems and society. For the Peace‐Athabasca Delta (PAD), floods from the Peace and Athabasca rivers are critical for sustaining abundant shallow water habitat, but their frequency has been in decline for decades over much of its area. Here, we assess current hydrological and limnological status in the PAD by integrating spatial and temporal data. Analysis of water isotope compositions and water chemistry measured at numerous lakes across the delta shows that hydro‐limnological effects of the large‐scale ice‐jam flood event of 2014 failed to persist beyond the early ice‐free season of 2015. Isotope‐inferred paleohydrological records from five hydrologically representative lakes in the PAD indicate that periodic desiccation during the Little Ice Age occurred at the most elevated basin in response to locally arid climatic conditions, yet other lower elevation sites were influenced by high water level on Lake Athabasca owing to increased snowmelt‐ and glacier‐derived river discharge. In contrast, water isotope data during the past 15 yr at all five lakes consistently document the strong role of evaporation, a trend which began in the early to mid‐20th century according to sediment records and is indicative of widespread aridity unprecedented during the past 400 yr. We suggest that integration of hydrological and limnological approaches over space and time is needed to inform assessment of contemporary lake conditions in large, complex floodplain landscapes.</abstract><url hash="ec99a7cd">2018.GWF-1.121</url><doi>10.1002/lno.10787</doi><bibkey>Remmer-etal-2018-Inconsequential</bibkey></paper><paper id="122"><title>A spatial evaluation of global wildfire-water risks to human and natural systems.</title><author><first>F.</first><last>Robinne</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Bladon</last></author><author><first>Carol</first><last>Miller</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Parisien</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Mathieu</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Flannigan</last></author><abstract /><url hash="7590f677">2018.GWF-1.122</url><doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.08.112</doi><bibkey>Robinne-etal-2018-A</bibkey></paper><paper id="123"><title>Emerging trends in global freshwater availability</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Rodell</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Famiglietti</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Wiese</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Reager</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Beaudoing</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Landerer</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Lo</last></author><abstract /><url hash="0297c6e1">2018.GWF-1.123</url><doi>10.1038/s41586-018-0123-1</doi><bibkey>Rodell-etal-2018-Emerging</bibkey></paper><paper id="124"><title>Ice-jam flood research: a scoping review</title><author><first>P.</first><last>Rokaya</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Budhathoki</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Lindenschmidt</last></author><abstract /><url hash="9cf35342">2018.GWF-1.124</url><doi>10.1007/s11069-018-3455-0</doi><bibkey>Rokaya-etal-2018-Ice-jam</bibkey></paper><paper id="125"><title>Trends in the Timing and Magnitude of Ice-Jam Floods in Canada</title><author><first>P.</first><last>Rokaya</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Budhathoki</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Lindenschmidt</last></author><abstract /><url hash="ebf463d4">2018.GWF-1.125</url><doi>10.1038/s41598-018-24057-z</doi><bibkey>Rokaya-etal-2018-Trends</bibkey></paper><paper id="126"><title>Capturing agricultural soil freeze/thaw state through remote sensing and ground observations: A soil freeze/thaw validation campaign</title><author><first>T.</first><last>Rowlandson</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Berg</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>Edward</first><last>J. Kim</last></author><author><first>Renato</first><last>Pardo Lara</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Powers</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Lewis</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Houser</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>McDonald</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Toose</last></author><author><first>Albert</first><last>Wu</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>D. Marco</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Derksen</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Entin</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Colliander</last></author><author><first>Xiaolan</first><last>Xu</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Mavrovic</last></author><abstract /><url hash="72fd326e">2018.GWF-1.126</url><doi>10.1016/J.RSE.2018.04.003</doi><bibkey>Rowlandson-etal-2018-Capturing</bibkey></paper><paper id="127"><title>Improving in-lake water quality modeling using variable chlorophyll a/algal biomass ratios</title><author><first>A.</first><last>Sadeghian</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Chapra</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Hudson</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Wheater</last></author><author><first>K.</first><last>Lindenschmidt</last></author><abstract /><url hash="05fa02f8">2018.GWF-1.127</url><doi>10.1016/j.envsoft.2017.12.009</doi><bibkey>Sadeghian-etal-2018-Improving</bibkey></paper><paper id="128"><title>Avoiding the Guise of an Anonymous Review</title><author><first>R.</first><last>Sheikholeslami</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Razavi</last></author><abstract /><url hash="95451f69">2018.GWF-1.128</url><doi>10.1029/2018EO098217</doi><bibkey>Sheikholeslami-etal-2018-Avoiding</bibkey></paper><paper id="129"><title>Assessing local adaptation vs. plasticity under different resource conditions in seedlings of a dominant boreal tree species</title><author><first>A.</first><last>Sniderhan</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>McNickle</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Baltzer</last></author><abstract>In this study, we used a common garden to determine if there is differentiation among black spruce seedlings from populations across 15° of latitude in western Canada. Additionally, we tested whether seedlings exhibit trait plasticity in response to increased resource availability. Our results clearly indicated that southern populations grow larger, faster and longer than their northern counterparts. However, there were no differences in allocation patterns or physiological traits among populations and little evidence of plasticity. This study on population-level differentiation and trait plasticity in black spruce contributes to better understanding the resilience of this species under a changing climate.</abstract><url hash="e2422fff">2018.GWF-1.129</url><doi>10.1093/aobpla/ply004</doi><bibkey>Sniderhan-etal-2018-Assessing</bibkey></paper><paper id="130"><title>Water table dynamics in a constructed wetland, Fort McMurray, Alberta</title><author><first>Haley</first><last>M. Spennato</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Ketcheson</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Mendoza</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Carey</last></author><abstract>Surface mining in northern Alberta transforms wetlands and forests into open pits, tailings ponds, and overburden. As part of their license to operate, mine operators are required to reclaim this altered landscape to a predisturbance capacity. In 2012, Syncrude Canada Limited constructed one of the first of two reclaimed wetlands, the Sandhill Fen Watershed (SFW), to evaluate wetland reclamation strategies. SFW is a 52‐ha system atop soft‐tailings that includes an inflow/outflow pump system, underdrains, upland hummocks, and a fen lowland. In this study, water table dynamics of the fen lowland were evaluated in the 2 years following commissioning (2014–2015) to assess whether this newly constructed watershed has hydrological conditions that facilitate hydric soils with water table regimes similar to reference systems. Results indicate that the location and hydrophysical properties of placed materials control water table responses to both water management and precipitation. This differential water table response in the SFW lowland drove lateral fluxes between adjacent landforms, suggesting periods of intermittent water supply from uplands to wetlands along hummock margins. As in natural systems, the lowland fen exhibited several lateral flow reversals over the 2 years depending upon water level. Water tables on‐average were greater than those observed in natural analogues. Comparison during these first 2 years following commissioning contribute to the increasing insight as to how construction and management practices support reclamation postmining.</abstract><url hash="8285a61a">2018.GWF-1.130</url><doi>10.1002/hyp.13308</doi><bibkey>M. Spennato-etal-2018-Water</bibkey></paper><paper id="131"><title>Precipitation characteristics and associated weather conditions on the eastern slopes of the Canadian Rockies during March–April 2015</title><author><first>J.</first><last>Thériault</last></author><author><first>Ida</first><last>Hung</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Vaquer</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Stewart</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pomeroy</last></author><abstract>Abstract. Precipitation events that bring rain and snow to the
Banff–Calgary area of Alberta are a critical aspect of the region's water
cycle and can lead to major flooding events such as the June 2013 event that
was the second most costly natural disaster in Canadian history. Because no
special atmospheric-oriented observations of these events have been made, a
field experiment was conducted in March and April 2015 in Kananaskis,
Alberta, to begin to fill this gap. The goal was to characterize and better
understand the formation of the precipitation at the surface during
spring 2015 at a specific location in the Kananaskis Valley. Within the
experiment, detailed measurements of precipitation and weather conditions
were obtained, a vertically pointing Doppler radar was deployed and weather
balloons were released. Although 17 precipitation events occurred, this
period was associated with much less precipitation than normal (−35 %)
and above-normal temperatures (2.5 ∘C). Of the 133 h of observed
precipitation, solid precipitation occurred 71 % of the time, mixed
precipitation occurred 9 % and rain occurred 20 %. An analysis of
17 504 precipitation particles from 1181 images showed that a wide variety
of crystals and aggregates occurred and approximately 63 % showed signs of
riming. This was largely independent of whether flows aloft were upslope
(easterly) or downslope (westerly). In the often sub-saturated surface
conditions, hydrometeors containing ice occurred at temperatures as high as
9 ∘C. Radar structures aloft were highly variable with reflectivity
sometimes &gt;30 dBZe and Doppler velocity up to −1 m s−1, which
indicates upward motion of particles within ascending air masses.
Precipitation was formed in this region within cloud fields sometimes having
variable structures and within which supercooled water at least sometimes
existed to produce accreted particles massive enough to reach the surface
through the relatively dry sub-cloud region.
</abstract><url hash="f582968c">2018.GWF-1.131</url><doi>10.5194/HESS-22-4491-2018</doi><bibkey>Thériault-etal-2018-Precipitation</bibkey></paper><paper id="132"><title>The predictability of a lake phytoplankton community, over time-scales of hours to years.</title><author><first>Mridul</first><last>K. Thomas</last></author><author><first>Simone</first><last>Fontana</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Reyes</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Kehoe</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Pomati</last></author><abstract>Forecasting changes to ecological communities is one of the central challenges in ecology. However, nonlinear dependencies, biotic interactions and data limitations have limited our ability to assess how predictable communities are. Here, we used a machine learning approach and environmental monitoring data (biological, physical and chemical) to assess the predictability of phytoplankton cell density in one lake across an unprecedented range of time-scales. Communities were highly predictable over hours to months: model R2 decreased from 0.89 at 4 hours to 0.74 at 1 month, and in a long-term dataset lacking fine spatial resolution, from 0.46 at 1 month to 0.32 at 10 years. When cyanobacterial and eukaryotic algal cell densities were examined separately, model-inferred environmental growth dependencies matched laboratory studies, and suggested novel trade-offs governing their competition. High-frequency monitoring and machine learning can set prediction targets for process-based models and help elucidate the mechanisms underlying ecological dynamics.</abstract><url hash="6c8bc736">2018.GWF-1.132</url><doi>10.1111/ele.12927</doi><bibkey>K. Thomas-etal-2018-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="133"><title>Biogeochemical asynchrony: Ecosystem drivers of seasonal concentration regimes across the Great Lakes Basin</title><author><first>K.</first><last>V. Van Meter</last></author><author><first>Shadman</first><last>T. Chowdhury</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Byrnes</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Basu</last></author><abstract>Changes in seasonal nutrient dynamics are occurring across a range of climates and land use types. Although it is known that seasonal patterns in nutrient availability are key drivers of both stream metabolism and eutrophication, there has been little success in developing a comprehensive understanding of seasonal variations in nutrient export across watersheds or of the relationship between nutrient seasonality and watershed characteristics. In the present study, we have used concentration and discharge data from more than 200 stations across U.S. and Canadian watersheds to identify (1) archetypal seasonal concentration regimes for nitrate, soluble reactive phosphorus (SRP), and total phosphorus, and (2) dominant watershed controls on these regimes across a gradient of climate, land use, and topography. Our analysis shows that less impacted watersheds, with more forested and wetland area, most commonly exhibit concentration regimes that are in phase with discharge, with concentration lows occurring during summer low‐flow periods. Agricultural watersheds also commonly exhibit in‐phase behavior, though the seasonality is usually muted compared to that seen in less impacted areas. With increasing urban area, however, nutrient concentrations frequently become essentially aseasonal or even exhibit clearly out‐of‐phase behavior. In addition, our data indicate that seasonal SRP concentration patterns may be strongly influenced by proximal controls such as the presence of dams and reservoirs. In all, these results suggest that human activity is significantly altering nutrient concentration regimes, with large potential consequences for both in‐stream metabolism and eutrophication risk in downstream waterbodies.</abstract><url hash="1b8cf7a0">2018.GWF-1.133</url><doi>10.1002/lno.11353</doi><bibkey>V. Van Meter-etal-2018-Biogeochemical</bibkey></paper><paper id="134"><title>Legacy nitrogen may prevent achievement of water quality goals in the Gulf of Mexico</title><author><first>K.</first><last>V. Van Meter</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Van Cappellen</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Basu</last></author><abstract>Haunted by the past Reducing the extent of hypoxia in the Gulf of Mexico will not be as easy as reducing agricultural nitrogen use. Van Meter et al. report that so much nitrogen from runoff has accumulated in the Mississippi River basin that, even if future agricultural nitrogen inputs are eliminated, it will still take 30 years to realize the 60% decrease in load needed to reduce eutrophication in the Gulf. This legacy effect means that a dramatic shift in land-use practices, which may not be compatible with current levels of agricultural production, will be needed to control hypoxia in the Gulf of Mexico. Science, this issue p. 427 Agricultural nitrogen stored in Mississippi watersheds will slow efforts to reduce hypoxia in the Gulf of Mexico. In August 2017, the Gulf of Mexico’s hypoxic zone was declared to be the largest ever measured. It has been estimated that a 60% decrease in watershed nitrogen (N) loading may be necessary to adequately reduce eutrophication in the Gulf. However, to date there has been no rigorous assessment of the effect of N legacies on achieving water quality goals. In this study, we show that even if agricultural N use became 100% efficient, it would take decades to meet target N loads due to legacy N within the Mississippi River basin. Our results suggest that both long-term commitment and large-scale changes in agricultural management practices will be necessary to decrease Mississippi N loads and to meet current goals for reducing the size of the Gulf hypoxic zone.</abstract><url hash="85e86203">2018.GWF-1.134</url><doi>10.1126/science.aar4462</doi><bibkey>V. Van Meter-etal-2018-Legacy</bibkey></paper><paper id="135"><title>DOs and DON'Ts for using climate change information for water resource planning and management: guidelines for study design</title><author><first>J.</first><last>Vano</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Arnold</last></author><author><first>Bart</first><last>Nijssen</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Clark</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Wood</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Gutmann</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Addor</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Hamman</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Lehner</last></author><abstract /><url hash="f2ef5295">2018.GWF-1.135</url><doi>10.1016/J.CLISER.2018.07.002</doi><bibkey>Vano-etal-2018-DOs</bibkey></paper><paper id="136"><title>Soil organic layer combustion in boreal black spruce and jack pine stands of the Northwest Territories, Canada</title><author><first>X.</first><last>Walker</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Baltzer</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Cumming</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>J. Day</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Johnstone</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Rogers</last></author><author><first>Kylen</first><last>Solvik</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Turetsky</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Mack</last></author><abstract>Increased fire frequency, extent and severity are expected to strongly affect the structure and function of boreal forest ecosystems. In this study, we examined 213 plots in boreal forests dominated by black spruce (Picea mariana) or jack pine (Pinus banksiana) of the Northwest Territories, Canada, after an unprecedentedly large area burned in 2014. Large fire size is associated with high fire intensity and severity, which would manifest as areas with deep burning of the soil organic layer (SOL). Our primary objectives were to estimate burn depth in these fires and then to characterise landscapes vulnerable to deep burning throughout this region. Here we quantify burn depth in black spruce stands using the position of adventitious roots within the soil column, and in jack pine stands using measurements of burned and unburned SOL depths. Using these estimates, we then evaluate how burn depth and the proportion of SOL combusted varies among forest type, ecozone, plot-level moisture and stand density. Our results suggest that most of the SOL was combusted in jack pine stands regardless of plot moisture class, but that black spruce forests experience complete combustion of the SOL only in dry and moderately well-drained landscape positions. The models and calibrations we present in this study should allow future research to more accurately estimate burn depth in Canadian boreal forests.</abstract><url hash="6be6032f">2018.GWF-1.136</url><doi>10.1071/WF17095</doi><bibkey>Walker-etal-2018-Soil</bibkey></paper><paper id="137"><title>Cross‐scale controls on carbon emissions from boreal forest megafires</title><author><first>X.</first><last>Walker</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Rogers</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Baltzer</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Cumming</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>J. Day</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Goetz</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Johnstone</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Schuur</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Turetsky</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Mack</last></author><abstract>Climate warming and drying is associated with increased wildfire disturbance and the emergence of megafires in North American boreal forests. Changes to the fire regime are expected to strongly increase combustion emissions of carbon (C) which could alter regional C balance and positively feedback to climate warming. In order to accurately estimate C emissions and thereby better predict future climate feedbacks, there is a need to understand the major sources of heterogeneity that impact C emissions at different scales. Here, we examined 211 field plots in boreal forests dominated by black spruce (Picea mariana) or jack pine (Pinus banksiana) of the Northwest Territories (NWT), Canada after an unprecedentedly large area burned in 2014. We assessed both aboveground and soil organic layer (SOL) combustion, with the goal of determining the major drivers in total C emissions, as well as to develop a high spatial resolution model to scale emissions in a relatively understudied region of the boreal forest. On average, 3.35 kg C m−2 was combusted and almost 90% of this was from SOL combustion. Our results indicate that black spruce stands located at landscape positions with intermediate drainage contribute the most to C emissions. Indices associated with fire weather and date of burn did not impact emissions, which we attribute to the extreme fire weather over a short period of time. Using these results, we estimated a total of 94.3 Tg C emitted from 2.85 Mha of burned area across the entire 2014 NWT fire complex, which offsets almost 50% of mean annual net ecosystem production in terrestrial ecosystems of Canada. Our study also highlights the need for fine‐scale estimates of burned area that represent small water bodies and regionally specific calibrations of combustion that account for spatial heterogeneity in order to accurately model emissions at the continental scale.</abstract><url hash="1ce133b9">2018.GWF-1.137</url><doi>10.1111/gcb.14287</doi><bibkey>Walker-etal-2018-Cross‐scale</bibkey></paper><paper id="138"><title>Semi-Automated Classification of Lake Ice Cover Using Dual Polarization RADARSAT-2 Imagery</title><author><first>Junqian</first><last>Wang</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Duguay</last></author><author><first>David</first><last>A Clausi</last></author><author><first>V.</first><last>Pinard</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Howell</last></author><abstract>Lake ice is a significant component of the cryosphere due to its large spatial coverage in high-latitude regions during the winter months. The Laurentian Great Lakes are the world’s largest supply of freshwater and their ice cover has a major impact on regional weather and climate, ship navigation, and public safety. Ice experts at the Canadian Ice Service (CIS) have been manually producing operational Great Lakes image analysis charts based on visual interpretation of the synthetic aperture radar (SAR) images. In that regard, we have investigated the performance of the semi-automated segmentation algorithm “glocal” Iterative Region Growing with Semantics (IRGS) for lake ice classification using dual polarized RADARSAT-2 imagery acquired over Lake Erie. Analysis of various case studies indicated that the “glocal” IRGS algorithm could provide a reliable ice-water classification using dual polarized images with a high overall accuracy of 90.4%. However, lake ice types that are based on stage of development were not effectively identified due to the ambiguous relation between backscatter and ice types. The slight improvement of using dual-pol as opposed to single-pol images for ice-water discrimination was also demonstrated.</abstract><url hash="8c5e2e28">2018.GWF-1.138</url><doi>10.3390/rs10111727</doi><bibkey>Wang-etal-2018-Semi-Automated</bibkey></paper><paper id="139"><title>Recent global decline in endorheic basin water storages</title><author><first>Jida</first><last>Wang</last></author><author><first>Chunqiao</first><last>Song</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Reager</last></author><author><first>Fangfang</first><last>Yao</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Famiglietti</last></author><author><first>Y.</first><last>Sheng</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>MacDonald</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Brun</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Schmied</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Marston</last></author><author><first>Y.</first><last>Wada</last></author><abstract /><url hash="fb591ebe">2018.GWF-1.139</url><doi>10.1038/s41561-018-0265-7</doi><bibkey>Wang-etal-2018-Recent</bibkey></paper><paper id="140"><title>Beaver Dams Induce Hyporheic and Biogeochemical Changes in Riparian Areas in a Mountain Peatland</title><author><first>Xiaoyue</first><last>Wang</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>L. Shaw</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Westbrook</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Bedard-Haughn</last></author><abstract /><url hash="cdc430dd">2018.GWF-1.140</url><doi>10.1007/s13157-018-1059-9</doi><bibkey>Wang-etal-2018-Beaver</bibkey></paper><paper id="141"><title>Minor contribution of overstorey transpiration to landscape evapotranspiration in boreal permafrost peatlands</title><author><first>Rebecca</first><last>K. Warren</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Pappas</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Helbig</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Chasmer</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Berg</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Baltzer</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Quinton</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Sonnentag</last></author><abstract>Evapotranspiration (ET) is a key component of the water cycle, whereby accurate partitioning of ET into evaporation and transpiration provides important information about the intrinsically coupled carbon, water, and energy fluxes. Currently, global estimates of partitioned evaporative and transpiration fluxes remain highly uncertain, especially for high‐latitude ecosystems where measurements are scarce. Forested peat plateaus underlain by permafrost and surrounded by permafrost‐free wetlands characterize approximately 60% (7.0 × 107 km2) of Canadian peatlands. In this study, 22 Picea mariana (black spruce) individuals, the most common tree species of the North American boreal forest, were instrumented with sap flow sensors within the footprint of an eddy covariance tower measuring ET from a forest–wetland mosaic landscape. Sap flux density (JS), together with remote sensing data and in situ measurements of canopy structure, was used to upscale tree‐level JS to overstorey transpiration (TBS). Black spruce trees growing in nutrient‐poor permafrost peat soils were found to have lower mean JS than those growing in mineral soils. Overall, TBS contributed less than 1% to landscape ET. Climate‐change‐induced forest loss and the expansion of wetlands may further minimize the contributions of TBS to ET and increase the contribution of standing water.</abstract><url hash="bac3004b">2018.GWF-1.141</url><doi>10.1002/eco.1975</doi><bibkey>K. Warren-etal-2018-Minor</bibkey></paper><paper id="142"><title>Globally scalable alpine snow metrics</title><author><first>N.</first><last>Wayand</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Marsh</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Shea</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pomeroy</last></author><abstract /><url hash="23ca51f1">2018.GWF-1.142</url><doi>10.1016/J.RSE.2018.05.012</doi><bibkey>Wayand-etal-2018-Globally</bibkey></paper><paper id="143"><title>Topoedaphic and Forest Controls on Post-Fire Vegetation Assemblies Are Modified by Fire History and Burn Severity in the Northwestern Canadian Boreal Forest</title><author><first>E.</first><last>Whitman</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Parisien</last></author><author><first>Dan</first><last>K. Thompson</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Flannigan</last></author><abstract>Wildfires, which constitute the most extensive natural disturbance of the boreal biome, produce a broad range of ecological impacts to vegetation and soils that may influence post-fire vegetation assemblies and seedling recruitment. We inventoried post-fire understory vascular plant communities and tree seedling recruitment in the northwestern Canadian boreal forest and characterized the relative importance of fire effects and fire history, as well as non-fire drivers (i.e., the topoedaphic context and climate), to post-fire vegetation assemblies. Topoedaphic context, pre-fire forest structure and composition, and climate primarily controlled the understory plant communities and shifts in the ranked dominance of tree species (***8% and **13% of variance explained, respectively); however, fire and fire-affected soils were significant secondary drivers of post-fire vegetation. Wildfire had a significant indirect effect on understory vegetation communities through post-fire soil properties (**5%), and fire history and burn severity explained the dominance shifts of tree species (*7%). Fire-related variables were important explanatory variables in classification and regression tree models explaining the dominance shifts of four tree species (R2 = 0.43–0.65). The dominance of jack pine (Pinus banksiana Lamb.) and trembling aspen (Populus tremuloides Michx.) increased following fires, whereas that of black spruce (Picea mariana (Mill.) BSP.) and white spruce (Picea glauca (Moench) Voss) declined. The overriding importance of site and climate to post-fire vegetation assemblies may confer some resilience to disturbed forests; however, if projected increases in fire activity in the northwestern boreal forest are borne out, secondary pathways of burn severity, fire frequency, and fire effects on soils are likely to accelerate ongoing climate-driven shifts in species compositions.</abstract><url hash="54cd6167">2018.GWF-1.143</url><doi>10.3390/F9030151</doi><bibkey>Whitman-etal-2018-Topoedaphic</bibkey></paper><paper id="144"><title>The effects of black spruce fuel management on surface fuel condition and peat burn severity in an experimental fire</title><author><first>S.</first><last>Wilkinson</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Moore</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Thompson</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>M. Wotton</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Hvenegaard</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Schroeder</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Waddington</last></author><abstract>In the boreal plains ecozone, black spruce (Picea mariana (Mill.) Britton, Sterns &amp; Poggenb.) peatlands can represent large parts of the expanding wildland–urban interface (WUI) and wildland–industry interface (WII). The boreal plains wildfire regime is predicted to increase in areal extent and intensity, amplifying the need for wildfire management to protect the WUI and WII. Forested peatland ecosystems can burn at high intensity and present challenges for wildfire managers such as severe smouldering combustion and large carbon loss. Fuel management techniques such as mulching treatments (converting surface and canopy fuel to a masticated fuelbed) can be applied to black spruce peatlands, yet the impact on fuel load, condition, and peat burn severity is unclear. Using observations from an experimental fire, we found that a mulch-thinning fuel treatment could reduce peat depth of burn. However, where peat bulk density was increased by compaction, this led to an increased peat combustion carbon loss relati...</abstract><url hash="caa9f4c4">2018.GWF-1.144</url><doi>10.1139/CJFR-2018-0217</doi><bibkey>Wilkinson-etal-2018-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="145"><title>Plot-scale assessment of soil freeze/thaw detection and variability with impedance probes: implications for remote sensing validation networks.</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Williamson</last></author><author><first>Justin</first><last>R. Adams</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Berg</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Derksen</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Toose</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Walker</last></author><abstract>Several large in-situ soil moisture-monitoring networks currently exist over seasonally frozen regions that may have use for the validation of remote sensing soil freeze/thaw (F/T) products. However, further understanding of how the existing network instrumentation responds to changes in near surface soil F/T is recommended. This case study describes the results of a small plot-scale (7 × 7 m) study from November 2013 through April 2014 instrumented with 36 impedance probes. Soil temperature and real dielectric permittivity ϵ r 9 were measured every 15 minutes during F/T transition periods at shallow soil depths (0–10 cm). Categorical soil temperature and real dielectric permittivity techniques were used to define the soil F/T state during these periods. Results demonstrate that both methods for detecting soil F/T have strong agreement (84.7–95.6%) during the fall freeze but weak agreement (53.3–60.9%) during the spring thaw. Bootstrapping results demonstrated both techniques showed a mean difference within ±1.0°C and ±1.4 ϵ r 9 between the standard 5 cm below surface measurement depth and probes at 2, 10 and integrated 0–5.7 cm depths installed within the same study plot. Overall this study demonstrates that the Hydra Probe offers promise for near surface soil F/T detection using existing soil moisture monitoring networks particularly for the fall freeze.</abstract><url hash="bdaec452">2018.GWF-1.145</url><doi>10.2166/NH.2017.183</doi><bibkey>Williamson-etal-2018-Plot-scale</bibkey></paper><paper id="146"><title>L-band radiometry freeze/ thaw validation using air temperature and ground measurements</title><author><first>M.</first><last>Williamson</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Rowlandson</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Berg</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Roy</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Toose</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Derksen</last></author><author><first>Lauren</first><last>Arnold</last></author><author><first>Erica</first><last>Tetlock</last></author><abstract>ABSTRACT Assessment of remote sensing derived freeze/thaw products from L-band radiometry requires ground validation. There is growing interest in utilizing soil moisture networks to meet this validation requirement, although it remains unclear whether the current configuration of these networks is appropriate. To address this issue, a small-scale L-band radiometry study was conducted from November 2014 to April 2015 to capture F/T events. Soil moisture probes measuring soil temperature and real dielectric permittivity were installed within a surface-based L-band radiometer footprint vertically at the surface and horizontally at 2.5, 5 and 10 cm depths. A binary freeze/thaw product was derived using radiometer brightness temperatures and compared to the binary F/T classification using soil temperature, real dielectric permittivity and air temperature measurements. The results of the study found that shallow probe depths (vertical and 2.5 cm) resulted in an improvement in the radiometer F/T product accuracy over the standard 5 cm instrument depth currently utilized at soil moisture networks. Air temperature based approaches for validation result in lower accuracy for F/T events with no snow or wet snow, but performed similarly to soil measurements of temperature and permittivity during dry snow F/T events.</abstract><url hash="24a795e8">2018.GWF-1.146</url><doi>10.1080/2150704X.2017.1422872</doi><bibkey>Williamson-etal-2018-L-band</bibkey></paper><paper id="147"><title>From principles to practice in paying for nature’s services</title><author><first>S.</first><last>Wunder</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Brouwer</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Engel</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Ezzine‐de‐Blas</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Muradian</last></author><author><first>U.</first><last>Pascual</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Pinto</last></author><abstract /><url hash="53a0a57e">2018.GWF-1.147</url><doi>10.1038/s41893-018-0036-x</doi><bibkey>Wunder-etal-2018-From</bibkey></paper><paper id="148"><title>In situ microbiota distinguished primary anthropogenic stressor in freshwater sediments.</title><author><first>Yuwei</first><last>Xie</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Floehr</last></author><author><first>Xiaowei</first><last>Zhang</last></author><author><first>Hongxia</first><last>Xiao</last></author><author><first>Jianghu</first><last>Yang</last></author><author><first>Pu</first><last>Xia</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>A. Burton</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Hollert</last></author><abstract /><url hash="c31fb8ef">2018.GWF-1.148</url><doi>10.1016/j.envpol.2018.03.099</doi><bibkey>Xie-etal-2018-In</bibkey></paper><paper id="149"><title>eDNA-based bioassessment of coastal sediments impacted by an oil spill.</title><author><first>Yuwei</first><last>Xie</last></author><author><first>Xiaowei</first><last>Zhang</last></author><author><first>Jianghu</first><last>Yang</last></author><author><first>Seonjin</first><last>Kim</last></author><author><first>Seongjin</first><last>Hong</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Giesy</last></author><author><first>U.</first><last>Yim</last></author><author><first>W.</first><last>Shim</last></author><author><first>Hongxia</first><last>Yu</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Khim</last></author><abstract /><url hash="b4188879">2018.GWF-1.149</url><doi>10.1016/j.envpol.2018.02.081</doi><bibkey>Xie-etal-2018-eDNA-based</bibkey></paper><paper id="150"><title>Environmental Indicator Principium with Case References to Agricultural Soil, Water, and Air Quality and Model-Derived Indicators.</title><author><first>T.</first><last>Zhang</last></author><author><first>Z.</first><last>Zheng</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Lal</last></author><author><first>Z.</first><last>Q. Lin</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Sharpley</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Shober</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Smith</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>S. Tan</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Van Cappellen</last></author><abstract>Environmental indicators are powerful tools for tracking environmental changes, measuring environmental performance, and informing policymakers. Many diverse environmental indicators, including agricultural environmental indicators, are currently in use or being developed. This special collection of technical papers expands on the peer-reviewed literature on environmental indicators and their application to important current issues in the following areas: (i) model-derived indicators to indicate phosphorus losses from arable land to surface runoff and subsurface drainage, (ii) glutathione-ascorbate cycle-related antioxidants as early-warning bioindicators of polybrominated diphenyl ether toxicity in mangroves, and (iii) assessing the effectiveness of using organic matrix biobeds to limit herbicide dissipation from agricultural fields, thereby controlling on-farm point-source pollution. This introductory review also provides an overview of environmental indicators, mainly for agriculture, with examples related to the quality of the agricultural soil-water-air continuum and the application of model-derived indicators. Current knowledge gaps and future lines of investigation are also discussed. It appears that environmental indicators, particularly those for agriculture, work efficiently at the field, catchment, and local scales and serve as valuable metrics of system functioning and response; however, these indicators need to be refined or further developed to comprehensively meet community expectations in terms of providing a consistent picture of relevant issues and/or allowing comparisons to be made nationally or internationally.</abstract><url hash="d4df019c">2018.GWF-1.150</url><doi>10.2134/jeq2017.10.0398</doi><bibkey>Zhang-etal-2018-Environmental</bibkey></paper><paper id="151"><title>Evaluation of convection-permitting WRF CONUS simulation on the relationship between soil moisture and heatwaves</title><author><first>Zhe</first><last>Zhang</last></author><author><first>Yanping</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>Fei</first><last>Chen</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Barlage</last></author><author><first>Zhenhua</first><last>Li</last></author><abstract /><url hash="a3d8310a">2018.GWF-1.151</url><doi>10.1007/s00382-018-4508-5</doi><bibkey>Zhang-etal-2018-Evaluation</bibkey></paper><paper id="152"><title>Forward and Inverse Radar Modeling of Terrestrial Snow Using SnowSAR Data</title><author><first>Jiyue</first><last>Zhu</last></author><author><first>Shurun</first><last>Tan</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>King</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Derksen</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Lemmetyinen</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Tsang</last></author><abstract>In this paper, we develop a radar snow water equivalent (SWE) retrieval algorithm based on a parameterized forward model of bicontinuous dense media radiative transfer (Bic-DMRT). The algorithm is based on retrieving the absorption loss of the snowpack which is directly proportional to the SWE. In the algorithm, Bic-DMRT is first applied to generate a lookup table (LUT) of snowpack backscattering at X- and Ku-band. Regression training is applied to the LUT to transform the dual-frequency backscatter into functions of two parameters: the scattering albedo at X-band and SWE. The background scattering is subtracted from the SnowSAR data to give the volume scattering of snow. Classification of SnowSAR data is applied to provide a priori information. Based on the obtained volume scattering and the priori information, a cost function is established to find SWE. Performance of the retrieval algorithm was tested using three sets of airborne SnowSAR data acquired over mixed areas in Finland and open tundra landscape in Canada. It is shown that the retrieval algorithm has a root-mean-square error below 30 mm of SWE and a correlation coefficient above 0.64.</abstract><url hash="3ad160b0">2018.GWF-1.152</url><doi>10.1109/TGRS.2018.2848642</doi><bibkey>Zhu-etal-2018-Forward</bibkey></paper><paper id="153"><title>Historical drought patterns over Canada and their relation to teleconnections</title><author><first>Z.</first><last>E. Asong</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Wheater</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Bonsal</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Razavi</last></author><author><first>Sopan</first><last>Kurkute</last></author><abstract>Drought is a recurring extreme climate event and among the most costly natural disasters in the world. This is particularly true over Canada, where drought is both a frequent and damaging phenomenon with impacts on regional water resources, agriculture, industry, aquatic ecosystems and health. However, nation-wide drought assessments are currently lacking and impacted by limited ground-based observations. This study provides a comprehensive analysis of historical droughts over the whole of Canada, including the role of large-scale teleconnections. Drought events are characterized by the Standardized Precipitation-Evapotranspiration Index (SPEI) over various temporal scales (1, 3, 6, and 12 consecutive months, 6 months from April to September, and 12 months from October to September) applied to different gridded monthly data sets for the period 1950–2013. The Mann Kendall test, Rotated Empirical Orthogonal Function, Continuous Wavelet Transform, and Wavelet Coherence analyses are used, respectively, to investigate the trend, spatiotemporal patterns, periodicity, and teleconnectivity of drought events. Results indicate that southern (northern) parts of the country experienced significant trends towards drier (wetter) conditions although substantial variability exists. Two spatially well-defined regions with different temporal evolution of droughts were identified―the Canadian Prairies and Northern-central Canada. The analyses also revealed the presence of a dominant periodicity of between 8–32 months in the Prairie region, and 8–40 months in the Northern central region. These cycles of low-frequency variability are found to be associated principally to the Pacific-North American (PNA) and Multivariate El Nino/Southern Oscillation Index (MEI) relative to other considered large-scale climate indices. This study is the first of its kind to identify dominant periodicities in drought variability over the whole of Canada in terms of when the drought events occur, the duration, and how often they do so.</abstract><url hash="4dd65026">2018.GWF-1.153</url><doi>10.5194/HESS-2018-122</doi><bibkey>E. Asong-etal-2018-Historical1</bibkey></paper><paper id="154"><title>Investigating the impact of soil moisture on European summer climate in ensemble numerical experiments</title><author><first>C.</first><last>Ardilouze</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Batté</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Déqué</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>van Meijgaard</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>van den Hurk</last></author><abstract /><url hash="d3b2c585">2018.GWF-1.154</url><doi>10.1007/s00382-018-4358-1</doi><bibkey>Ardilouze-etal-2018-Investigating</bibkey></paper><paper id="155"><title>The spectral and radiometric calibration of the ENMAP onboard calibration assembly (OBCA) (Conference Presentation)</title><author><first>C.</first><last>Monte</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Reiniger</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Baltruschat</last></author><author><first>I.</first><last>Müller</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Wachter</last></author><author><first>Ludger</first><last>Wilkens</last></author><author><first>Felix</first><last>Theml</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Staton</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Taubert</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Hollandt</last></author><abstract>The Environmental Mapping and Analysis Program (EnMAP) is a German hyperspectral satellite mission to monitor and characterize the Earth’s environment. The EnMAP payload, the Hyper Spectral Imager (HSI) features an on-board calibration assembly (OBCA) which is designated to provide the optical radiation to monitor the instrument radiometric and spectral ‎stability during the ‎mission lifetime. The assembly comprises two integrating spheres in twin configuration equipped with several different optical radiation sources. The large ‎sphere made of white diffuse reflecting material is dedicated for radiometric stability ‎measurements, while the ‎small sphere, made of rare-earth doped diffuse reflecting material, is dedicated for spectral stability checks. ‎The ‎OBCA utilizes two types of optical radiation sources: ‎tungsten halogen lamps and white light LEDs.

Here we report on the spectral and radiometric calibration of the OBCA qualification and flight model in the Reduced Background Calibration Facility 2 (RBCF2) of Physikalisch-Technische Bundesanstalt (PTB) [1].

The demanding requirements were to perform a calibration in air and in vacuum with an uncertainty of less than 2% with a spectral resolution of 0.1 nm over a wavelength range from 400 nm to 2500 nm not exceeding an operating time of 40 h for the halogen lamps and 100 h for the LEDs. Furthermore, a precise mapping of the OBCA exit aperture of size 2 mm by 24 mm with 1 mm sampling diameter had to be performed. For that purposes PTB developed a calibration procedure based on spectral comparisons of the OBCA with respect to dedicated vacuum radiance standards with an FTS in three wavelength ranges which were covered by three beamsplitter detector combinations. A dedicated imaging optics was designed transforming the F:3 opening of the OBCA to the F:8 opening ratio of the FTS and providing also the required small sampling area. 

Before and after their application, the dedicated vacuum qualified radiance standards were calibrated against the primary standards of PTB and corrected for the transition from air to vacuum and back to account for possible drifts of the sources. By this procedure a spectral and radiometric calibration of the OBCA traceable to the SI was achieved with the aspired uncertainties.

[1] C. Monte et al, The new Reduced Background Calibration Facility 2 for Detectors, Cameras and Sources at the Physikalisch-Technische Bundesanstalt, Sensors, Systems, and Next-Generation Satellites SPIE 2018</abstract><url hash="a4b5f513">2018.GWF-1.155</url><doi>10.1117/12.2325750</doi><bibkey>Monte-etal-2018-The</bibkey></paper><paper id="156"><title>ESM-SnowMIP: assessing snow models and quantifying snow-related climate feedbacks</title><author><first>G.</first><last>Krinner</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Derksen</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Essery</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Flanner</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Hagemann</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Clark</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Hall</last></author><author><first>H.</first><last>Rott</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Brutel-Vuilmet</last></author><author><first>Hyungjun</first><last>Kim</last></author><author><first>Cecile</first><last>B Menard</last></author><author><first>L.</first><last>Mudryk</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Thackeray</last></author><author><first>Libo</first><last>Wang</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Arduini</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Balsamo</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Bartlett</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Boike</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Boone</last></author><author><first>F.</first><last>Chéruy</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Colin</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Cuntz</last></author><author><first>Yongjiu</first><last>Dai</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Decharme</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Derry</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Ducharne</last></author><author><first>E.</first><last>Dutra</last></author><author><first>X.</first><last>Fang</last></author><author><first>C.</first><last>Fierz</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Ghattas</last></author><author><first>Y.</first><last>Gusev</last></author><author><first>V.</first><last>Haverd</last></author><author><first>A.</first><last>Kontu</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Lafaysse</last></author><author><first>R.</first><last>Law</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Lawrence</last></author><author><first>Weiping</first><last>Li</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Marke</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Marks</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Ménégoz</last></author><author><first>O.</first><last>Nasonova</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Nitta</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Niwano</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Pomeroy</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Raleigh</last></author><author><first>G.</first><last>Schaedler</last></author><author><first>V.</first><last>Semenov</last></author><author><first>Tanya</first><last>G. Smirnova</last></author><author><first>T.</first><last>Stacke</last></author><author><first>U.</first><last>Strasser</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Svenson</last></author><author><first>D.</first><last>Turkov</last></author><author><first>Tao</first><last>Wang</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>Wever</last></author><author><first>Hua</first><last>Yuan</last></author><author><first>Wenyan</first><last>Zhou</last></author><author><first>Dan</first><last>Zhu</last></author><abstract>Abstract. This paper describes ESM-SnowMIP, an international coordinated modelling
effort to evaluate current snow schemes, including snow schemes that are
included in Earth system models, in a wide variety of settings against local
and global observations. The project aims to identify crucial processes and
characteristics that need to be improved in snow models in the context of
local- and global-scale modelling. A further objective of ESM-SnowMIP is to
better quantify snow-related feedbacks in the Earth system. Although it is
not part of the sixth phase of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project
(CMIP6), ESM-SnowMIP is tightly linked to the CMIP6-endorsed Land Surface,
Snow and Soil Moisture Model Intercomparison (LS3MIP).
</abstract><url hash="3dbca4a9">2018.GWF-1.156</url><doi>10.5194/GMD-11-5027-2018</doi><bibkey>Krinner-etal-2018-ESM-SnowMIP:</bibkey></paper><paper id="157"><title>Did enhanced afforestation cause high severity peat burn in the Fort McMurray Horse River wildfire?</title><author><first>S.</first><last>Wilkinson</last></author><author><first>P.</first><last>Moore</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Flannigan</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>M. Wotton</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Waddington</last></author><abstract>Climate change mediated drying of boreal peatlands is expected to enhance peatland afforestation and wildfire vulnerability. The water table depth–afforestation feedback represents a positive feedback that can enhance peat drying and consolidation and thereby increase peat burn severity; exacerbating the challenges and costs of wildfire suppression efforts and potentially shifting the peatland to a persistent source of atmospheric carbon. To address this wildfire management challenge, we examined burn severity across a gradient of drying in a black spruce dominated peatland that was partially drained in 1975−1980 and burned in the 2016 Fort McMurray Horse River wildfire. We found that post-drainage black spruce annual ring width increased substantially with intense drainage. Average (±SD) basal diameter was 2.6 ± 1.2 cm, 3.2 ± 2.0 cm and 7.9 ± 4.7 cm in undrained (UD), moderately drained (MD) and heavily drained (HD) treatments, respectively. Depth of burn was significantly different between treatments (p &lt; 0.001) and averaged (±SD) 2.5 ± 3.5 cm, 6.4 ± 5.0 cm and 36.9 ± 29.6 cm for the UD, MD and HD treatments, respectively. The high burn severity in the HD treatment included 38% of the treatment that experienced combustion of the entire peat profile, and we estimate that overall 51% of the HD pre-burn peat carbon stock was lost. We argue that the HD treatment surpassed an ecohydrological tipping point to high severity peat burn that may be identified using black spruce stand characteristics in boreal plains bogs. While further studies are needed, we believe that quantifying this threshold will aid in developing effective adaptive management techniques and protecting boreal peatland carbon stocks.</abstract><url hash="4abb943f">2018.GWF-1.157</url><doi>10.1088/1748-9326/aaa136</doi><bibkey>Wilkinson-etal-2018-Did</bibkey></paper><paper id="158"><title>ABoVE: Wildfire Carbon Emissions and Burned Plot Characteristics, NWT, CA, 2014-2016</title><author><first>X.</first><last>Walker</last></author><author><first>B.</first><last>Rogers</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Baltzer</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Cummings</last></author><author><first>N.</first><last>J. Day</last></author><author><first>S.</first><last>Goetz</last></author><author><first>J.</first><last>Johnstone</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Turetsky</last></author><author><first>M.</first><last>Mack</last></author><abstract /><url hash="da0489ae">2018.GWF-1.158</url><doi>10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1561</doi><bibkey>Walker-etal-2018-ABoVE:</bibkey></paper></volume></collection>