<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<collection id="G23">
	<volume id="1">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems, Volume 15, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Geophysical Union (AGU)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Challenges in Hydrologic‐Land Surface Modeling of Permafrost Signatures—A Canadian Perspective</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mohamed S.</first>
				<last>Abdelhamed</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mohamed</first>
				<last>Elshamy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Saman</first>
				<last>Razavi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>H. S.</first>
				<last>Wheater</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Permafrost thaw/degradation in the Northern Hemisphere due to global warming is projected to accelerate in coming decades. Assessment of this trend requires improved understanding of the evolution and dynamics of permafrost areas. Land surface models (LSMs) are well-suited for this due to their physical basis and large-scale applicability. However, LSM application is challenging because (a) LSMs demand extensive and accurate meteorological forcing data, which are not readily available for historic conditions and only available with significant biases for future climate, (b) LSMs possess a large number of model parameters, and (c) observations of thermal/hydraulic regimes to constrain those parameters are severely limited. This study addresses these challenges by applying the MESH-CLASS modeling framework (Modélisation Environmenntale communautaire—Surface et Hydrology embedding the Canadian Land Surface Scheme) to three regions within the Mackenzie River Basin, Canada, under various meteorological forcing data sets, using the variogram analysis of response surfaces framework for sensitivity analysis and threshold-based identifiability analysis. The study shows that the modeler may face complex trade-offs when choosing a forcing data set; for current and future scenarios, forcing data require multi-variate bias correction, and some data sets enable the representation of some aspects of permafrost dynamics, but are inadequate for others. The results identify the most influential model parameters and show that permafrost simulation is most sensitive to parameters controlling surface insulation and runoff generation. But the identifiability analysis reveals that many of the most influential parameters are unidentifiable. These conclusions can inform future efforts for data collection and model parameterization.</abstract>
			<url hash="205d72cd">G23-1001</url>
			<doi>10.1029/2022ms003013</doi>
			<bibkey>Abdelhamed-2023-Challenges</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>			
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="2">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrology and Earth System Sciences Discussions, Volume 2023</booktitle>
			<publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>On the optimal level of complexity for the representation of wetland systems in land surface models</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mennatullah</first>
				<last>Elrashidy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>A. M.</first>
				<last>Ireson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Saman</first>
				<last>Razavi</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. Wetland systems are among the largest stores of carbon on the planet, most biologically diverse of all ecosystems, and dominant controls of the hydrologic cycle. However, their representation in land surface models (LSMs), which are the terrestrial lower boundary of Earth system models (ESMs) that inform climate actions, is limited. Here, we explore different possible parametrizations to represent wetland-groundwater-upland interactions with varying levels of system and computational complexity. We perform a series of numerical experiments that are informed by field observations from wetlands in the well-instrumented White Gull Creek in Saskatchewan, in the boreal region of North America. We show that the typical representation of wetlands in LSMs, which ignores interactions with groundwater and uplands, can be inadequate. We show that the optimal level of model complexity depends on the land cover, soil type, and the ultimate modelling purpose, being nowcasting and prediction, scenario analysis, or diagnostic learning.</abstract>
			<url hash="dce6bc0f">G23-2003</url>
			<doi>10.5194/hess-2023-68</doi>
			<bibkey>Elrashidy-2023-On</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
		<paper id="2">
			<title>Modeling the sensitivity of snowmelt, soil moisture and streamflow generation to climate over the Canadian Prairies using a basin classification approach</title>
			<author>
				<first>Zhaofeng</first>
				<last>He</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kevin</first>
				<last>Shook</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Christopher</first>
				<last>Spence</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Colin J.</first>
				<last>Whitfield</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. This study evaluated the effects of climate perturbations on snowmelt, soil moisture and streamflow generation in small Canadian Prairie basins using a modeling approach based on classification of basin biophysical and hydraulic parameters. Seven basin classes that encompass the entirety of the Prairie ecozone in Canada were determined by cluster analysis of biophysical characteristics. Individual semi-distributed virtual basin (VB) models representing these classes were parameterized in the Cold Regions Hydrological Model (CRHM) platform which includes modules for snowmelt and sublimation, soil freezing and thawing, actual evapotranspiration (ET), soil moisture dynamics, groundwater recharge and depressional storage dynamics including fill and spill runoff generation and variable connected areas. Precipitation (P) and temperature (T) perturbation scenarios covering the range of climate model predictions for the 21st century were used to evaluate climate sensitivity of hydrological processes in individual land cover and basin types across the Prairie ecozone. Results indicated that snow accumulation in wetlands had a greater sensitivity to P and T than that in croplands and grasslands in all the basin types. Wetland soil moisture was also more sensitive to T than the cropland and grassland soil moisture. Jointly influenced by land cover distribution and local climate, basin-average snow accumulation was more sensitive to T in the drier and grassland-characterized basins than in the wetter basins dominated by cropland, whilst basin-average soil moisture was most sensitive to T and P perturbations in basins typified by pothole depressions and broad river valleys. Annual streamflow had the greatest sensitivities to T and P in the dry and poorly connected Interior Grassland basins but the smallest in the wet and well-connected Southern Manitoba basins. The ability of P to compensate for warming induced reductions in snow accumulation and streamflow was much higher in the wetter and cropland-dominated basins than in the drier and grassland-characterized basins, whilst decreases in cropland soil moisture induced by the maximum expected warming of 6 °C could be fully offset by P increase of 11 % in all the basins. These results can be used to 1) identify locations which had the largest hydrological sensitivities to changing climate; and 2) diagnose underlying processes responsible for hydrological responses to expected climate change. Variations of hydrological sensitivity in land cover and basin types suggest that different water management and adaptation methods are needed to address enhanced water stress due to expected climate change in different regions of the Prairie ecozone.</abstract>
			<url hash="428229ac">G23-2004</url>
			<doi>10.5194/hess-2023-71</doi>
			<bibkey>He-2023-Modeling</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="3">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Climate, Volume 36, Issue 9</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Meteorological Society</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Changes of Extreme Precipitation in CMIP6 Projections: Should We Use Stationary or Nonstationary Models?</title>
			<author>
				<first>Hebatallah Mohamed</first>
				<last>Abdelmoaty</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Simon Michael</first>
				<last>Papalexiou</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract With global warming, the behavior of extreme precipitation shifts toward nonstationarity. Here, we analyze the annual maxima of daily precipitation (AMP) all over the globe using projections of the latest phase of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP6) under four shared socioeconomic pathways (SSPs). The projections were bias corrected using a semiparametric quantile mapping, a novel technique extended to extreme precipitation. This analysis 1) explores the variability of future AMP globally and 2) investigates the performance of stationary and nonstationary models in describing future AMP with trends. The results show that global warming potentially intensifies AMP. For the nonparametric analysis, the 33-yr precipitation levels are increasing up to 33.2 mm compared to the historical period. The parametric analysis shows that the return period of 100-yr historical events will decrease approximately to 50 and 70 years in the Northern and Southern Hemispheres, respectively. Under the highest emission scenario, the projected 100-yr levels are expected to increase by 7.5%–21% over the historical levels. Using stationary models to estimate the 100-yr return level for AMP projections with trends leads to an underestimation of 3.4% on average. Extensive Monte Carlo experiments are implemented to explain this underestimation.</abstract>
			<url hash="8a54ba46">G23-3001</url>
			<pages>2999-3014</pages>
			<doi>10.1175/jcli-d-22-0467.1</doi>
			<bibkey>Abdelmoaty-2023-Changes</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="4">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society, Volume 149, Issue 752</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Projected changes in the hotspots for agriculturally relevant compound events in Western Canada cropping regions under the &lt;scp&gt;RCP8&lt;/scp&gt;.5 scenario</title>
			<author>
				<first>Richard Yao Kuma</first>
				<last>Agyeman</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fei</first>
				<last>Huo</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zhenhua</first>
				<last>Li</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yanping</first>
				<last>Li</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The Canadian Prairies are a major grain production region, producing most of the wheat for export in Canada. Global warming and the associated changes in extreme precipitation and temperature events pose significant risks to agriculture on the Canadian Prairies. Compound hazards can cause higher crop failure than isolated events, especially in the main grain production regions in western Canada. To achieve informed climate risk management, it is critical to characterize the threats posed by compound hazards in current and future climates in western Canada. In this study, return periods of events were computed to assess the potential changes in the hotspots for agriculturally relevant compound events in western Canada using two convection-permitting climate simulations: current (CTL) climate and future climate under the RCP8.5 scenario based on a pseudo-global-warming (PGW) approach. Specifically, our study analyzed agricultural drought, low precipitation, heatwaves, and cool waves related to cool-season crops. The results showed the overall good performance of the CTL simulation in capturing spatial patterns of these compound events in western Canada. In the current climate, droughts and heatwaves co-occur mostly in southeastern parts of the prairies. Under the RCP8.5 scenario, they are likely to increase in frequency and expand to cover the major croplands of western Canada. This study provides information that policymakers in the fields of climate change adaptation and agricultural disaster management will find useful.</abstract>
			<url hash="178382ff">G23-4001</url>
			<pages>830-842</pages>
			<doi>10.1002/qj.4434</doi>
			<bibkey>Agyeman-2023-Projected</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="5">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Ecological Indicators, Volume 146</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Interactions of land-use cover and climate change at global level: How to mitigate the environmental risks and warming effects</title>
			<author>
				<first>Amir Hossein</first>
				<last>Barati</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Milad</first>
				<last>Zhoolideh</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hossein</first>
				<last>Azadi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ju-Hyoung</first>
				<last>Lee</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jürgen</first>
				<last>Scheffran</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Humanity deals with several challenges in this century such as climate change, land use, and land use/cover change (LUCC). Determining the patterns, developments, and consequences of LUCC issues for the livelihoods of people, especially poor people, is very important. Therefore, this paper aims to investigate the interactions between LUCC and climate change over the period of 1966–2015 (50 years) as a complex system at the global level. CO2 emissions and surface temperature are considered as the main indicators of climate change (CC). The data were analyzed in time-oriented (time-based) and local or place-oriented (country-based) manners. The results showed that arable and rangeland use changes (LUC) affect CO2 emissions in both direct and indirect ways. However, the direct effect of rangeland use change is positive, and its indirect effect is negative. In addition, deforestation has increased CO2 emissions indirectly. LUCC can also change the ability of the ecosystem to deliver services to people, including biodiversity and other resources such as food, fiber, water, etc. Therefore, it is critical to determine the patterns, trends, and impacts of LUCC on CC. Thus, CC mitigation policies should be followed by considering both direct and indirect effects. Without a doubt, this will be realized when the decision and policymakers have a better understanding of the structure and interaction between CC, LUCC, and their components as a whole system.</abstract>
			<url hash="af3fe59a">G23-5001</url>
			<pages>109829</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.ecolind.2022.109829</doi>
			<bibkey>Barati-2023-Interactions</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="6">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Flood Risk Management</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Towards a coherent flood forecasting framework for Canada: Local to global implications</title>
			<author>
				<first>Louise</first>
				<last>Arnal</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Alain</first>
				<last>Pietroniro</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Vincent</first>
				<last>Fortin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>David R.</first>
				<last>Casson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Tricia A.</first>
				<last>Stadnyk</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Prabin</first>
				<last>Rokaya</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Dorothy</first>
				<last>Durnford</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Evan</first>
				<last>Friesenhan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Martyn P.</first>
				<last>Clark</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Operational flood forecasting in Canada is a provincial responsibility that is carried out by several entities across the country. However, the increasing costs and impacts of floods require better and nationally coordinated flood prediction systems. A more coherent flood forecasting framework for Canada can enable implementing advanced prediction capabilities across the different entities with responsibility for flood forecasting. Recently, the Canadian meteorological and hydrological services were tasked to develop a national flow guidance system. Alongside this initiative, the Global Water Futures program has been advancing cold regions process understanding, hydrological modeling, and forecasting. A community of practice was established for industry, academia, and decision‐makers to share viewpoints on hydrological challenges. Taken together, these initiatives are paving the way towards a national flood forecasting framework. In this article, forecasting challenges are identified (with a focus on cold regions), and recommendations are made to promote the creation of this framework. These include the need for cooperation, well‐defined governance, and better knowledge mobilization. Opportunities and challenges posed by the increasing data availability globally are also highlighted. Advances in each of these areas are positioning Canada as a major contributor to the international operational flood forecasting landscape. This article highlights a route towards the deployment of capacities across large geographical domains.</abstract>
			<url hash="bd8a4a74">G23-6001</url>
			<doi>10.1111/jfr3.12895</doi>
			<bibkey>Arnal-2023-Towards</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="7">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Science of The Total Environment, Volume 876</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>A wastewater-based risk index for SARS-CoV-2 infections among three cities on the Canadian Prairie</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mohsen</first>
				<last>Asadi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Femi Francis</first>
				<last>Oloye</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yuwei</first>
				<last>Xie</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jenna</first>
				<last>Cantin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jonathan K.</first>
				<last>Challis</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kerry N.</first>
				<last>McPhedran</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Warsame</first>
				<last>Yusuf</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>David</first>
				<last>Champredon</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ximing</first>
				<last>Pu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Chantel De</first>
				<last>Lange</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Seba</first>
				<last>El-Baroudy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mark R.</first>
				<last>Servos</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Paul D.</first>
				<last>Jones</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Markus</first>
				<last>Brinkmann</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Wastewater surveillance (WWS) is useful to better understand the spreading of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in communities, which can help design and implement suitable mitigation measures. The main objective of this study was to develop the Wastewater Viral Load Risk Index (WWVLRI) for three Saskatchewan cities to offer a simple metric to interpret WWS. The index was developed by considering relationships between reproduction number, clinical data, daily per capita concentrations of virus particles in wastewater, and weekly viral load change rate. Trends of daily per capita concentrations of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater for Saskatoon, Prince Albert, and North Battleford were similar during the pandemic, suggesting that per capita viral load can be useful to quantitatively compare wastewater signals among cities and develop an effective and comprehensible WWVLRI. The effective reproduction number (Rt) and the daily per capita efficiency adjusted viral load thresholds of 85 × 106 and 200 × 106 N2 gene counts (gc)/population day (pd) were determined. These values with rates of change were used to categorize the potential for COVID-19 outbreaks and subsequent declines. The weekly average was considered 'low risk' when the per capita viral load was 85 × 106 N2 gc/pd. A 'medium risk' occurs when the per capita copies were between 85 × 106 and 200 × 106 N2 gc/pd. with a rate of change &lt;100 %. The start of an outbreak is indicated by a 'medium-high' risk classification when the week-over-week rate of change was &gt;100 %, and the absolute magnitude of concentrations of viral particles was &gt;85 × 106 N2 gc/pd. Lastly, a 'high risk' occurs when the viral load exceeds 200 × 106 N2 gc/pd. This methodology provides a valuable resource for decision-makers and health authorities, specifically given the limitation of COVID-19 surveillance based on clinical data.</abstract>
			<url hash="05362d11">G23-7001</url>
			<pages>162800</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.162800</doi>
			<bibkey>Asadi-2023-A</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
		<paper id="2">
			<title>Modeling multi-year phosphorus dynamics in a bioretention cell: Phosphorus partitioning, accumulation, and export</title>
			<author>
				<first>Bowen</first>
				<last>Zhou</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mahyar</first>
				<last>Shafii</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Christopher T.</first>
				<last>Parsons</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Elodie</first>
				<last>Passeport</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fereidoun</first>
				<last>Rezanezhad</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ariel</first>
				<last>Lisogorsky</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Phosphorus (P) export from urban areas via stormwater runoff contributes to eutrophication of downstream aquatic ecosystems. Bioretention cells are a Low Impact Development (LID) technology promoted as a green solution to attenuate urban peak flow discharge, as well as the export of excess nutrients and other contaminants. Despite their rapidly growing implementation worldwide, a predictive understanding of the efficiency of bioretention cells in reducing urban P loadings remains limited. Here, we present a reaction-transport model to simulate the fate and transport of P in a bioretention cell facility in the greater Toronto metropolitan area. The model incorporates a representation of the biogeochemical reaction network that controls P cycling within the cell. We used the model as a diagnostic tool to determine the relative importance of processes immobilizing P in the bioretention cell. The model predictions were compared to multi-year observational data on 1) the outflow loads of total P (TP) and soluble reactive P (SRP) during the 2012-2017 period, 2) TP depth profiles collected at 4 time points during the 2012-2019 period, and 3) sequential chemical P extractions performed on core samples from the filter media layer obtained in 2019. Results indicate that exfiltration to underlying native soil was principally responsible for decreasing the surface water discharge from the bioretention cell (63 % runoff reduction). From 2012 to 2017, the cumulative outflow export loads of TP and SRP only accounted for 1 % and 2 % of the corresponding inflow loads, respectively, hence demonstrating the extremely high P reduction efficiency of this bioretention cell. Accumulation in the filter media layer was the predominant mechanism responsible for the reduction in P outflow loading (57 % retention of TP inflow load) followed by plant uptake (21 % TP retention). Of the P retained within the filter media layer, 48 % occurred in stable, 41 % in potentially mobilizable, and 11 % in easily mobilizable forms. There were no signs that the P retention capacity of the bioretention cell was approaching saturation after 7 years of operation. The reactive transport modeling approach developed here can in principle be transferred and adapted to fit other bioretention cell designs and hydrological regimes to estimate P surface loading reductions at a range of temporal scales, from a single precipitation event to long-term (i.e., multi-year) operation.</abstract>
			<url hash="9c3f7cab">G23-7002</url>
			<pages>162749</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.162749</doi>
			<bibkey>Zhou-2023-Modeling</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="8">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Earth System Science Data, Volume 15, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Lake surface temperature retrieved from Landsat satellite series (1984 to 2021) for the North Slave Region</title>
			<author>
				<first>Gifty</first>
				<last>Attiah</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Homa Kheyrollah</first>
				<last>Pour</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>K. Andrea</first>
				<last>Scott</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. Lake surface temperature (LST) is an important attribute that highlights regional weather and climate variability and trends. The spatial resolution and thermal sensors on Landsat platforms provide the capability of monitoring the temporal and spatial distribution of lake surface temperature on small- to medium-sized lakes. In this study, a retrieval algorithm was applied to the thermal bands of Landsat archives to generate a LST dataset (North Slave LST dataset) for 535 lakes in the North Slave Region (NSR) of the Northwest Territories (NWT), Canada, for the period of 1984 to 2021. North Slave LST was retrieved from Landsat 5 Thematic Mapper (TM), Landsat 7 Enhanced Thematic Mapper Plus (ETM+), and Landsat 8 Operational Land Imager (OLI) and the Thermal Infrared Sensor (TIRS); however, most of the dataset was created from the thermal bands of Landsat 5 (43 %) due to its longevity (1984–2013). Cloud masks were applied to Landsat images to eliminate cloud cover. In addition, a 100 m inward buffer was applied to lakes to prevent pixel mixing with shorelines. To evaluate the algorithm applied, retrieved LST was compared with in situ data and Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) LST observations. A good agreement was observed between in situ observations and North Slave LST, with a mean bias of 0.12 ∘C and a root mean squared deviation (RMSD) of 1.7 ∘C. The North Slave LST dataset contains more available data for warmer months (May to September; 57.3 %) compared to colder months (October to April). The average number of images per year for each lake across the NSR ranged from 20 to 45. The North Slave LST dataset, available at https://doi.org/10.5683/SP3/J4GMC2 (Attiah et al., 2022), will provide communities, scientists, and stakeholders with spatial and temporal changing temperature trends on lakes for the past 38 years.</abstract>
			<url hash="5d553d47">G23-8001</url>
			<pages>1329-1355</pages>
			<doi>10.5194/essd-15-1329-2023</doi>
			<bibkey>Attiah-2023-Lake</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
		<paper id="2">
			<title>Pan-Arctic soil element bioavailability estimations</title>
			<author>
				<first>Peter</first>
				<last>Stimmler</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mathias</first>
				<last>Goeckede</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bo</first>
				<last>Elberling</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Susan M.</first>
				<last>Natali</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Peter</first>
				<last>Kuhry</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nia</first>
				<last>Perron</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fabrice</first>
				<last>Lacroix</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Gustaf</first>
				<last>Hugelius</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Oliver</first>
				<last>Sonnentag</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jens</first>
				<last>Strauss</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>C.</first>
				<last>Minions</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michael</first>
				<last>Sommer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jörg</first>
				<last>Schaller</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. Arctic soils store large amounts of organic carbon and other elements, such as amorphous silicon, silicon, calcium, iron, aluminum, and phosphorous. Global warming is projected to be most pronounced in the Arctic, leading to thawing permafrost which, in turn, changes the soil element availability. To project how biogeochemical cycling in Arctic ecosystems will be affected by climate change, there is a need for data on element availability. Here, we analyzed the amorphous silicon (ASi) content as a solid fraction of the soils as well as Mehlich III extractions for the bioavailability of silicon (Si), calcium (Ca), iron (Fe), phosphorus (P), and aluminum (Al) from 574 soil samples from the circumpolar Arctic region. We show large differences in the ASi fraction and in Si, Ca, Fe, Al, and P availability among different lithologies and Arctic regions. We summarize these data in pan-Arctic maps of the ASi fraction and available Si, Ca, Fe, P, and Al concentrations, focusing on the top 100 cm of Arctic soil. Furthermore, we provide element availability values for the organic and mineral layers of the seasonally thawing active layer as well as for the uppermost permafrost layer. Our spatially explicit data on differences in the availability of elements between the different lithological classes and regions now and in the future will improve Arctic Earth system models for estimating current and future carbon and nutrient feedbacks under climate change (https://doi.org/10.17617/3.8KGQUN, Schaller and Goeckede, 2022).</abstract>
			<url hash="c45c6cfd">G23-8002</url>
			<pages>1059-1075</pages>
			<doi>10.5194/essd-15-1059-2023</doi>
			<bibkey>Stimmler-2023-Pan-Arctic</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="9">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Hydrology: Regional Studies, Volume 47</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Process based calibration of a continental-scale hydrological model using soil moisture and streamflow data</title>
			<author>
				<first>A. R.</first>
				<last>Bajracharya</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mansoor</first>
				<last>Ahmed</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Tricia A.</first>
				<last>Stadnyk</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Masoud</first>
				<last>Asadzadeh</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Nelson Churchill River Basin (NCRB), Canada, and USA. Soil temperature and moisture are essential variables that fluctuate based on soil depth, controlling several sub-surface hydrologic processes. The Hydrological Predictions for the Environment (HYPE) model’s soil profile depth can vary up to four meters, discretized into three soil layers. Here, we further discretized the HYPE subsurface domain to accommodate up to seven soil layers to improve the representation of subsurface thermodynamics and water transfer more accurately. Soil moisture data from different locations across NCRB are collected from 2013 to 2017 for model calibration. We use multi-objective optimization (MOO) to account for streamflow and soil moisture variability and improve the model fidelity at a continental scale. Our study demonstrates that MOO significantly improves soil moisture simulation from the median Kling Gupta Efficiency (KGE) of 0.21–0.66 without deteriorating the streamflow performance. Streamflow and soil moisture simulation performance improvements are statistically insignificant between the original three-layer and seven-layer discretization of HYPE. However, the finer discretization model shows improved simulation in sub-surface components such as the evapotranspiration when verified against reanalysis products, indicating a 12 % underestimation of evapotranspiration from the three-layer HYPE model. The improvement of the discretized HYPE model and simulating the soil temperature at finer vertical resolution makes it a prospective model for permafrost identification and climate change analysis.</abstract>
			<url hash="e5e95a22">G23-9001</url>
			<pages>101391</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.ejrh.2023.101391</doi>
			<bibkey>Bajracharya-2023-Process</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="10">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Methods in Ecology and Evolution, Volume 14, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Empowering ecological modellers with a &lt;scp&gt;PERFICT&lt;/scp&gt; workflow: Seamlessly linking data, parameterisation, prediction, validation and visualisation</title>
			<author>
				<first>Ceres</first>
				<last>Barros</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yong</first>
				<last>Luo</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Alex M</first>
				<last>Chubaty</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ian M. S.</first>
				<last>Eddy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Tatiane</first>
				<last>Micheletti</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Céline</first>
				<last>Boisvenue</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>David</first>
				<last>Andison</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Steven G.</first>
				<last>Cumming</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Eliot J. B.</first>
				<last>McIntire</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Modelling is widely used in ecology and its utility continues to increase as scientists, managers and policy‐makers face pressure to effectively manage ecosystems and meet conservation goals with limited resources. As the urgency to forecast ecosystem responses to global change grows, so do the number and complexity of predictive ecological models and the value of iterative prediction, both of which demand validation and cross‐model comparisons. This challenges ecologists to provide predictive models that are reusable, interoperable, transparent and able to accommodate updates to both data and algorithms. We propose a practical solution to this challenge based on the PERFICT principles (frequent Predictions and Evaluations of Reusable, Freely accessible, Interoperable models, built within Continuous workflows that are routinely Tested), using a modular and integrated framework. We present its general implementation across seven common components of ecological model applications—(i) the modelling toolkit; (ii) data acquisition and treatment; (iii) model parameterisation and calibration; (iv) obtaining predictions; (v) model validation; (vi) analysing and presenting model outputs; and (vii) testing model code—and apply it to two approaches used to predict species distributions: (1) a static statistical model, and (2) a complex spatiotemporally dynamic model. Adopting a continuous workflow enabled us to reuse our models in new study areas, update predictions with new data, and re‐parameterise with different interoperable modules using freely accessible data sources, all with minimal user input. This allowed repeating predictions and automatically evaluating their quality, while centralised inputs, parameters and outputs, facilitated ensemble forecasting and tracking uncertainty. Importantly, the integrated model validation promotes a continuous evaluation of the quality of more‐ or less‐parsimonious models, which is valuable in predictive ecological modelling. By linking all stages of an ecological modelling exercise, it is possible to overcome common challenges faced by ecological modellers, such as changing study areas, choosing between different modelling approaches, and evaluating the appropriateness of the model. This ultimately creates a more equitable and robust playing field for both modellers and end users (e.g. managers), and contributes to position predictive ecology as a central contributor to global change forecasting.</abstract>
			<url hash="7f323d89">G23-10001</url>
			<pages>173-188</pages>
			<doi>10.1111/2041-210x.14034</doi>
			<bibkey>Barros-2023-Empowering</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="11">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Earth's Future, Volume 10, Issue 4</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Geophysical Union (AGU)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Fire and Ice: The Impact of Wildfire‐Affected Albedo and Irradiance on Glacier Melt</title>
			<author>
				<first>Caroline</first>
				<last>Aubry-Wake</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>André</first>
				<last>Bertoncini</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Wildfire occurrence and severity is predicted to increase in the upcoming decades with severe negative impacts on human societies. The impacts of upwind wildfire activity on glacier melt, a critical source of freshwater for downstream environments, were investigated through analysis of field and remote sensing observations and modeling experiments for the 2015–2020 melt seasons at the well-instrumented Athabasca Glacier in the Canadian Rockies. Upwind wildfire activity influenced surface glacier melt through both a decrease in the surface albedo from deposition of soot on the glacier and through the impact of smoke on atmospheric conditions above the glacier. Athabasca Glacier on-ice weather station observations show days with dense smoke were warmer than clear, non-smoky days, and sustained a reduction in surface shortwave irradiance of 103 W m−2 during peak shortwave irradiance and an increase in longwave irradiance of 10 W m−2, producing an average 15 W m−2 decrease in net radiation. Albedo observed on-ice gradually decreased after the wildfires started, from a summer average of 0.29 in 2015 before the wildfires to as low as 0.16 in 2018 after extensive wildfires and remained low for two more melt seasons without substantial upwind wildfires. Reduced all-wave irradiance partly compensated for the increase in melt due to lowered albedo in those seasons when smoke was detected above Athabasca Glacier. In melt seasons without smoke, the suppressed albedo increased melt by slightly more than 10% compared to the simulations without fire-impacted albedo, increasing melt by 0.42 m. w.e. in 2019 and 0.37 m. w.e. in 2020.</abstract>
			<url hash="c78e5aec">G23-11001</url>
			<doi>10.1029/2022ef002685</doi>
			<bibkey>Aubry‐Wake-2023-Fire</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="12">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrological Processes, Volume 36, Issue 10</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Hydrological process controls on streamflow variability in a glacierized headwater basin</title>
			<author>
				<first>Caroline</first>
				<last>Aubry-Wake</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Dhiraj</first>
				<last>Pradhananga</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Mountain glacierized headwaters are currently witnessing a transient shift in their hydrological and glaciological systems in response to rapid climate change. To characterize these changes, a robust understanding of the hydrological processes operating in the basin and their interactions is needed. Such an investigation was undertaken in the Peyto Glacier Research Basin, Canadian Rockies over 32 years (1988–2020). A distributed, physically based, uncalibrated glacier hydrology model was developed using the modular, object-oriented Cold Region Hydrological Modelling Platform to simulate both on and off-glacier high mountain processes and streamflow generation. The hydrological processes that generate streamflow from this alpine basin are characterized by substantial inter-annual variability over the 32 years. Snowmelt runoff always provided the largest fraction of annual streamflow (44% to 89%), with smaller fractional contributions occurring in higher streamflow years. Ice melt runoff provided 10% to 45% of annual streamflow volume, with higher fractions associated with higher flow years. Both rainfall and firn melt runoff contributed less than 13% of annual streamflow. Years with high streamflow were on average 1.43°C warmer than low streamflow years, and higher streamflow years had lower seasonal snow accumulation, earlier snowmelt and higher summer rainfall than years with lower streamflow. Greater ice exposure in warmer, low snowfall (high rainfall) years led to greater streamflow generation. The understanding gained here provides insight into how future climate and increased meteorological variability may impact glacier meltwater contributions to streamflow and downstream water availability as alpine glaciers continue to retreat.</abstract>
			<url hash="d53bf502">G23-12001</url>
			<doi>10.1002/hyp.14731</doi>
			<bibkey>Aubry‐Wake-2023-Hydrological</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="13">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Ecosystems</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Post-fire Recovery of Soil Organic Layer Carbon in Canadian Boreal Forests</title>
			<author>
				<first>Kristen</first>
				<last>Bill</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Catherine M.</first>
				<last>Dieleman</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jennifer L.</first>
				<last>Baltzer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Geneviève É.</first>
				<last>Degré-Timmons</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michelle C.</first>
				<last>Mack</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nicola J.</first>
				<last>Day</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Steven G.</first>
				<last>Cumming</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Xanthe J.</first>
				<last>Walker</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>M. R.</first>
				<last>Turetsky</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="6d879267">G23-13001</url>
			<doi>10.1007/s10021-023-00854-0</doi>
			<bibkey>Bill-2023-Post-fire</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="14">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrological Processes, Volume 37, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Below canopy evapotranspiration in four different variable retention harvesting treatments in a red pine plantation forest</title>
			<author>
				<first>Alanna V.</first>
				<last>Bodo</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>William C.</first>
				<last>Parker</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ken A.</first>
				<last>Elliott</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>M. Altaf</first>
				<last>Arain</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Variable retention harvest (VRH) is a silvicultural approach that retains differing proportions and patterns of canopy trees across a harvested area to emulate natural disturbance effects on stand structure and enhance the resilience of the regenerating stand to abiotic and biotic stresses. Four VRH treatments were applied to an 83-year-old red pine (Pinus resinosa Ait.) plantation forest in the Mixedwood Plains Ecozone of Canada that included 55% aggregate retention (55A), 55% dispersed retention (55D), 33% aggregate retention (33A), 33% dispersed retention (33D) and an unharvested control (CN). In the sixth growing season after harvest, tree stem sap flow and eddy covariance flux measurements were used to examine the impacts of VRH on the dominant components of total stand evapotranspiration (ET), i.e., canopy transpiration (TC) and water flux from the understory vegetation and soil (ETU) as well as understory and canopy water use efficiency (WUE). A positive relationship was found between harvest intensity and the growth of understory vegetation and ETU. The contribution of ETU to ET was higher in the dispersed compared to the aggregate VRH treatments. Canopy transpiration contributed 83% of ET in the CN plot and 58%, 55%, 30% and 23% in the 55D, 55A, 33A and 33D treatments, respectively. Overall, VRH treatments resulted in increased canopy WUE but little comparative effect on understory WUE. Our results suggest that the dispersed retention pattern led to higher ET and productivity than the aggregate pattern of the same retention level. Where carbon sequestration and climate change mitigation is the primary management objective, higher retention levels such as 55D might be used to favour stand level carbon storage while accepting slower rates of understory development. Our findings on the effects of VRH on productivity and WUE of the canopy and understory will help forest managers to better employ VRH as an option to meet multiple objectives and adapt forests to a warmer, more variable climate.</abstract>
			<url hash="f050aade">G23-14001</url>
			<doi>10.1002/hyp.14789</doi>
			<bibkey>Bodo-2023-Below</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="15">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Science of The Total Environment, Volume 895</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>A comparative analysis of the partitioning behaviour of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in liquid and solid fractions of wastewater</title>
			<author>
				<first>Patrick</first>
				<last>Breadner</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hadi A.</first>
				<last>Dhiyebi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Azar</first>
				<last>Fattahi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nivetha</first>
				<last>Srikanthan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Samina</first>
				<last>Hayat</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Marc G.</first>
				<last>Aucoin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Scott Joseph</first>
				<last>Boegel</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Leslie M.</first>
				<last>Bragg</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Paul M.</first>
				<last>Craig</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yuwei</first>
				<last>Xie</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mark R.</first>
				<last>Servos</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>As fragments of SARS-CoV-2 RNA can be quantified and measured temporally in wastewater, surveillance of concentrations of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater has become a vital resource for tracking the spread of COVID-19 in and among communities. However, the absence of standardized methods has affected the interpretation of data for public health efforts. In particular, analyzing either the liquid or solid fraction has implications for the interpretation of how viral RNA is quantified. Characterizing how SARS-CoV-2 or its RNA fragments partition in wastewater is a central part of understanding fate and behaviour in wastewater. In this study, partitioning of SARS-CoV-2 was investigated by use of centrifugation with varied durations of spin and centrifugal force, polyethylene glycol (PEG) precipitation followed by centrifugation, and ultrafiltration of wastewater. Partitioning of the endogenous pepper mild mottled virus (PMMoV), used to normalize the SARS-CoV-2 signal for fecal load in trend analysis, was also examined. Additionally, two surrogates for coronavirus, human coronavirus 229E and murine hepatitis virus, were analyzed as process controls. Even though SARS-CoV-2 has an affinity for solids, the total RNA copies of SARS-CoV-2 per wastewater sample, after centrifugation (12,000 g, 1.5 h, no brake), were partitioned evenly between the liquid and solid fractions. Centrifugation at greater speeds for longer durations resulted in a shift in partitioning for all viruses toward the solid fraction except for PMMoV, which remained mostly in the liquid fraction. The surrogates more closely reflected the partitioning of SARS-CoV-2 under high centrifugation speed and duration while PMMoV did not. Interestingly, ultrafiltration devices were inconsistent in estimating RNA copies in wastewater, which can influence the interpretation of partitioning. Developing a better understanding of the fate of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater and creating a foundation of best practices is the key to supporting the current pandemic response and preparing for future potential infectious diseases.</abstract>
			<url hash="48eccdbb">G23-15001</url>
			<pages>165095</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.165095</doi>
			<bibkey>Breadner-2023-A</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="16">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Agricultural Water Management, Volume 284</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Performance of simple low-cost edge-of-field filters for mitigating P losses in surface runoff from agricultural fields</title>
			<author>
				<first>R.</first>
				<last>Carlow</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Janina M.</first>
				<last>Plach</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>William T.</first>
				<last>Pluer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>W. Vito</first>
				<last>Lam</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mazda</first>
				<last>Kompani-Zare</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>R.</first>
				<last>Brunke</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kevin</first>
				<last>McKague</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Helen P.</first>
				<last>Jarvie</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Merrin L.</first>
				<last>Macrae</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Nutrient losses from agricultural fields are the largest sources of phosphorus (P) entering the Great Lakes in North America. Stacked conservation practices (CPs) may reduce P losses from individual fields. Simple low-cost, low disturbance, commercially available filters containing wood chips and phosphorus sorbing materials (PSM) were installed on two fields already using conservation practices in midwestern Ontario (ILD and LON) to quantify their ability to remove soluble reactive P (SRP), particulate P (PP), total P (TP) and total suspended sediments (TSS) from surface runoff. Laboratory tests on unused (new) and used (field) filter materials were also conducted to estimate P sorption and remobilization potentials. During the two-year study period, the filter retained 0.018 kg ha-1 of SRP, 0.38 kg ha-1 of PP, 0.4 kg ha-1 of TP and 8.75 kg ha-1 of TSS from surface runoff at the ILD site. In contrast, although the filter at LON removed 37 kg ha-1 of TSS and 0.07 kg ha-1 of PP, it released 0.22 kg ha-1 of SRP and 0.15 kg ha-1 TP. A reduction in filter efficacy was observed over time, particularly at the site with greater cumulative surface runoff and larger runoff events (LON). The majority of the SRP retained by the filter was held in a loosely bound form, thus, susceptible to P remobilization. The results of this study demonstrate that low-cost, simple PSMs have some potential to retain P from surface runoff, but their efficacy may decline over time and their P retention capability may differ with site hydrology (e.g., runoff volumes and velocity) and P supply.</abstract>
			<url hash="5a596255">G23-16001</url>
			<pages>108362</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.agwat.2023.108362</doi>
			<bibkey>Carlow-2023-Performance</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="17">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Cold Regions Science and Technology, Volume 209</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Future change in amplitude and timing of high-flow events in a Canadian subarctic watershed</title>
			<author>
				<first>Olivier</first>
				<last>Champagne</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>M. Altaf</first>
				<last>Arain</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Shusen</first>
				<last>Wang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Martin</first>
				<last>Leduc</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The Hudson Bay basin is a large contributor of freshwater input in the Arctic Ocean and is also an area affected by destructive spring floods. In this study, the hydrological model MESH (Modelisation Environmentale Communautaire - Surface and hydrology) was set up for the Groundhog River watershed situated in the Hudson Bay basin, to simulate the future evolution of streamflow and annual maximum streamflow. MESH was forced by meteorological data from ERA5 reanalyses in the historical period (1979–2018) and 12 models of the Coupled model intercomparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5) downscaled with the Canadian Regional Climate model version 5 (CRCM5) in historical (1979–2005) and scenario period (2006–2098). The projections consistently indicate an earlier spring flow and a reduction in the amount of annual maximum streamflow by the end of the 21st century. Under the RCP8.5 scenario, the annual maximum streamflow occurring in the spring is expected to be advanced by 2 weeks and reduced on average from 852 m3/s (±265) in the historical period (1979–2018) to 717m3/s (±250) by the end of the 21st century (2059–2098). Because the seasonal projection of streamflow was not investigated in previous studies, this work is an important first step to assess the seasonal change of streamflow in the Hudson Bay region under climate change.</abstract>
			<url hash="e2e50530">G23-17001</url>
			<pages>103807</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.coldregions.2023.103807</doi>
			<bibkey>Champagne-2023-Future</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="18">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Canadian Journal of Remote Sensing, Volume 49, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Comparative Analysis of Empirical and Machine Learning Models for Chl&lt;i&gt;a&lt;/i&gt; Extraction Using Sentinel-2 and Landsat OLI Data: Opportunities, Limitations, and Challenges</title>
			<author>
				<first>Amir M.</first>
				<last>Chegoonian</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nima</first>
				<last>Pahlevan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kiana</first>
				<last>Zolfaghari</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Peter R.</first>
				<last>Leavitt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John-Mark</first>
				<last>Davies</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Helen M.</first>
				<last>Baulch</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Claude R.</first>
				<last>Duguay</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Remote retrieval of near-surface chlorophyll-a (Chla) concentration in small inland waters is challenging due to substantial optical interferences of various water constituents and uncertainties in the atmospheric correction (AC) process. Although various algorithms have been developed to estimate Chla from moderate-resolution terrestrial missions (∼10–60 m), the production of both accurate distribution maps and time series of Chla has proven challenging, limiting the use of remote analyses for lake monitoring. Here, we develop a support vector regression (SVR) model, which uses satellite-derived remote-sensing reflectance spectra (Rrsδ) from Sentinel-2 and Landsat-8 images as input for Chla retrieval in a representative eutrophic prairie lake, Buffalo Pound Lake (BPL), Saskatchewan, Canada. Validated against in situ Chla from seven ice-free seasons (N ∼ 200; 2014–2020), the SVR model outperformed both locally tuned, Rrsδ-fed empirical models (Normalized Difference Chlorophyll Index, 2- and 3-band, and OC3) and Mixture Density Networks (MDNs) by 15–65%, while exhibiting comparable performance to a locally trained MDN, with an error of ∼35%. Comparison of Chla retrieval models, AC processors (iCOR, ACOLITE), and radiometric products (Rayleigh-corrected, surface, and top-of-atmosphere reflectance) showed that the best Chla maps and optimal time series (up to 100 mg m−3) were produced using a coupled SVR-iCOR system.</abstract>
			<url hash="ba861566">G23-18001</url>
			<doi>10.1080/07038992.2023.2215333</doi>
			<bibkey>Chegoonian-2023-Comparative</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="19">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Research Letters, Volume 17, Issue 11</booktitle>
			<publisher>IOP Publishing</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Evaluating photosynthetic activity across Arctic-Boreal land cover types using solar-induced fluorescence</title>
			<author>
				<first>Rui</first>
				<last>Cheng</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Troy S.</first>
				<last>Magney</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Erica L</first>
				<last>Orcutt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zoe</first>
				<last>Pierrat</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philipp</first>
				<last>Köhler</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>David R.</first>
				<last>Bowling</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>M. Syndonia</first>
				<last>Bret-Harte</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Eugénie S.</first>
				<last>Euskirchen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Martin</first>
				<last>Jung</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hideki</first>
				<last>Kobayashi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>A. V.</first>
				<last>Rocha</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Oliver</first>
				<last>Sonnentag</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>J.</first>
				<last>Stutz</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sophia</first>
				<last>Walther</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Donatella</first>
				<last>Zona</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Christian</first>
				<last>Frankenberg</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Photosynthesis of terrestrial ecosystems in the Arctic-Boreal region is a critical part of the global carbon cycle. Solar-induced chlorophyll Fluorescence (SIF), a promising proxy for photosynthesis with physiological insight, has been used to track gross primary production (GPP) at regional scales. Recent studies have constructed empirical relationships between SIF and eddy covariance-derived GPP as a first step to predicting global GPP. However, high latitudes pose two specific challenges: (a) Unique plant species and land cover types in the Arctic–Boreal region are not included in the generalized SIF-GPP relationship from lower latitudes, and (b) the complex terrain and sub-pixel land cover further complicate the interpretation of the SIF-GPP relationship. In this study, we focused on the Arctic-Boreal vulnerability experiment (ABoVE) domain and evaluated the empirical relationships between SIF for high latitudes from the TROPOspheric Monitoring Instrument (TROPOMI) and a state-of-the-art machine learning GPP product (FluxCom). For the first time, we report the regression slope, linear correlation coefficient, and the goodness of the fit of SIF-GPP relationships for Arctic-Boreal land cover types with extensive spatial coverage. We found several potential issues specific to the Arctic-Boreal region that should be considered: (a) unrealistically high FluxCom GPP due to the presence of snow and water at the subpixel scale; (b) changing biomass distribution and SIF-GPP relationship along elevational gradients, and (c) limited perspective and misrepresentation of heterogeneous land cover across spatial resolutions. Taken together, our results will help improve the estimation of GPP using SIF in terrestrial biosphere models and cope with model-data uncertainties in the Arctic-Boreal region.</abstract>
			<url hash="023a7203">G23-19001</url>
			<pages>115009</pages>
			<doi>10.1088/1748-9326/ac9dae</doi>
			<bibkey>Cheng-2023-Evaluating</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="20">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Proceedings of the 46th International ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval</booktitle>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>MMEAD: MS MARCO Entity Annotations and Disambiguations</title>
			<author>
				<first>Chris</first>
				<last>Kamphuis</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Aileen</first>
				<last>Lin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>S. A.</first>
				<last>Yang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jimmy</first>
				<last>Lin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Arjen P. de</first>
				<last>Vries</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Faegheh</first>
				<last>Hasibi</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>MMEAD, or MS MARCO Entity Annotations and Disambiguations, is a resource for entity links for the MS MARCO datasets. We specify a format to store and share links for both document and passage collections of MS MARCO. Following this specification, we release entity links to Wikipedia for documents and passages in both MS MARCO collections (v1 and v2). Entity links have been produced by the REL and BLINK systems. MMEAD is an easy-to-install Python package, allowing users to load the link data and entity embeddings effortlessly. Using MMEAD takes only a few lines of code. Finally, we show how MMEAD can be used for IR research that uses entity information. We show how to improve recall@1000 and MRR@10 on more complex queries on the MS MARCO v1 passage dataset by using this resource. We also demonstrate how entity expansions can be used for interactive search applications.</abstract>
			<url hash="38924759">G23-20001</url>
			<doi>10.1145/3539618.3591887</doi>
			<bibkey>Kamphuis-2023-MMEAD:</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="21">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Reviews, Volume 31, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>Canadian Science Publishing</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Impact of climate change on catchment nutrient dynamics: insights from around the world</title>
			<author>
				<first>Diogo</first>
				<last>Costa</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Caleb</first>
				<last>Sutter</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Anita</first>
				<last>Shepherd</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Helen P.</first>
				<last>Jarvie</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Henry F.</first>
				<last>Wilson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>J. M.</first>
				<last>Elliott</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jian</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Merrin L.</first>
				<last>Macrae</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>This study is a meta-analysis of global articles on hydrological nutrient dynamics to determine trends and consensus on: (1) the effects of climate change-induced hydrological and temperature drivers on nutrient dynamics and how these effects vary along the catchment continuum from land to river to lake; (2) the convergence of climate change impacts with other anthropogenic pressures (agriculture, urbanization) in nutrient dynamics; and (3) regional variability in the effects of climate change on nutrient dynamics and water-quality impairment across different climate zones. An innovative web crawler tool was employed to help critically synthesize the information in the literature. The literature suggests that climate change will impact nutrient dynamics around the globe and exacerbate contemporary water-quality challenges. Nutrient leaching and overland flow transport are projected to increase globally, promoted by extreme precipitation. Seasonal variations in streamflow are expected to emulate changing precipitation patterns, but the specific local impacts of climate change on hydrology and nutrient dynamics will vary both seasonally and regionally. Plant activity may reduce some of this load in nonagricultural soils if the expected increase in plant uptake of nutrients prompted by increased temperatures can compensate for greater nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P) mineralization, N deposition, and leaching rates. High-temperature forest and grass fires may help reduce mineralization and microbial turnover by altering N speciation via the pyrolysis of organic matter. In agricultural areas that are at higher risk of erosion, extreme precipitation will exacerbate existing water-quality issues, and greater plant nutrient uptake may lead to an increase in fertilizer use. Future urban expansion will amplify these effects. Higher ambient temperatures will promote harmful cyanobacterial blooms by enhancing thermal stratification, increasing nutrient load into streams and lakes from extreme precipitation events, decreasing summer flow and thus baseflow dilution capacity, and increasing water and nutrient residence times during increasingly frequent droughts. Land management decisions must consider the nuanced regional and seasonal changes identified in this review (realized and predicted). Such knowledge is critical to increasing international cooperation and accelerating action toward the United Nations’s global sustainability goals and the specific objectives of the Conference of Parties (COP) 26.</abstract>
			<url hash="802e203c">G23-21001</url>
			<pages>4-25</pages>
			<doi>10.1139/er-2021-0109</doi>
			<bibkey>Costa-2023-Impact</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="22">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology Part B: Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Volume 269</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Investigating wastewater treatment plant effluent and pharmaceutical exposure on innate cytokine expression of darters (Etheostoma spp.) in the Grand River watershed</title>
			<author>
				<first>Rachel E.</first>
				<last>Dawe</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Leslie M.</first>
				<last>Bragg</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hadi A.</first>
				<last>Dhiyebi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mark R.</first>
				<last>Servos</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Paul M.</first>
				<last>Craig</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Fish live in continuous contact with various stressors and antigenic material present within their environments. The impact of stressors associated with wastewater-exposed environments on fish has become of particular interest in toxicology studies. The objectives of this study were to examine potential effects of wastewater treatment plant (WWTP) effluent-associated stressors on innate cytokine expression within the gills of darter species (Etheostoma spp.), using both field and laboratory approaches. Male and female darters (rainbow, greenside, fantail, and johnny darters) were collected upstream and downstream of the Waterloo WWTP in the Grand River, Ontario. Gill samples were collected from fish in the field and from a second subset of fish brought back to the laboratory. Laboratory fish were acutely exposed (96-h) to an environmentally relevant concentration of venlafaxine (1.0 μg/L), a commonly prescribed antidepressant. To assess the impacts of these stressors on the innate immunity of darters, the expression of key innate cytokines was examined. Minor significant effects on innate cytokine expression were observed between upstream and downstream fish. Moderate effects on cytokine expression were observed in venlafaxine-exposed fish compared to their control counterparts however, changes were not indicative of a biologically significant immune response occurring due to the exposure. Although the results of this study did not display extensive impacts of effluent and pharmaceutical exposure on innate cytokine expression within the gills, they provide a novel avenue of study, illustrating the importance of examining potential impacts that effluent-associated stressors can have on fundamental immune responses of native fish species.</abstract>
			<url hash="929b8fd2">G23-22001</url>
			<pages>110875</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.cbpb.2023.110875</doi>
			<bibkey>Dawe-2023-Investigating</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="23">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Frontiers in Public Health, Volume 11</booktitle>
			<publisher>Frontiers Media SA</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Assessment of seasonality and normalization techniques for wastewater-based surveillance in Ontario, Canada</title>
			<author>
				<first>Hadi A.</first>
				<last>Dhiyebi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jad</first>
				<last>Farah</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Heather</first>
				<last>Ikert</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nivetha</first>
				<last>Srikanthan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Samina</first>
				<last>Hayat</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Leslie M.</first>
				<last>Bragg</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Asim</first>
				<last>Qasim</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mark</first>
				<last>Payne</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Linda</first>
				<last>Kaleis</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Caitlyn</first>
				<last>Paget</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Dominika</first>
				<last>Celmer-Repin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Arianne M.</first>
				<last>Folkema</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sarah</first>
				<last>Drew</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Robert</first>
				<last>Delatolla</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mark R.</first>
				<last>Servos</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Introduction Wastewater-based surveillance is at the forefront of monitoring for community prevalence of COVID-19, however, continued uncertainty exists regarding the use of fecal indicators for normalization of the SARS-CoV-2 virus in wastewater. Using three communities in Ontario, sampled from 2021–2023, the seasonality of a viral fecal indicator (pepper mild mottle virus, PMMoV) and the utility of normalization of data to improve correlations with clinical cases was examined. Methods Wastewater samples from Warden, the Humber Air Management Facility (AMF), and Kitchener were analyzed for SARS-CoV-2, PMMoV, and crAssphage. The seasonality of PMMoV and flow rates were examined and compared by Season-Trend-Loess decomposition analysis. The effects of normalization using PMMoV, crAssphage, and flow rates were analyzed by comparing the correlations to clinical cases by episode date (CBED) during 2021. Results Seasonal analysis demonstrated that PMMoV had similar trends at Humber AMF and Kitchener with peaks in January and April 2022 and low concentrations (troughs) in the summer months. Warden had similar trends but was more sporadic between the peaks and troughs for PMMoV concentrations. Flow demonstrated similar trends but was not correlated to PMMoV concentrations at Humber AMF and was very weak at Kitchener ( r = 0.12). Despite the differences among the sewersheds, unnormalized SARS-CoV-2 (raw N1–N2) concentration in wastewater ( n = 99–191) was strongly correlated to the CBED in the communities ( r = 0.620–0.854) during 2021. Additionally, normalization with PMMoV did not improve the correlations at Warden and significantly reduced the correlations at Humber AMF and Kitchener. Flow normalization ( n = 99–191) at Humber AMF and Kitchener and crAssphage normalization ( n = 29–57) correlations at all three sites were not significantly different from raw N1–N2 correlations with CBED. Discussion Differences in seasonal trends in viral biomarkers caused by differences in sewershed characteristics (flow, input, etc.) may play a role in determining how effective normalization may be for improving correlations (or not). This study highlights the importance of assessing the influence of viral fecal indicators on normalized SARS-CoV-2 or other viruses of concern. Fecal indicators used to normalize the target of interest may help or hinder establishing trends with clinical outcomes of interest in wastewater-based surveillance and needs to be considered carefully across seasons and sites.</abstract>
			<url hash="2a27e8b7">G23-23001</url>
			<doi>10.3389/fpubh.2023.1186525</doi>
			<bibkey>Dhiyebi-2023-Assessment</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="24">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Emerging Infectious Diseases, Volume 29, Issue 8</booktitle>
			<publisher>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Omicron COVID-19 Case Estimates Based on Previous SARS-CoV-2 Wastewater Load, Regional Municipality of Peel, Ontario, Canada</title>
			<author>
				<first>Lydia</first>
				<last>Cheng</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hadi A.</first>
				<last>Dhiyebi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Monali</first>
				<last>Varia</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kyle</first>
				<last>Atanas</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nivetha</first>
				<last>Srikanthan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Samina</first>
				<last>Hayat</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Heather</first>
				<last>Ikert</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Meghan</first>
				<last>Fuzzen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Carly</first>
				<last>Sing-Judge</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yash</first>
				<last>Badlani</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Eli</first>
				<last>Zeeb</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Leslie M.</first>
				<last>Bragg</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Robert</first>
				<last>Delatolla</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Elaine</first>
				<last>Gilliland</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mark R.</first>
				<last>Servos</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>We determined correlations between SARS-CoV-2 load in untreated water and COVID-19 cases and patient hospitalizations before the Omicron variant (September 2020-November 2021) at 2 wastewater treatment plants in the Regional Municipality of Peel, Ontario, Canada. Using pre-Omicron correlations, we estimated incident COVID-19 cases during Omicron outbreaks (November 2021-June 2022). The strongest correlation between wastewater SARS-CoV-2 load and COVID-19 cases occurred 1 day after sampling (r = 0.911). The strongest correlation between wastewater load and COVID-19 patient hospitalizations occurred 4 days after sampling (r = 0.819). At the peak of the Omicron BA.2 outbreak in April 2022, reported COVID-19 cases were underestimated 19-fold because of changes in clinical testing. Wastewater data provided information for local decision-making and are a useful component of COVID-19 surveillance systems.</abstract>
			<url hash="b7f0d00e">G23-24001</url>
			<doi>10.3201/eid2908.221580</doi>
			<bibkey>Cheng-2023-Omicron</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="25">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Water Economics and Policy, Volume 09, Issue 01</booktitle>
			<publisher>World Scientific Pub Co Pte Ltd</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Testing the Predictive Power of Hydro-Economic Supply-Side Input–Output Models Under Different Water Availability and Economic Conditions Over Time in a Transboundary River Basin</title>
			<author>
				<first>Leila</first>
				<last>Eamen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Roy</first>
				<last>Brouwer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Saman</first>
				<last>Razavi</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Although the temporal transferability of input–output (IO) models has been examined before, no study has investigated the impacts of changing water availability conditions over time, e.g., due to climate change, on the predictive power of water-inclusive IO models. To address this gap, we investigate the performance of inter-regional supply-side input–output (ISIO) models that incorporate precipitation and water intake under varying climates over time in a transboundary water management context. Using the Saskatchewan River Basin in Western Canada as a case study, we develop four ISIO models based on available economic and hydrological data from years with different climatic conditions, i.e., two dry and two wet years. Accounting for price changes over these years, our findings indicate that the joint impact of changes in water availability and economic structural changes on economic output can be considerable. The results furthermore show that each model performs particularly well in predicting the economic output for similar climatic years. The models remain reliable in predicting economic outputs over several years as long as changes in water availability are within the range observed in the water-inclusive base year ISIO model.</abstract>
			<url hash="0f4cb76b">G23-25001</url>
			<doi>10.1142/s2382624x23400040</doi>
			<bibkey>Eamen-2023-Testing</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="26">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Chemosphere, Volume 334</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Wastewater discharges alter microbial community composition in surface waters of the canadian prairies</title>
			<author>
				<first>Milena</first>
				<last>Esser</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Cameron</first>
				<last>Hoggarth</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Helen M.</first>
				<last>Baulch</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jonathan K.</first>
				<last>Challis</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yuwei</first>
				<last>Xie</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Markus</first>
				<last>Hecker</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Markus</first>
				<last>Brinkmann</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Microbial communities are an important component of freshwater biodiversity that is threatened by anthropogenic impacts. Wastewater discharges pose a particular concern by being major sources of anthropogenic contaminants and microorganisms that may influence the composition of natural microbial communities. Nevertheless, the effects of wastewater treatment plant (WWTP) effluents on microbial communities remain largely unexplored. In this study, the effects of wastewater discharges on microbial communities from five different WWTPs in Southern Saskatchewan were investigated using rRNA gene metabarcoding. In parallel, nutrient levels and the presence of environmentally relevant organic pollutants were analyzed. Higher nutrient loads and pollutant concentrations resulted in significant changes in microbial community composition. The greatest changes were observed in Wascana Creek (Regina), which was found to be heavily polluted by wastewater discharges. Several taxa occurred in greater relative abundance in the wastewater-influenced stream segments, indicating anthropogenic pollution and eutrophication, especially taxa belonging to Proteobacteria, Bacteroidota, and Chlorophyta. Strong decreases were measured within the taxa Ciliphora, Diatomea, Dinoflagellata, Nematozoa, Ochrophyta, Protalveolata, and Rotifera. Across all sample types, a significant decline in sulfur bacteria was measured, implying changes in functional biodiversity. In addition, downstream of the Regina WWTP, an increase in cyanotoxins was detected which was correlated with a significant change in cyanobacterial community composition. Overall, these data suggest a causal relationship between anthropogenic pollution and changes in microbial communities, possibly reflecting an impairment of ecosystem health.</abstract>
			<url hash="1df91885">G23-26001</url>
			<pages>138991</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.138991</doi>
			<bibkey>Esser-2023-Wastewater</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="27">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Science of The Total Environment, Volume 881</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>An improved method for determining frequency of multiple variants of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater using qPCR assays</title>
			<author>
				<first>Meghan</first>
				<last>Fuzzen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nathanael B.J.</first>
				<last>Harper</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hadi A.</first>
				<last>Dhiyebi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nivetha</first>
				<last>Srikanthan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Samina</first>
				<last>Hayat</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Leslie M.</first>
				<last>Bragg</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Shelley</first>
				<last>Peterson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ivy</first>
				<last>Yang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jianxian</first>
				<last>Sun</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Elizabeth</first>
				<last>Edwards</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Chand S.</first>
				<last>Mangat</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Tyson E.</first>
				<last>Graber</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Robert</first>
				<last>Delatolla</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mark R.</first>
				<last>Servos</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Wastewater-based surveillance has become an effective tool around the globe for indirect monitoring of COVID-19 in communities. Variants of Concern (VOCs) have been detected in wastewater by use of reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) or whole genome sequencing (WGS). Rapid, reliable RT-PCR assays continue to be needed to determine the relative frequencies of VOCs and sub-lineages in wastewater-based surveillance programs. The presence of multiple mutations in a single region of the N-gene allowed for the design of a single amplicon, multiple probe assay, that can distinguish among several VOCs in wastewater RNA extracts. This approach which multiplexes probes designed to target mutations associated with specific VOC's along with an intra-amplicon universal probe (non-mutated region) was validated in singleplex and multiplex. The prevalence of each mutation (i.e. VOC) is estimated by comparing the abundance of the targeted mutation with a non-mutated and highly conserved region within the same amplicon. This is advantageous for the accurate and rapid estimation of variant frequencies in wastewater. The N200 assay was applied to monitor frequencies of VOCs in wastewater extracts from several communities in Ontario, Canada in near real time from November 28, 2021 to January 4, 2022. This includes the period of the rapid replacement of the Delta variant with the introduction of the Omicron variant in these Ontario communities in early December 2021. The frequency estimates using this assay were highly reflective of clinical WGS estimates for the same communities. This style of qPCR assay, which simultaneously measures signal from a non-mutated comparator probe and multiple mutation-specific probes contained within a single qPCR amplicon, can be applied to future assay development for rapid and accurate estimations of variant frequencies.</abstract>
			<url hash="a5457fe0">G23-27001</url>
			<pages>163292</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.163292</doi>
			<bibkey>Fuzzen-2023-An</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="28">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrology and Earth System Sciences, Volume 27, Issue 5</booktitle>
			<publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Cooperation in a transboundary river basin: a large-scale  socio-hydrological model of the Eastern Nile</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mohammad</first>
				<last>Ghoreishi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Amin</first>
				<last>Elshorbagy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Saman</first>
				<last>Razavi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Günter</first>
				<last>Blöschl</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Murugesu</first>
				<last>Sivapalan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ahmed</first>
				<last>Abdelkader</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. While conflict-and-cooperation phenomena in transboundary basins have been widely studied, much less work has been devoted to representing the process interactions in a quantitative way. This paper identifies the main factors in the riparian countries' willingness to cooperate in the Eastern Nile River basin, involving Ethiopia, Sudan, and Egypt, from 1983 to 2016. We propose a quantitative model of the willingness to cooperate at the national and river basin scales. Our results suggest that relative political stability and foreign direct investment can explain Ethiopia's decreasing willingness to cooperate between 2009 and 2016. Further, we show that the 2008 food crisis may account for Sudan recovering its willingness to cooperate with Ethiopia. Long-term lack of trust among the riparian countries may have reduced basin-wide cooperation. While the proposed model has some limitations regarding model assumptions and parameters, it does provide a quantitative representation of the evolution of cooperation pathways among the riparian countries, which can be used to explore the effects of changes in future dam operation and other management decisions on the emergence of conflict and cooperation in the basin.</abstract>
			<url hash="fd266fb6">G23-28001</url>
			<pages>1201-1219</pages>
			<doi>10.5194/hess-27-1201-2023</doi>
			<bibkey>Ghoreishi-2023-Cooperation</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="29">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Ecohydrology, Volume 16, Issue 4</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Applying a two‐dimensional hydrodynamic model to estimate fish stranding risk downstream from a hydropeaking hydroelectric station</title>
			<author>
				<first>Sarah E.</first>
				<last>Glowa</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Andrea J.</first>
				<last>Kneale</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Douglas A.</first>
				<last>Watkinson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Haitham</first>
				<last>Ghamry</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Eva C.</first>
				<last>Enders</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Timothy D.</first>
				<last>Jardine</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Fish stranding is of global concern with increasing hydropower operations using hydropeaking to respond to fluctuating energy demand. Determining the effects hydropeaking has on fish communities is challenging because fish stranding is dependent on riverscape features, such as topography, bathymetry and substrate. By using a combination of physical habitat assessments, hydrodynamic modelling and empirical data on fish stranding, we estimated the number of fish stranding over a 5‐month period for three model years in a large Prairie river. More specifically, we modelled how many fish potentially stranded during the years 2019, 2020 and 2021 across a 16 km study reached downstream from E.B. Campbell Hydroelectric Station on the Saskatchewan River, Canada. Fish stranding densities calculated from data collected through remote photography and transect monitoring in 2021 were applied to the daily area subject to drying determined by the River2D hydrodynamic model. The cumulative area subject to change was 90.05, 53.02 and 80.74 km 2 for years 2019, 2020 and 2021, respectively, from June to October. The highest number of stranded fish was estimated for the year 2021, where estimates ranged from 89,800 to 1,638,000 individuals based on remote photography and transect monitoring fish stranding densities, respectively, 157 to 2,856 fish stranded per hectare. Our approach of estimating fish stranding on a large scale allows for a greater understanding of the impact hydropeaking has on fish communities and can be applied to other riverscapes threatened by hydropeaking.</abstract>
			<url hash="459a08d3">G23-29001</url>
			<doi>10.1002/eco.2530</doi>
			<bibkey>Glowa-2023-Applying</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="30">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>River Research and Applications, Volume 39, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Evaluating the risk of fish stranding due to hydropeaking in a large continental river</title>
			<author>
				<first>Sarah E.</first>
				<last>Glowa</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Douglas A.</first>
				<last>Watkinson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Timothy D.</first>
				<last>Jardine</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Eva C.</first>
				<last>Enders</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>With the continuous development of hydropower on a global scale, stranding of freshwater fishes is of growing concern, and an understanding of the mechanisms and variables affecting fish stranding in hydropeaking rivers is urgently needed. In particular, a methodology is required to identify the magnitude and timing at which fish stranding occurs in relation to environmental conditions. Here, we studied fish stranding in three reaches downstream of a hydropeaking generation station in the Saskatchewan River, Saskatchewan, Canada, using an innovative remote photography approach with 45 trail cameras and traditional transect monitoring, conducting 323 transects. We observed that juvenile sport and commercial fish species are stranding at a higher proportion than small bodied fish species. The remote photography approach provided more precise fish stranding timing and associated the environmental and physical conditions with a given stranding event, but captured fewer fish and only rarely allowed species identification. The comparison of the two methodologies resulted in similar stranded fish densities, but the remote photography allowed for continuous observations whereas the transect monitoring was limited by the observer availability in the field. Remote photography allowed for additional information on the scavenging of stranded fish, with scavenging occurring on average within 240 minutes of the fish being stranded. The probability of fish stranding increased significantly with increasing water temperature and substrate particle size resulted in greater stranding on finer substrates. Our findings have important implications for hydroelectric flow management by introducing an innovative, standardized method to study the effects of hydropeaking events on fish stranding that can be applied to increase our understanding of the impacts of hydropeaking on fish communities.</abstract>
			<url hash="05f26ee9">G23-30001</url>
			<pages>444-459</pages>
			<doi>10.1002/rra.4083</doi>
			<bibkey>Glowa-2023-Evaluating</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="31">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Physical Review Fluids, Volume 8, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Physical Society (APS)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Gravity currents in the cabbeling regime</title>
			<author>
				<first>Andrew</first>
				<last>Grace</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Marek</first>
				<last>Stastna</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kevin G.</first>
				<last>Lamb</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>K. Andrea</first>
				<last>Scott</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Freshwater has been shown to have a maximum density at about four degrees Celsius, and this leads to a phenomenon known as cabbeling. Cabbeling occurs when masses of water on different sides of the temperature of maximum density mix and create a denser mass. What happens when intruding and ambient temperatures in a gravity current are on opposite sides of the temperature of maximum density? How does cabbeling affect the evolution characteristics of gravity currents, and what sort of long term behavior arises?</abstract>
			<url hash="bd4e098c">G23-31001</url>
			<doi>10.1103/physrevfluids.8.014502</doi>
			<bibkey>Grace-2023-Gravity</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="32">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>International Journal of Wildland Fire</booktitle>
			<publisher>CSIRO Publishing</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Evaluation of new methods for drought estimation in the Canadian Forest Fire Danger Rating System</title>
			<author>
				<first>Chelene C.</first>
				<last>Hanes</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mike</first>
				<last>Wotton</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Laura</first>
				<last>Bourgeau-Chavez</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Douglas G.</first>
				<last>Woolford</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stéphane</first>
				<last>Bélair</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>David L.</first>
				<last>Martell</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mike D.</first>
				<last>Flannigan</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Background Canadian fire management agencies track drought conditions using the Drought Code (DC) in the Canadian Forest Fire Danger Rating System. The DC represents deep organic layer moisture.Aims To determine if electronic soil moisture probes and land surface model estimates of soil moisture content can be used to supplement and/or improve our understanding of drought in fire danger rating.Methods We carried out field studies in the provinces of Alberta and Ontario. We installed in situ soil moisture probes at two different depths in seven forest plots, from the surface through the organic layers, and in some cases into the mineral soil.Results Our results indicated that the simple DC model predicted the moisture content of the deeper organic layers (10–18 cm depths) well, even compared with the more sophisticated land surface model.Conclusions Electronic moisture probes can be used to supplement the DC. Land surface model estimates of moisture content consistently underpredicted organic layer moisture content.Implications Calibration and validation of the land surface model to organic soils in addition to mineral soils is necessary for future use in fire danger prediction.</abstract>
			<url hash="affba662">G23-32001</url>
			<doi>10.1071/wf22112</doi>
			<bibkey>Hanes-2023-Evaluation</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="33">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Agricultural and Forest Meteorology, Volume 341</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Crop water use efficiency from eddy covariance methods in cold water-limited regions</title>
			<author>
				<first>Phillip</first>
				<last>Harder</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Warren</first>
				<last>Helgason</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bruce</first>
				<last>Johnson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Crop–water interactions define productivity in water-limited dryland agricultural production systems in cold regions. Despite the agronomic and economic importance of this relationship there are challenges in quantifying crop water use efficiency (WUE). To understand dynamics driving crop water use and agricultural productivity in these environments, observations of evapotranspiration, carbon assimilation, meteorology, and crop growth were collected over 17 site-years at 5 agricultural sites in the sub-humid continental Canadian Prairies. Eddy-covariance (EC) derived water and carbon fluxes provided a means to comprehensively assess the WUE of current agricultural practices by both physiological (WUEP: g C kg−1 H2O) and agronomic (WUEY): kg yield mm H2O−1 hectare−1) approaches. Mean field scale WUEY for grain yields were 10.4 (Barley), 10.2 (Wheat), 6.0 (Canola), 19.3 (Peas), 12.2 (Lentils) and for silage/forage crops were 23.0 (Barley), 11.9 (Forage), and 20.7 (Corn) (kg yield mm H2O−1 hectare−1). An assessment of environmental factors and their covariance with WUE, utilising a conditional inference tree approach, demonstrated that WUE decreased when crops were under greater evapotranspiration demands. EC-based areal WUE approaches, measuring fluxes over footprints of hundreds of square metres, were compared with more commonly reported point-scale water balance residual approaches (WUEWB) and demonstrated consistently smaller magnitudes. WUEWB was greater than EC-estimated WUEY by an average of 52% and 65% for grain and forage/silage crops respectively. WUEWB also had greater variability than EC estimates, with standard deviations 188% and 128% greater than Barley and Wheat crops, respectively. This comparison highlights the scale dependency of WUE estimation methods, demonstrates considerable uncertainty in point scale water balance approaches due to spatial variability in crop–water interactions, and shows how this variability can be accounted for by EC observations. This improves the understanding of WUE and quantifies its variability in cold continental water-limited climates and provides a means to diagnose improved agricultural water management.</abstract>
			<url hash="1747c107">G23-33001</url>
			<pages>109657</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.agrformet.2023.109657</doi>
			<bibkey>Harder-2023-Crop</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="34">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>The Cryosphere, Volume 14, Issue 6</booktitle>
			<publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Improving sub-canopy snow depth mapping with unmanned aerial vehicles: lidar versus structure-from-motion techniques</title>
			<author>
				<first>Phillip</first>
				<last>Harder</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Warren</first>
				<last>Helgason</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Phillip</first>
				<last>Harder</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Warren</first>
				<last>Helgason</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. Vegetation has a tremendous influence on snow processes and snowpack dynamics, yet remote sensing techniques to resolve the spatial variability of sub-canopy snow depth are not always available and are difficult from space-based platforms. Unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) have had recent widespread application to capture high-resolution information on snow processes and are herein applied to the sub-canopy snow depth challenge. Previous demonstrations of snow depth mapping with UAV structure from motion (SfM) and airborne lidar have focussed on non-vegetated surfaces or reported large errors in the presence of vegetation. In contrast, UAV-lidar systems have high-density point clouds and measure returns from a wide range of scan angles, increasing the likelihood of successfully sensing the sub-canopy snow depth. The effectiveness of UAV lidar and UAV SfM in mapping snow depth in both open and forested terrain was tested in a 2019 field campaign at the Canadian Rockies Hydrological Observatory, Alberta, and at Canadian prairie sites near Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, Canada. Only UAV lidar could successfully measure the sub-canopy snow surface with reliable sub-canopy point coverage and consistent error metrics (root mean square error (RMSE) &lt;0.17 m and bias −0.03 to −0.13 m). Relative to UAV lidar, UAV SfM did not consistently sense the sub-canopy snow surface, the interpolation needed to account for point cloud gaps introduced interpolation artefacts, and error metrics demonstrated relatively large variability (RMSE&lt;0.33 m and bias 0.08 to −0.14 m). With the demonstration of sub-canopy snow depth mapping capabilities, a number of early applications are presented to showcase the ability of UAV lidar to effectively quantify the many multiscale snow processes defining snowpack dynamics in mountain and prairie environments.</abstract>
			<url hash="8a90f9be">G23-34001</url>
			<pages>1919-1935</pages>
			<doi>10.5194/tc-14-1919-2020</doi>
			<bibkey>Harder-2023-Improving</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="35">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrological Processes, Volume 37, Issue 5</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Field observation and mathematical representation of the hydrogeological function of alpine landforms in the Canadian Rockies</title>
			<author>
				<first>Jesse</first>
				<last>He</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Masaki</first>
				<last>Hayashi</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Groundwater discharge sustains the baseflow of alpine headwater streams, which is critical for water supply and aquatic environments in mountainous regions. Periglacial landforms typical of alpine headwaters (e.g., talus, moraine, rock glacier, alpine meadows) are important aquifers in alpine watersheds. This study examines the hydrological function of an alpine aquifer complex in a small headwater basin in the Canadian Rockies. The aquifer complex consisting of talus, alpine meadow underlain by a bedrock depression, and recessional moraine provided essentially all baseflow of a 6.5 km 2 watershed, even though the upper sub‐watershed containing the aquifer complex occupies only 14% of the watershed. Chemical and isotopic signatures indicated that the recessional moraine serves as a gatekeeper of the upper sub‐watershed, whereby it integrates groundwater components from multiple aquifers and controls the discharge from the outlet springs. Field observation of discharge and the water table in the moraine aquifer showed a nonlinear groundwater storage‐discharge relationship. Numerical groundwater flow models of the upper sub‐watershed showed that the transmissivity feedback resulting from a decrease in hydraulic conductivity with depth was essential for determining the nonlinear storage‐discharge relationship. A simple exponential function was proposed to represent the observed groundwater storage‐discharge relationship, which can be implemented within large‐scale hydrological models to simulate baseflow coming out of alpine headwater regions.</abstract>
			<url hash="322c9edb">G23-35001</url>
			<doi>10.1002/hyp.14881</doi>
			<bibkey>He-2023-Field</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="36">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Aquatic Toxicology, Volume 261</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Intersex manifestation in the rainbow darter (Etheostoma caeruleum): Are adult male fish susceptible to developing and recovering from intersex after exposure to endocrine active compounds?</title>
			<author>
				<first>Keegan A.</first>
				<last>Hicks</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Meghan</first>
				<last>Fuzzen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hadi A.</first>
				<last>Dhiyebi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Leslie M.</first>
				<last>Bragg</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Patricija</first>
				<last>Marjan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jessie</first>
				<last>Cunningham</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mark E.</first>
				<last>McMaster</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nivetha</first>
				<last>Srikanthan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kirsten E.</first>
				<last>Nikel</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Maricor J.</first>
				<last>Arlos</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mark R.</first>
				<last>Servos</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>For over a decade, intersex has been observed in rainbow darter (RD) (Etheostoma caeruleum) populations living downstream wastewater treatment plants (WWTPs) in the Grand River, Ontario, Canada. To further our understanding of intersex development in adult male fish, the current study addressed three objectives: i) can intersex be induced in adult male fish, ii) is there a specific window of exposure when adult male fish are more susceptible to developing intersex, and iii) can pre-exposed adult male fish recover from intersex? To assess intersex induction in adult male fish, wild male RD were exposed in the laboratory for 22 weeks (during periods of spawning, gonadal regression, and gonadal recrudescence) to environmentally relevant concentrations of 17α-ethinylestradiol (EE2) including nominal 0, 1, and 10 ng/L. Intersex rates and severity at 10 ng/L EE2 were similar to those observed historically in adult male populations living downstream WWTPs in the Grand River and confirmed previous predictions that 1–10 ng/L EE2 would cause these adverse effects. To assess a window of sensitivity in developing intersex, male RD were exposed to nominal 0, 1 or 10 ng/L EE2 for 4 weeks during three different periods of gonadal development, including (i) spawning, (ii) early recrudescence and (iii) late recrudescence. These short-term exposures revealed that intersex incidence and severity were greater when RD were exposed while gonads were fully developed (during spawning) compared to periods of recrudescence. To assess if RD recover from intersex, wild fish were collected downstream WWTPs in the Grand River and assessed for intersex both before and after a 22-week recovery period in clean water that included gonadal regression and recrudescence. Results showed that fish did not recover from intersex, with intersex rates and severity similar to those both before and after the transition to clean water. This study further advances our knowledge on intersex manifestation in adult male fish including their sensitivity to endocrine active compounds during different periods of their annual reproductive cycle and their limited ability to recover from intersex after onset of the condition.</abstract>
			<url hash="20993135">G23-36001</url>
			<pages>106636</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.aquatox.2023.106636</doi>
			<bibkey>Hicks-2023-Intersex</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="37">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Angewandte Chemie International Edition, Volume 62, Issue 12</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Simultaneous Detection of L‐Lactate and D‐Glucose Using DNA Aptamers in Human Blood Serum**</title>
			<author>
				<first>Po-Jung Jimmy</first>
				<last>Huang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Juewen</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>L-lactate is a key metabolite indicative of physiological states, glycolysis pathways, and various diseases such as sepsis, heart attack, lactate acidosis, and cancer. Detection of lactate has been relying on a few enzymes that need additional oxidants. In this work, DNA aptamers for L-lactate were obtained using a library-immobilization selection method and the highest affinity aptamer reached a Kd of 0.43 mM as determined using isothermal titration calorimetry. The aptamers showed up to 50-fold selectivity for L-lactate over D-lactate and had little responses to other closely related analogs such as pyruvate or 3-hydroxybutyrate. A fluorescent biosensor based on the strand displacement method showed a limit of detection of 0.55 mM L-lactate, and the sensor worked in 90 % serum. Simultaneous detection of L-lactate and D-glucose in the same solution was achieved. This work has broadened the scope of aptamers to simple metabolites and provided a useful probe for continuous and multiplexed monitoring.</abstract>
			<url hash="98255650">G23-37001</url>
			<doi>10.1002/anie.202212879</doi>
			<bibkey>Huang-2023-Simultaneous</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="38">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Water Resources Research</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Geophysical Union (AGU)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Numerical study of coupled water and vapour flow, heat transfer, and solute transport in variably‐saturated deformable soil during freeze‐thaw cycles</title>
			<author>
				<first>Xiang</first>
				<last>Huang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>David L.</first>
				<last>Rudolph</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract As climate change intensifies, soil water flow, heat transfer, and solute transport in the active, unfrozen zones within permafrost and seasonally frozen ground exhibit progressively more complex interactions that are difficult to elucidate with measurements alone. For example, frozen conditions impede water flow and solute transport in soil, while heat and mass transfer are significantly affected by high thermal inertia generated from water‐ice phase change during the freeze‐thaw cycle. To assist in understanding these subsurface processes, the current study presents a coupled two‐dimensional model, which examines heat conduction‐convection with water‐ice phase change, soil water (liquid water and vapour) and groundwater flow, ad v ective‐dispersive solute transport with sorption, and soil deformation (frost heave and thaw settlement) in variably saturated soils subjected to freeze‐thaw actions. This coupled multiphysics problem is numerically solved using the finite element method. The model's performance is first verified by comparison to a well‐documented freezing test on unsaturated soil in a laboratory environment obtained from the literature. Then based on the proposed model, we quantify the impacts of freeze‐thaw cycles on the distribution of temperature, water content, displacement history, and solute concentration in three distinct soil types, including sand, silt and clay textures. The influence of fluctuations in the air temperature, groundwater level, hydraulic conductivity, and solute transport parameters was also comparatively studied.The results show that (i) there is a significant bidirectional exchange between groundwater in the saturated zone and soil water in the vadose zone during freeze‐thaw periods, and its magnitude increases with the combined influence of higher hydraulic conductivity and higher capillarity; (ii) the rapid dewatering ahead of the freezing front causes local volume shrinkage within the non‐frozen region when the freezing front propagates downward during the freezing stage and this volume shrinkage reduces the impact of frost heave due to ice formation. This gradually recovers when the thawed water replenishes the water loss zone during the thawing stage; and (iii) the profiles of soil moisture, temperature, displacement, and solute concentration during freeze‐thaw cycles are sensitive to the changes in amplitude and freeze‐thaw period of the sinusoidal varying air temperature near the ground surface, hydraulic conductivity of soil texture, and the initial groundwater levels. Our modelling framework and simulation results highlight the need to account for coupled thermal‐hydraulic‐mechanical‐chemical behaviours to better understand soil water and groundwater dynamics during freeze‐thaw cycles and further help explain the observed changes in water cycles and landscape evolution in cold regions. This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</abstract>
			<url hash="c0464606">G23-38001</url>
			<doi>10.1029/2022wr032146</doi>
			<bibkey>Huang-2023-Numerical</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="39">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Geoscientific Model Development, Volume 16, Issue 2</booktitle>
			<publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>A simple, efficient, mass-conservative approach to solving Richards' equation (openRE, v1.0)</title>
			<author>
				<first>A. M.</first>
				<last>Ireson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Raymond J.</first>
				<last>Spiteri</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Martyn P.</first>
				<last>Clark</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Simon A.</first>
				<last>Mathias</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. A simple numerical solution procedure – namely the method of lines combined with an off-the-shelf ordinary differential equation (ODE) solver – was shown in previous work to provide efficient, mass-conservative solutions to the pressure-head form of Richards' equation. We implement such a solution in our model openRE. We developed a novel method to quantify the boundary fluxes that reduce water balance errors without negative impacts on model runtimes – the solver flux output method (SFOM). We compare this solution with alternatives, including the classic modified Picard iteration method and the Hydrus 1D model. We reproduce a set of benchmark solutions with all models. We find that Celia's solution has the best water balance, but it can incur significant truncation errors in the simulated boundary fluxes, depending on the time steps used. Our solution has comparable runtimes to Hydrus and better water balance performance (though both models have excellent water balance closure for all the problems we considered). Our solution can be implemented in an interpreted language, such as MATLAB or Python, making use of off-the-shelf ODE solvers. We evaluated alternative SciPy ODE solvers that are available in Python and make practical recommendations about the best way to implement them for Richards' equation. There are two advantages of our approach: (i) the code is concise, making it ideal for teaching purposes; and (ii) the method can be easily extended to represent alternative properties (e.g., novel ways to parameterize the K(ψ) relationship) and processes (e.g., it is straightforward to couple heat or solute transport), making it ideal for testing alternative hypotheses.</abstract>
			<url hash="78fa2163">G23-39001</url>
			<pages>659-677</pages>
			<doi>10.5194/gmd-16-659-2023</doi>
			<bibkey>Ireson-2023-A</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="40">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Ecosphere, Volume 14, Issue 7</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>The influence of postfire recovery and environmental conditions on boreal vegetation</title>
			<author>
				<first>Alexis Gardiner</first>
				<last>Jorgensen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Raquel</first>
				<last>Alfaro-Sánchez</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Steven G.</first>
				<last>Cumming</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Alison L.</first>
				<last>White</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Geneviève É.</first>
				<last>Degré-Timmons</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nicola J.</first>
				<last>Day</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>M. R.</first>
				<last>Turetsky</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jill F.</first>
				<last>Johnstone</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Xanthe J.</first>
				<last>Walker</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jennifer L.</first>
				<last>Baltzer</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Climate change is increasing the frequency and extent of fires in the boreal biome of North America. These changes can alter the recovery of both canopy and understory vegetation. There is uncertainty about plant and lichen recovery patterns following fire, and how they are mediated by environmental conditions. Here, we aim to address these knowledge gaps by studying patterns of postfire vegetation recovery at the community and individual species level over the first 100+ years following fire. Data from vegetation surveys collected from 581 plots in the Northwest Territories, Canada, ranging from 1 to 275 years postfire, were used to assess the influence of time after fire and local environmental conditions on plant community composition and to model trends in the relative abundance of several common plant and lichen species. Time after fire significantly influenced vegetation community composition and interacted with local environmental conditions, particularly soil moisture. Soil moisture individually (in the absence of interactions) was the most commonly significant variable in plant and lichen recovery models. Patterns of postfire recovery varied greatly among species. Our results provide novel information on plant community recovery after fire and highlight the importance of soil moisture to local vegetation patterns. They will aid northern communities and land managers to anticipate the impacts of increased fire activity on both local vegetation and the wildlife that relies on it.</abstract>
			<url hash="b7d2b2f9">G23-40001</url>
			<doi>10.1002/ecs2.4605</doi>
			<bibkey>Jorgensen-2023-The</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="41">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Research, Volume 216</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Paleolimnological evaluation of metal(loid) enrichment from oil sands and gold mining operations in northwestern Canada</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mitchell L.</first>
				<last>Kay</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Izabela</first>
				<last>Jasiak</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Wynona H.</first>
				<last>Klemt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Johan A.</first>
				<last>Wiklund</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jelle</first>
				<last>Faber</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Lauren A.</first>
				<last>MacDonald</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>James V.</first>
				<last>Telford</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Cory A. M.</first>
				<last>Savage</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Colin A.</first>
				<last>Cooke</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brent B.</first>
				<last>Wolfe</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Roland I.</first>
				<last>Hall</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abundant reserves of metals and oil have spurred large-scale mining developments across northwestern Canada during the past 80 years. Historically, the associated emissions footprint of hazardous metal(loid)s has been difficult to identify, in part, because monitoring records are too short and sparse to have characterized their natural concentrations before mining began. Stratigraphic analysis of lake sediment cores has been employed where concerns of pollution exist to determine pre-disturbance metal(loid) concentrations and quantify the degree of enrichment since mining began. Here, we synthesize the current state of knowledge via systematic re-analysis of temporal variation in sediment metal(loid) concentrations from 51 lakes across four key regions spanning 670 km from bitumen mining in the Alberta Oil Sands Region (AOSR) to gold mining (Giant and Con mines) at Yellowknife in central Northwest Territories. Our compilation includes upland and floodplain lakes at varying distances from the mines to evaluate dispersal of pollution-indicator metal(loid)s from bitumen (vanadium and nickel) and gold mining (arsenic and antimony) via atmospheric and fluvial pathways. Results demonstrate ‘severe’ enrichment of vanadium and nickel at near-field sites (≤20 km) within the AOSR and ‘severe’ (near-field; ≤ 40 km) to ‘considerable’ (far-field; 40–80 km) enrichment of arsenic and antimony due to gold mining at Yellowknife via atmospheric pathways, but no evidence of enrichment of vanadium or nickel via atmospheric or fluvial pathways at the Peace-Athabasca Delta and Slave River Delta. Findings can be used by decision makers to evaluate risks associated with contaminant dispersal by the large-scale mining activities. In addition, we reflect upon methodological approaches to be considered when evaluating paleolimnological data for evidence of anthropogenic contributions to metal(loid) deposition and advocate for proactive inclusion of paleolimnology in the early design stage of environmental contaminant monitoring programs.</abstract>
			<url hash="0f6ed59c">G23-41001</url>
			<pages>114439</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.envres.2022.114439</doi>
			<bibkey>Kay-2023-Paleolimnological</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="42">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Water, Volume 15, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>MDPI AG</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Assessing and Mitigating Ice-Jam Flood Hazards and Risks: A European Perspective</title>
			<author>
				<first>Karl-Erich</first>
				<last>Lindenschmidt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Knut</first>
				<last>Alfredsen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Dirk</first>
				<last>Carstensen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Adam</first>
				<last>Choryński</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Gustafsson,</first>
				<last>David</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michał</first>
				<last>Halicki</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bernd</first>
				<last>Hentschel</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Niina</first>
				<last>Karjalainen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michael</first>
				<last>Kögel</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Tomasz</first>
				<last>Kolerski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Marika</first>
				<last>Kornaś-Dynia</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michał</first>
				<last>Kubicki</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zbigniew W.</first>
				<last>Kundzewicz</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Cornelia</first>
				<last>Lauschke</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Albert</first>
				<last>Malinger</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Włodzimierz</first>
				<last>Marszelewski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fabian</first>
				<last>Möldner</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Barbro</first>
				<last>Näslund-Landenmark</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Tomasz</first>
				<last>Niedzielski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Antti</first>
				<last>Parjanne</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bogusław</first>
				<last>Pawłowski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Iwona</first>
				<last>Pińskwar</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Joanna</first>
				<last>Remisz</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Maik</first>
				<last>Renner</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michael</first>
				<last>Roers</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Maksymilian</first>
				<last>Rybacki</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ewelina</first>
				<last>Szałkiewicz</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michał</first>
				<last>Szydłowski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Grzegorz</first>
				<last>Walusiak</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matylda</first>
				<last>Witek</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mateusz</first>
				<last>Zagata</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Maciej</first>
				<last>Zdralewicz</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The assessment and mapping of riverine flood hazards and risks is recognized by many countries as an important tool for characterizing floods and developing flood management plans. Often, however, these management plans give attention primarily to open-water floods, with ice-jam floods being mostly an afterthought once these plans have been drafted. In some Nordic regions, ice-jam floods can be more severe than open-water floods, with floodwater levels of ice-jam floods often exceeding levels of open-water floods for the same return periods. Hence, it is imperative that flooding due to river ice processes be considered in flood management plans. This also pertains to European member states who are required to submit renewed flood management plans every six years to the European governance authorities. On 19 and 20 October 2022, a workshop entitled “Assessing and mitigating ice-jam flood hazard and risk” was hosted in Poznań, Poland to explore the necessity of incorporating ice-jam flood hazard and risk assessments in the European Union’s Flood Directive. The presentations given at the workshop provided a good overview of flood risk assessments in Europe and how they may change due to the climate in the future. Perspectives from Norway, Sweden, Finland, Germany, and Poland were presented. Mitigation measures, particularly the artificial breakage of river ice covers and ice-jam flood forecasting, were shared. Advances in ice processes were also presented at the workshop, including state-of-the-art developments in tracking ice-floe velocities using particle tracking velocimetry, characterizing hanging dam ice, designing new ice-control structures, detecting, and monitoring river ice covers using composite imagery from both radar and optical satellite sensors, and calculating ice-jam flood hazards using a stochastic modelling approach.</abstract>
			<url hash="1ddb7a72">G23-42001</url>
			<pages>76</pages>
			<doi>10.3390/w15010076</doi>
			<bibkey>Lindenschmidt-2023-Assessing</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="43">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrology Research, Volume 54, Issue 2</booktitle>
			<publisher>IWA Publishing</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Extension and refinement of a stochastic modelling approach to assess ice-jam flood hazard</title>
			<author>
				<first>Karl-Erich</first>
				<last>Lindenschmidt</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract In the spring of 2020, the town of Fort McMurray, which lies on the banks of the Athabasca River, experienced an ice-jam flood event that was the most severe in approximately 60 years. In order to capture the severity of the event, a stochastic modelling approach, previously developed by the author for ice-jam flood forecasting, has been refined for ice-jam flood hazard and risk assessments and ice-jam mitigation feasibility studies, which is the subject of this paper. Scenarios of artificial breakage demonstrate the applicability of the revised modelling framework.</abstract>
			<url hash="a5671d17">G23-43001</url>
			<pages>149-164</pages>
			<doi>10.2166/nh.2023.042</doi>
			<bibkey>Lindenschmidt-2023-Extension</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="44">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Water, Volume 15, Issue 4</booktitle>
			<publisher>MDPI AG</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Surface Water Quality Modelling</title>
			<author>
				<first>Karl-Erich</first>
				<last>Lindenschmidt</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Surface water quality modelling has become an important means of better understanding aquatic and riparian ecosystem processes at all scales, from the micro-scale (e [...]</abstract>
			<url hash="38b025ae">G23-44001</url>
			<pages>828</pages>
			<doi>10.3390/w15040828</doi>
			<bibkey>Lindenschmidt-2023-Surface</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="45">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Contemporary Economic Policy, Volume 41, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>What is the future of water quality trading?</title>
			<author>
				<first>Haiyan</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Roy</first>
				<last>Brouwer</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>A comprehensive review of experiences with water quality trading (WQT) programs worldwide is presented, spanning altogether more than 4 decades. A new WQT database is built, extracting data and information from existing review papers, complemented with gray and published literature about individual trading programs. Key aspects that affect trading volumes and program continuation are identified and categorized. No single success or fail factor emerges from this review, typically a mix of factors play a role. There is potential for WQT to evolve further and serve as a cost-effective pollution control instrument, but this requires nudging political will to regulate nonpoint source.</abstract>
			<url hash="800c42cb">G23-45001</url>
			<pages>194-217</pages>
			<doi>10.1111/coep.12583</doi>
			<bibkey>Liu-2023-What</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="46">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Science &amp; Technology, Volume 56, Issue 20</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Chemical Society (ACS)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Large Fractionation in Iron Isotopes Implicates Metabolic Pathways for Iron Cycling in Boreal Shield Lakes</title>
			<author>
				<first>Kai</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sherry L.</first>
				<last>Schiff</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Lingling</first>
				<last>Wu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Lewis A.</first>
				<last>Molot</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jason J.</first>
				<last>Venkiteswaran</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michael</first>
				<last>Paterson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Richard J.</first>
				<last>Elgood</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jackson M.</first>
				<last>Tsuji</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Josh D.</first>
				<last>Neufeld</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kai</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sherry L.</first>
				<last>Schiff</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Lingling</first>
				<last>Wu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Lewis A.</first>
				<last>Molot</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jason J.</first>
				<last>Venkiteswaran</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michael</first>
				<last>Paterson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Richard J.</first>
				<last>Elgood</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jackson M.</first>
				<last>Tsuji</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Josh D.</first>
				<last>Neufeld</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Stable Fe isotopes have only recently been measured in freshwater systems, mainly in meromictic lakes. Here we report the δ56Fe of dissolved, particulate, and sediment Fe in two small dimictic boreal shield headwater lakes: manipulated eutrophic Lake 227, with annual cyanobacterial blooms, and unmanipulated oligotrophic Lake 442. Within the lakes, the range in δ56Fe is large (ca. -0.9 to +1.8‰), spanning more than half the entire range of natural Earth surface samples. Two layers in the water column with distinctive δ56Fe of dissolved (dis) and particulate (spm) Fe were observed, despite differences in trophic states. In the epilimnia of both lakes, a large Δ56Fedis-spm fractionation of 0.4-1‰ between dissolved and particulate Fe was only observed during cyanobacterial blooms in Lake 227, possibly regulated by selective biological uptake of isotopically light Fe by cyanobacteria. In the anoxic layers in both lakes, upward flux from sediments dominates the dissolved Fe pool with an apparent Δ56Fedis-spm fractionation of -2.2 to -0.6‰. Large Δ56Fedis-spm and previously published metagenome sequence data suggest active Fe cycling processes in anoxic layers, such as microaerophilic Fe(II) oxidation or photoferrotrophy, could regulate biogeochemical cycling. Large fractionation of stable Fe isotopes in these lakes provides a potential tool to probe Fe cycling and the acquisition of Fe by cyanobacteria, with relevance for understanding biogeochemical cycling of Earth's early ferruginous oceans.</abstract>
			<url hash="92b9ed25">G23-46001</url>
			<pages>14840-14851</pages>
			<doi>10.1021/acs.est.2c04247</doi>
			<bibkey>Liu-2023-Large</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="47">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Environmental Management, Volume 341</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Multiple anthropogenic stressors influence the taxonomic and functional homogenization of macroinvertebrate communities on the mainstream of an urban-agricultural river in China</title>
			<author>
				<first>Yue</first>
				<last>Ma</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zongling</first>
				<last>Yu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Shiqi</first>
				<last>Jia</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Naicheng</first>
				<last>Wu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kai</first>
				<last>Yin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yeyao</first>
				<last>Wang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Xiaowei</first>
				<last>Jin</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Biodiversity loss is caused by intensive human activities and threatens human well-being. However, less is known about how the combined effects of multiple stressors on the diversity of internal (alpha diversity) and multidimensional (beta diversity) communities. Here, we conducted a long-term experiment to quantify the contribution of environmental stressors (including water quality, land use, climate factors, and hydrological regimes) to macroinvertebrate communities alpha and beta diversity in the mainstream of the Songhua River, the third largest river in China, from 2012 to 2019. Our results demonstrated that the alpha and beta diversity indices showed a decline during the study period, with the dissimilarity in community composition between sites decreasing significantly, especially in the impacted river sections (upper and midstream). Despite overall improvement in water quality after management intervention, multiple human-caused stressors still have led to biotic homogenization of macroinvertebrate communities in terms of both taxonomic and functional diversities in the past decade. Our study revealed the increased human land use explained an important portion of the variation of diversities, further indirectly promoting biotic homogenization by changing the physical and chemical factors of water quality, ultimately altering assemblage ecological processes. Furthermore, the facets of diversity have distinct response mechanisms to stressors, providing complementary information from the perspective of taxonomy and function to better reflect the ecological changes of communities. Environmental filtering determined taxonomic beta diversity, and functional beta diversity was driven by the joint efforts of stressors and spatial processes. Finally, we proposed that traditional water quality monitoring alone cannot fully reveal the status of river ecological environment protection, and more importantly, we should explore the continuous changes in biodiversity over the long term. Meanwhile, our results also highlight timely control of nutrient input and unreasonable expansion of land use can better curb the ecological degradation of rivers and promote the healthy and sustainable development of floodplain ecosystems.</abstract>
			<url hash="2a058a40">G23-47001</url>
			<pages>118017</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.jenvman.2023.118017</doi>
			<bibkey>Ma-2023-Multiple</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="48">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Aquatic Toxicology, Volume 257</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Perfluoroethylcyclohexane sulphonate, an emerging perfluoroalkyl substance, disrupts mitochondrial membranes and the expression of key molecular targets in vitro</title>
			<author>
				<first>Hannah</first>
				<last>Mahoney</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jenna</first>
				<last>Cantin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yuwei</first>
				<last>Xie</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Markus</first>
				<last>Brinkmann</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Perfluoroethylcyclohexane sulphonate (PFECHS) is an emerging, replacement perfluoroalkyl substance (PFAS) with little information available on the toxic effects or potencies with which to characterize its potential impacts on aquatic environments. This study aimed to characterize effects of PFECHS using in vitro systems, including rainbow trout liver cells (RTL-W1 cell line) and lymphocytes separated from whole blood. It was determined that exposure to PFECHS caused minor acute toxic effects for most endpoints and that little PFECHS was concentrated into cells with a mean in vitro bioconcentration factor of 81 ± 25 L/kg. However, PFECHS was observed to affect the mitochondrial membrane and key molecular receptors, such as the peroxisome proliferator receptor, cytochrome p450-dependent monooxygenases, and receptors involved in oxidative stress. Also, glutathione-S-transferase was significantly down-regulated at a near environmentally relevant exposure concentration of 400 ng/L. These results are the first to report bioconcentration of PFECHS, as well as its effects on the peroxisome proliferator and glutathione-S-transferase receptors, suggesting that even with little bioconcentration, PFECHS has potential to cause adverse effects.</abstract>
			<url hash="72669a16">G23-48001</url>
			<pages>106453</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.aquatox.2023.106453</doi>
			<bibkey>Mahoney-2023-Perfluoroethylcyclohexane</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="49">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Science &amp; Technology, Volume 57, Issue 10</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Chemical Society (ACS)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Acute Exposure of Zebrafish (&lt;i&gt;Danio rerio&lt;/i&gt;) to the Next-Generation Perfluoroalkyl Substance, Perfluoroethylcyclohexanesulfonate, Shows Similar Effects as Legacy Substances</title>
			<author>
				<first>Hannah</first>
				<last>Mahoney</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jenna</first>
				<last>Cantin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Josephine</first>
				<last>Rybchuk</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yuwei</first>
				<last>Xie</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Markus</first>
				<last>Brinkmann</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Perfluoroethylcyclohexanesulfonate (PFECHS) is an emerging perfluoroalkyl substance (PFAS) that has been considered a potential replacement for perfluorooctanesulfonic acid (PFOS). However, there is little information characterizing the toxic potency of PFECHS to zebrafish embryos and its potential for effects in aquatic environments. This study assessed toxic potency of PFECHS in vivo during both acute (96-hour postfertilization) and chronic (21-day posthatch) exposures and tested concentrations of PFECHS from 500 ng/L to 2 mg/L. PFECHS was less likely to cause mortalities than PFOS for both the acute and chronic experiments based on previously published values for PFOS exposure, but exposure resulted in a similar incidence of deformities. Exposure to PFECHS also resulted in significantly increased abundance of transcripts of peroxisome proliferator activated receptor alpha (pparα), cytochrome p450 1a1 (cyp1a1), and apolipoprotein IV (apoaIV) at concentrations nearing those of environmental relevance. Overall, these results provide further insight into the safety of an emerging PFAS alternative in the aquatic environment and raise awareness that previously considered &quot;safer&quot; alternatives may show similar effects as legacy PFASs.</abstract>
			<url hash="cadafd73">G23-49001</url>
			<pages>4199-4207</pages>
			<doi>10.1021/acs.est.2c08463</doi>
			<bibkey>Mahoney-2023-Acute</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="50">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Climate Dynamics, Volume 60, Issue 5-6</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Changes in freezing rain occurrence over eastern Canada using convection-permitting climate simulations</title>
			<author>
				<first>Sébastien</first>
				<last>Marinier</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Julie M.</first>
				<last>Thériault</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kyoko</first>
				<last>Ikeda</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sébastien</first>
				<last>Marinier</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Julie M.</first>
				<last>Thériault</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kyoko</first>
				<last>Ikeda</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Freezing precipitation has major consequences for ground and air transportation, the health of citizens, and power networks. Previous studies using coarse resolution climate models have shown a northward migration of freezing rain in the future. Increased model resolution can better define local topography leading to improved representation of conditions that are favorable for freezing rain. The goal of this study is to examine the climatology and characteristics of future freezing rain events using very-high resolution climate simulations. Historical and pseudo-global warming simulations with a 4-km horizontal grid length were used and compared with available observations. Simulations revealed a northerly shift of freezing rain occurrence, and an increase in the winter. Freezing rain was still shown to occur in the Saint-Lawrence River Valley in a warmer climate, primarily due to stronger wind channeling. Up to 50% of the future freezing rain events also occurred in present day climate within 12 h of each other. In northern Maine, they are typically shorter than 6 h in current climate and longer than 6 h in warmer conditions due to the onset of precipitation during low-pressure systems occurrences. The occurrence of freezing rain also locally increases slightly north of Québec City in a warmer climate because of freezing rain that is produced by warm rain processes. Overall, the study shows that high-resolution regional climate simulations are needed to study freezing rain events in warmer climate conditions, because high horizontal resolutions better define small-scale topographic features and local physical mechanisms that have an influence on these events.</abstract>
			<url hash="8ab29b49">G23-50001</url>
			<pages>1369-1384</pages>
			<doi>10.1007/s00382-022-06370-6</doi>
			<bibkey>Marinier-2023-Changes</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="51">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Advances in Water Resources, Volume 173</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Non-asymptotic Weibull tails explain the statistics of extreme daily precipitation</title>
			<author>
				<first>Francesco</first>
				<last>Marra</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>William A.</first>
				<last>Amponsah</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>S.</first>
				<last>Papalexiou</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The exceedance probability of extreme daily precipitation is usually quantified assuming asymptotic behaviours. Non-asymptotic statistics, however, would allow us to describe extremes with reduced uncertainty and to establish relations between physical processes and emerging extremes. These approaches are still mistrusted by part of the community as they rely on assumptions on the tail behaviour of the daily precipitation distribution. This paper addresses this gap. We use global quality-controlled long rain gauge records to show that daily precipitation annual maxima are samples likely emerging from Weibull tails in most of the stations worldwide. These non-asymptotic tails can explain the statistics of observed extremes better than asymptotic approximations from extreme value theory. We call for a renewed consideration of non-asymptotic statistics for the description of extremes.</abstract>
			<url hash="320efc2c">G23-51001</url>
			<pages>104388</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.advwatres.2023.104388</doi>
			<bibkey>Marra-2023-Non-asymptotic</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="52">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Research Communications, Volume 5, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>IOP Publishing</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Validation of FABDEM, a global bare-earth elevation model, against UAV-lidar derived elevation in a complex forested mountain catchment</title>
			<author>
				<first>Christopher B.</first>
				<last>Marsh</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Phillip</first>
				<last>Harder</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Space-based, global-extent digital elevation models (DEMs) are key inputs to many Earth sciences applications. However, many of these applications require the use of a ‘bare-Earth’ DEM versus a digital surface model (DSM), the latter of which may include systematic positive biases due to tree canopies in forested areas. Critical topographic features may be obscured by these biases. Vegetation-free datasets have been created by using statistical relationships and machine learning to train on local-scale datasets (e.g., lidar) to de-bias the global-extent datasets. Recent advances in satellite platforms coupled with increased availability of computational resources and lidar reference products has allowed for a new generation of vegetation- and urban-canopy removals. One of these is the Forest And Buildings removed Copernicus DEM (FABDEM), based on the most recent and most accurate global DSM Copernicus-30. Among the more challenging landscapes to quantify surface elevations are densely forested mountain catchments, where even airborne lidar applications struggle to capture surface returns. The increasing affordability and availability of UAV-based lidar platforms have resulted in new capacity to fly modest spatial extents with unrivalled point densities. These data allow an unprecedented ability to validate global sub-canopy DEMs against representative UAV-based lidar data. In this work, the FABDEM is validated against up-scaled lidar data in a steep and forested mountain catchment considering elevation, slope, and Terrain Position Index (TPI) metrics. Comparisons of FABDEM with SRTM, MERIT, and the Copernicus-30 dataset are made. It was found that the FABDEM had a 24% reduction in elevation RMSE and a 135% reduction in bias compared to the Copernicus-30 dataset. Overall, the FABDEM provides a clear improvement over existing deforested DEM products in complex mountain topography such as the MERIT DEM. This study supports the use of FABDEM in forested mountain catchments as the current best-in-class data product.</abstract>
			<url hash="20bb53c2">G23-52001</url>
			<pages>031009</pages>
			<doi>10.1088/2515-7620/acc56d</doi>
			<bibkey>Marsh-2023-Validation</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="53">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Water Resources Research, Volume 59, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Geophysical Union (AGU)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Windmapper: An Efficient Wind Downscaling Method for Hydrological Models</title>
			<author>
				<first>Christopher B.</first>
				<last>Marsh</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Vincent</first>
				<last>Vionnet</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John W.</first>
				<last>Pomeroy</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Estimates of near-surface wind speed and direction are key meteorological components for predicting many surface hydrometeorological processes that influence critical aspects of hydrological and biological systems. However, observations of near-surface wind are typically spatially sparse. The use of these sparse wind fields to force distributed models, such as hydrological models, is greatly complicated in complex terrain, such as mountain headwaters basins. In these regions, wind flows are heavily impacted by overlapping influences of terrain at different scales. This can have a great impact on calculations of evapotranspiration, snowmelt, and blowing snow transport and sublimation. The use of high-resolution atmospheric models allows for numerical weather prediction (NWP) model outputs to be dynamically downscaled. However, the computation burden for large spatial extents and long periods of time often precludes their use. Here, a wind-library approach is presented to aid in downscaling NWP outputs and terrain-correcting spatially interpolated observations. This approach preserves important spatial characteristics of the flow field at a fraction of the computational costs of even the simplest high-resolution atmospheric models. This approach improves on previous implementations by: scaling to large spatial extents O(1M km2); approximating lee-side effects; and fully automating the creation of the wind library. Overall, this approach was shown to have a third quartile RMSE of 1.8 and a third quartile RMSE of 58.2° versus a standalone diagnostic windflow model. The wind velocity estimates versus observations were better than existing empirical terrain-based estimates and computational savings were approximately 100-fold versus the diagnostic model.</abstract>
			<url hash="980734a7">G23-53001</url>
			<doi>10.1029/2022wr032683</doi>
			<bibkey>Marsh-2023-Windmapper:</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
		<paper id="2">
			<title>Large‐Domain Multisite Precipitation Generation: Operational Blueprint and Demonstration for 1,000 Sites</title>
			<author>
				<first>S.</first>
				<last>Papalexiou</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Francesco</first>
				<last>Serinaldi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Martyn P.</first>
				<last>Clark</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Stochastic simulations of spatiotemporal patterns of hydroclimatic processes, such as precipitation, are needed to build alternative but equally plausible inputs for water‐related design and management, and to estimate uncertainty and assess risks. However, while existing stochastic simulation methods are mature enough to deal with relatively small domains and coarse spatiotemporal scales, additional work is required to develop simulation tools for large‐domain analyses, which are more and more common in an increasingly interconnected world. This study proposes a methodological advancement in the CoSMoS framework, which is a flexible simulation framework preserving arbitrary marginal distributions and correlations, to dramatically decrease the computational burden and make the algorithm fast enough to perform large‐domain simulations in short time. The proposed approach focuses on correlated processes with mixed (zero‐inflated) Uniform marginal distributions. These correlated processes act as intermediates between the target process to simulate (precipitation) and parent Gaussian processes that are the core of the simulation algorithm. Working in the mixed‐Uniform space enables a substantial simplification of the so‐called correlation transformation functions, which represent a computational bottle neck in the original CoSMoS formulation. As a proof of concept, we simulate 40 years of daily precipitation records from 1,000 gauging stations in the Mississippi River basin. Moreover, we extend CoSMoS incorporating parent non‐Gaussian processes with different degrees of tail dependence and suggest potential improvements including the separate simulation of occurrence and intensity processes, and the use of advection, anisotropy, and nonstationary spatiotemporal correlation functions.</abstract>
			<url hash="010e651d">G23-53002</url>
			<doi>10.1029/2022wr034094</doi>
			<bibkey>Papalexiou-2023-Large‐Domain</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="54">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Research, Volume 217</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Estimates, spatial variability, and environmental drivers of mercury biomagnification rates through lake food webs in the Canadian subarctic</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mehdi</first>
				<last>Moslemi-Aqdam</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>George C.</first>
				<last>Low</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mike</first>
				<last>Low</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brian</first>
				<last>Laird</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brian A.</first>
				<last>Branfireun</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Heidi K.</first>
				<last>Swanson</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Biomagnification of mercury (Hg) through lake food webs is understudied in rapidly changing northern regions, where wild-caught subsistence fish are critical to food security. We investigated estimates and among-lake variability of Hg biomagnification rates (BMR), relationships between Hg BMR and Hg levels in subsistence fish, and environmental drivers of Hg BMR in ten remote subarctic lakes in Northwest Territories, Canada. Lake-specific linear regressions between Hg concentrations (total Hg ([THg]) in fish and methyl Hg ([MeHg]) in primary consumers) and baseline-adjusted δ15N ratios were significant (p &lt; 0.001, r2 = 0.58–0.88), indicating biomagnification of Hg through food webs of all studied lakes. Quantified using the slope of Hg-δ15N regressions, Hg BMR ranged from 0.16 to 0.25, with mean ± standard deviation of 0.20 ± 0.03). Using fish [MeHg] rather than [THg] lowered estimates of Hg BMR by ∼10%, suggesting that the use of [THg] as a proxy for [MeHg] in fish can influence estimates of Hg BMR. Among-lake variability of size-standardized [THg] in resident fish species from different trophic guilds, namely Lake Whitefish (Coregonus clupeaformis) and Northern Pike (Esox lucius), was not significantly explained by among-lake variability in Hg BMR. Stepwise multiple regressions indicated that among-lake variability of Hg BMR was best explained by a positive relationship with catchment forest cover (p = 0.009, r2 = 0.59), likely reflecting effects of forest cover on water chemistry of downstream lakes and ultimately, concentrations of biomagnifying MeHg (and percent MeHg of total Hg) in resident biota. These findings improve our understanding of Hg biomagnification in remote subarctic lakes.</abstract>
			<url hash="05d00c1e">G23-54001</url>
			<pages>114835</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.envres.2022.114835</doi>
			<bibkey>Moslemi-Aqdam-2023-Estimates,</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="55">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence, Volume 5</booktitle>
			<publisher>Frontiers Media SA</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Leveraging Guided Backpropagation to Select Convolutional Neural Networks for Plant Classification</title>
			<author>
				<first>Sakib</first>
				<last>Mostafa</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Debajyoti</first>
				<last>Mondal</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michael A.</first>
				<last>Beck</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>C. P.</first>
				<last>Bidinosti</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Christopher J.</first>
				<last>Henry</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ian</first>
				<last>Stavness</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The development of state-of-the-art convolutional neural networks (CNN) has allowed researchers to perform plant classification tasks previously thought impossible and rely on human judgment. Researchers often develop complex CNN models to achieve better performances, introducing over-parameterization and forcing the model to overfit on a training dataset. The most popular process for evaluating overfitting in a deep learning model is using accuracy and loss curves. Train and loss curves may help understand the performance of a model but do not provide guidance on how the model could be modified to attain better performance. In this article, we analyzed the relation between the features learned by a model and its capacity and showed that a model with higher representational capacity might learn many subtle features that may negatively affect its performance. Next, we showed that the shallow layers of a deep learning model learn more diverse features than the ones learned by the deeper layers. Finally, we propose SSIM cut curve, a new way to select the depth of a CNN model by using the pairwise similarity matrix between the visualization of the features learned at different depths by using Guided Backpropagation. We showed that our proposed method could potentially pave a new way to select a better CNN model.</abstract>
			<url hash="bd6c6b7b">G23-55001</url>
			<doi>10.3389/frai.2022.871162</doi>
			<bibkey>Mostafa-2023-Leveraging</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="56">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Agricultural and Forest Meteorology, Volume 331</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Phenological assessment of transpiration: The stem-temp approach for determining start and end of season</title>
			<author>
				<first>Magali F.</first>
				<last>Nehemy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zoe</first>
				<last>Pierrat</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jason</first>
				<last>Maillet</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Andrew D.</first>
				<last>Richardson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>J.</first>
				<last>Stutz</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bruce</first>
				<last>Johnson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Warren</first>
				<last>Helgason</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Alan</first>
				<last>Barr</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Colin P.</first>
				<last>Laroque</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jeffrey J.</first>
				<last>McDonnell</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Field-based assessment of transpiration phenology in boreal tree species is a significant challenge. Here we develop an objective approach that uses stem radius change and its correlation with sapwood temperature to determine the timing of phenological changes in transpiration in mixed evergreen species. We test the stem-temp approach using a five year stem-radius dataset from black spruce (Picea mariana) and jack pine (Pinus banksiana) trees in Saskatchewan (2016–2020). We further compare transpiration phenological transition dates from this approach with tower-based phenological assessment from green chromatic coordinate derived from phenocam images, eddy-covariance-derived evapotranspiration and carbon uptake, tower-based measurements of solar-induced chlorophyll fluorescence and snowmelt timing. The stem-temp approach identified the start and end of four key transpiration phenological phases: (i) the end of temperature-driven cycles indicating the start of biological activity, (ii) the onset of stem rehydration, (iii) the onset of transpiration, and (iv) the end of transpiration-driven cycles. The proposed method is thus useful for characterizing the timing of changes in transpiration phenology and provides information about distinct processes that cannot be assessed with canopy-level phenological measurements alone.</abstract>
			<url hash="afd9c495">G23-56001</url>
			<pages>109319</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.agrformet.2023.109319</doi>
			<bibkey>Nehemy-2023-Phenological</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="57">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Citizen Science: Theory and Practice, Volume 8, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>Ubiquity Press, Ltd.</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>iWetland: A Community Science Platform for Monitoring Wetland Water Levels</title>
			<author>
				<first>Taylor D.</first>
				<last>North</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Paul A.</first>
				<last>Moore</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Waverley</first>
				<last>Birch</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Chantel E.</first>
				<last>Markle</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hope</first>
				<last>Freeman</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Alex</first>
				<last>Furukawa</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Danielle T.</first>
				<last>Hudson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sophie</first>
				<last>Wilkinson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>J. M.</first>
				<last>Waddington</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>iWetland is a community science wetland water level monitoring platform developed by the McMaster Ecohydrology Lab and tested from 2016 to 2019 in wetlands located east of Georgian Bay, Ontario, Canada. The goal of iWetland is to engage community members in wetland science while collecting data to better understand the spatiotemporal variability in water level patterns of wetlands. We installed 24 iWetland water level monitoring stations in popular hiking and camping areas where visitors can text the water level of the wetland to an online database that automatically collates the data. Here, we share our approach for developing the iWetland community science platform and its importance for monitoring all types of wetland ecosystems. From 2016 through 2019, almost 2,000 individuals recorded more than 2,600 water table measurements. The iWetland platform successfully collected accurate water table data for 24 wetlands. We discuss the successes and shortcomings of the community science platform with respect to data collection, community engagement, and participation. We found that forming mutually beneficial partnerships with community groups paired with strong outreach presence were key to the success of this community science platform. Finally, we recommend that those interested in adopting the iWetland platform in their community partner with community groups, recognize participant contributions, identify accessible sites, and host outreach activities.</abstract>
			<url hash="1765a3f0">G23-57001</url>
			<pages>7</pages>
			<doi>10.5334/cstp.448</doi>
			<bibkey>North-2023-iWetland:</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="58">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Chemosphere, Volume 333</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Understanding common population markers for SARS-CoV-2 RNA normalization in wastewater – A review</title>
			<author>
				<first>Femi Francis</first>
				<last>Oloye</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yuwei</first>
				<last>Xie</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jonathan K.</first>
				<last>Challis</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Oluwabunmi P.</first>
				<last>Femi-Oloye</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Markus</first>
				<last>Brinkmann</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kerry N.</first>
				<last>McPhedran</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Paul D.</first>
				<last>Jones</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mark R.</first>
				<last>Servos</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Wastewater monitoring and epidemiology have seen renewed interest during the recent COVID-19 pandemic. As a result, there is an increasing need to normalize wastewater-derived viral loads in local populations. Chemical tracers, both exogenous and endogenous compounds, have proven to be more stable and reliable for normalization than biological indicators. However, differing instrumentation and extraction methods can make it difficult to compare results. This review examines current extraction and quantification methods for ten common population indicators: creatinine, coprostanol, nicotine, cotinine, sucralose, acesulfame, androstenedione 5-hydroindoleacetic acid (5-HIAA), caffeine, and 1,7-dimethyluric acid. Some wastewater parameters such as ammonia, total nitrogen, total phosphorus, and daily flowrate were also evaluated. The analytical methods included direct injection, dilute and shoot, liquid/liquid, and solid phase extraction (SPE). Creatine, acesulfame, nicotine, 5-HIAA and androstenedione have been analysed by direct injection into LC-MS; however, most authors prefer to include SPE steps to avoid matrix effects. Both LC-MS and GC-MS have been successfully used to quantify coprostanol in wastewater, and the other selected indicators have been quantified successfully with LC-MS. Acidification to stabilize the sample before freezing to maintain the integrity of samples has been reported to be beneficial. However, there are arguments both for and against working at acidic pHs. Wastewater parameters mentioned earlier are quick and easy to quantify, but the data does not always represent the human population effectively. A preference for population indicators originating solely from humans is apparent. This review summarises methods employed for chemical indicators in wastewater, provides a basis for choosing an appropriate extraction and analysis method, and highlights the utility of accurate chemical tracer data for wastewater-based epidemiology.</abstract>
			<url hash="4f06b3a6">G23-58001</url>
			<pages>138682</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.138682</doi>
			<bibkey>Oloye-2023-Understanding</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="59">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Ecosphere, Volume 14, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Blooms and flows: Effects of variable hydrology and management on reservoir water quality</title>
			<author>
				<first>Kristin J.</first>
				<last>Painter</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jason J.</first>
				<last>Venkiteswaran</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Helen M.</first>
				<last>Baulch</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Flow management has the potential to significantly affect ecosystem condition. Shallow lakes in arid regions are especially susceptible to flow management changes, which can have important implications for the formation of cyanobacterial blooms. Here, we reveal water quality shifts associated with changing source water inflow management. Using in situ monitoring data, we studied a seven-year time span during which inflows to a shallow, eutrophic drinking water reservoir transitioned from primarily natural landscape runoff (2014–2015) to managed flows from a larger upstream reservoir (Lake Diefenbaker; 2016–2020) and identified significant changes in cyanobacteria (as phycocyanin) using generalized additive models to classify cyanobacterial bloom formation. We then connected changes in water source with shifts in chemistry and the occurrence of cyanobacterial blooms using principal components analysis. Phycocyanin was greater in years with managed reservoir inflow from a mesotrophic upstream reservoir (2016–2020), but dissolved organic matter (DOM) and specific conductivity, important determinants of drinking water quality, were greatest in years when landscape runoff dominated lake water source (2014–2015). Most notably, despite changing rapidly, it took multiple years for lake water to return to a consistent and reduced level of DOM after managed inflows from the upstream reservoir were resumed, an observation that underscores how resilience may be hindered by weak resistance to change and slow recovery. Environmental flows for water quality are rarely defined, yet we show that trade-offs exist between poor water quality via elevated conductivity and DOM and higher bloom risk, depending on water source. Our work highlights the importance of source water quality, not just quantity, to water security, and our findings have important implications for water managers who must protect ecosystem services while adapting to projected hydroclimatic change.</abstract>
			<url hash="f7bad4c3">G23-59001</url>
			<doi>10.1002/ecs2.4472</doi>
			<bibkey>Painter-2023-Blooms</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="60">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrological Processes, Volume 37, Issue 2</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Spatial and temporal variation in forest transpiration across a forested boreal peatland complex</title>
			<author>
				<first>Nia</first>
				<last>Perron</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jennifer L.</first>
				<last>Baltzer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Oliver</first>
				<last>Sonnentag</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Transpiration is a globally important component of evapotranspiration. Careful upscaling of transpiration from point measurements is thus crucial for quantifying water and energy fluxes. In spatially heterogeneous landscapes common across the boreal biome, upscaled transpiration estimates are difficult to determine due to variation in local environmental conditions (e.g., basal area, soil moisture, permafrost). Here, we sought to determine stand‐level attributes that influence transpiration scalars for a forested boreal peatland complex consisting of sparsely treed wetlands and densely treed permafrost plateaus as land cover types. The objectives were to quantify spatial and temporal variability in stand‐level transpiration, and to identify sources of uncertainty when scaling point measurements to the stand‐level. Using heat ratio method sap flow sensors, we determined sap velocity for black spruce and tamarack for 2‐week periods during peak growing season in 2013, 2017 and 2018. We found greater basal area, drier soils, and the presence of permafrost increased daily sap velocity in individual trees, suggesting that local environmental conditions are important in dictating sap velocity. When sap velocity was scaled to stand‐level transpiration using gridded 20 × 20 m resolution data across the ~10 ha Scotty Creek ForestGEO plot, we observed significant differences in daily plot transpiration among years (0.17–0.30 mm), and across land cover types. Daily transpiration was lowest in grid‐cells with sparsely treed wetlands compared to grid‐cells with well‐drained and densely treed permafrost plateaus, where daily transpiration reached 0.80 mm, or 30% of the daily evapotranspiration. When transpiration scalars (i.e., sap velocity) were not specific to the different land cover types (i.e., permafrost plateaus and wetlands), scaled stand‐level transpiration was overestimated by 42%. To quantify the relative contribution of tree transpiration to ecosystem evapotranspiration, we recommend that sampling designs stratify across local environmental conditions to accurately represent variation associated with land cover types, especially with different hydrological functioning as encountered in rapidly thawing boreal peatland complexes.</abstract>
			<url hash="cd12e199">G23-60001</url>
			<doi>10.1002/hyp.14815</doi>
			<bibkey>Perron-2023-Spatial</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="61">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Science &amp; Technology, Volume 57, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Chemical Society (ACS)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Fluvial Deposition and Land Use Change Control Selenium Occurrence in Mollisols of Cold Region Agroecosystems</title>
			<author>
				<first>Kunfu</first>
				<last>Pi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yiqun</first>
				<last>Gan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Xinlin</first>
				<last>Zhong</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Lei</first>
				<last>Tong</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Weitao</first>
				<last>Chen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Xun</first>
				<last>Wang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yanxin</first>
				<last>Wang</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Mollisols support the most productive agroecosystems in the world. Despite their critical links to food quality and human health, the varying distributions of selenium (Se) species and factors governing Se mobility in the mollisol vadose zone remain elusive. This research reveals that, in northern mollisol agroecosystems, Se hotspots (≥0.32 mg/kg) prevail along the regional river systems draining the Lesser Khingan Mountains, where piedmont Se-rich oil shales are the most probable source of regional Se. While selenate and selenite dominate Se species in the water-soluble and absorbed pools, mollisol organic matter is the major host for Se. Poorly crystalline and crystalline Fe oxides are subordinate in Se retention, hosting inorganic and organic Se at levels comparable to those in the adsorbed pool. The depth-dependent distributions of mollisol Se species for the non-cropland and cropland sites imply a predominance of reduced forms of Se under the mildly acidic and reducing conditions that, in turn, are variably impacted by agricultural land use. These findings therefore highlight that fluvial deposition and land use change together are the main drivers of the spatial variability and speciation of mollisol Se.</abstract>
			<url hash="75ae86fc">G23-61001</url>
			<pages>751-760</pages>
			<doi>10.1021/acs.est.2c03647</doi>
			<bibkey>Pi-2023-Fluvial</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="62">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Water, Volume 15, Issue 2</booktitle>
			<publisher>MDPI AG</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Modelling Transport and Fate of Copper and Nickel across the South Saskatchewan River Using WASP—TOXI</title>
			<author>
				<first>Saurabh</first>
				<last>Prajapati</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Pouya</first>
				<last>Sabokruhie</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Markus</first>
				<last>Brinkmann</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Karl-Erich</first>
				<last>Lindenschmidt</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The South Saskatchewan River (SSR) is one of the most important river systems in Saskatchewan and, arguably, in Canada. Most of the Saskatchewan residents, industries, and powerplants depend on the SSR for their water requirements. An established 1D modelling approach was chosen and coupled with the Hydrologic Engineering Center’s River Analysis System (HEC-RAS). The WASP (Water Quality Analysis Simulation Program) stream transport module, TOXI, is coupled with flow routing for free-flow streams, ponded segments, and backwater reaches and is capable of calculating the flow of water, sediment, and dissolved constituents across branched and ponded segments. Copper and nickel were chosen as two metals with predominantly anthropogenic (agriculture, mining, and municipal and industrial waste management) and geogenic (natural weathering and erosion) sources, respectively. Analysis was carried out at ten different sites along the South Saskatchewan River, both upstream and downstream of the City of Saskatoon, in the years 2020 and 2021. Model performance was evaluated by comparing model predictions with concentrations of copper and nickel measured in a previously published study. The model performed well in estimating the concentrations of copper and nickel in water samples and worked reasonably well for sediment samples. The model underestimated the concentration values at certain segments in both water and sediment samples. In order to calibrate the model more accurately, extra diffusive contaminant loads were added. While several default parameter values had to be used due to the unavailability of primary historical data, our study demonstrates the predictive power of combining WASP—TOXI and HEC-RAS models for the prediction of contaminant loading. Future studies, including those on the impacts of global climate change on water quality on the Canadian prairies, will benefit from this proof-of-concept study.</abstract>
			<url hash="671b2912">G23-62001</url>
			<pages>265</pages>
			<doi>10.3390/w15020265</doi>
			<bibkey>Prajapati-2023-Modelling</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="63">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Cold Regions Science and Technology, Volume 210</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>An analysis of ice growth and temperature dynamics in two Canadian subarctic lakes</title>
			<author>
				<first>Arash</first>
				<last>Rafat</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Homa Kheyrollah</first>
				<last>Pour</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Christopher</first>
				<last>Spence</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michael</first>
				<last>Palmer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Alex</first>
				<last>MacLean</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The seasonal dynamics of freshwater lake ice and its interactions with air and snow are studied in two small subarctic lakes with comparable surface areas but contrasting depths (4.3 versus 91 m). Two, 2.9 m long thermistor chain sensors (Snow and Ice Mass Balance Apparatuses), were used to remotely measure air, snow, ice, and water temperatures every 15-min between December 2021 and March 2022. Results showed that freeze-up occurred later in the deeper lake (Ryan Lake) and earlier in the shallow lake (Landing Lake). Ice growth was significantly faster in Ryan Lake than in Landing Lake, due to cold water temperatures (mean (Tw¯) =0.65 to 0.96°C) persisting beneath the ice. In Landing Lake, basal ice growth was hindered because of warm water temperatures (Tw¯=1.5 to 2.1°C) caused by heat released from lake sediments. Variability in air temperatures at both lakes had significant influences on the thermal regimes of ice and snow, particularly in Ryan Lake, where ice temperatures were more sensitive to rapid changes in air temperatures. This finding suggests that conductive heat transfer through the air-water continuum may be more sensitive to variability in air temperatures in deeper lakes with colder water temperatures than in shallow lakes with warmer water temperatures, if snow depths and densities are comparable. This study highlights the significance of lake morphology and rapid air temperature variability on influencing ice growth processes. Conclusions drawn aim to improve the representation of ice growth processes in regional and global climate models, and to improve ice safety for northern communities.</abstract>
			<url hash="dfa74e77">G23-63001</url>
			<pages>103808</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.coldregions.2023.103808</doi>
			<bibkey>Rafat-2023-An</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="64">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Earth and Space Science, Volume 10, Issue 4</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Geophysical Union (AGU)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Precipitation Bias Correction: A Novel Semi‐parametric Quantile Mapping Method</title>
			<author>
				<first>Chandra Rupa</first>
				<last>Rajulapati</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>S.</first>
				<last>Papalexiou</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Bias correction methods are used to adjust simulations from global and regional climate models to use them in informed decision-making. Here we introduce a semi-parametric quantile mapping (SPQM) method to bias-correct daily precipitation. This method uses a parametric probability distribution to describe observations and an empirical distribution for simulations. Bias-correction techniques typically adjust the bias between observation and historical simulations to correct projections. The SPQM however corrects simulations based only on observations assuming the detrended simulations have the same distribution as the observations. Thus, the bias-corrected simulations preserve the climate change signal, including changes in the magnitude and probability dry, and guarantee a smooth transition from observations to future simulations. The results are compared with popular quantile mapping techniques, that is, the quantile delta mapping (QDM) and the statistical transformation of the CDF using splines (SSPLINE). The SPQM performed well in reproducing the observed statistics, marginal distribution, and wet and dry spells. Comparatively, it performed at least equally well as the QDM and SSPLINE, specifically in reproducing observed wet spells and extreme quantiles. The method is further tested in a basin-scale region. The spatial variability and statistics of the observed precipitation are reproduced well in the bias-corrected simulations. Overall, the SPQM is easy to apply, yet robust in bias-correcting daily precipitation simulations.</abstract>
			<url hash="427076ce">G23-64001</url>
			<doi>10.1029/2023ea002823</doi>
			<bibkey>Rajulapati-2023-Precipitation</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="65">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Chemosphere, Volume 325</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Effects of freeze-thaw cycles on methanogenic hydrocarbon degradation: Experiment and modeling</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mehdi</first>
				<last>Ramezanzadeh</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stephanie</first>
				<last>Slowinski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fereidoun</first>
				<last>Rezanezhad</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kathleen</first>
				<last>Murr</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Christina</first>
				<last>Lam</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Christina M.</first>
				<last>Smeaton</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Clément</first>
				<last>Alibert</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Marianne</first>
				<last>Vandergriendt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Cold regions are warming much faster than the global average, resulting in more frequent and intense freeze-thaw cycles (FTCs) in soils. In hydrocarbon-contaminated soils, FTCs modify the biogeochemical and physical processes controlling petroleum hydrocarbon (PHC) biodegradation and the associated generation of methane (CH4) and carbon dioxide (CO2). Thus, understanding the effects of FTCs on the biodegradation of PHCs is critical for environmental risk assessment and the design of remediation strategies for contaminated soils in cold regions. In this study, we developed a diffusion-reaction model that accounts for the effects of FTCs on toluene biodegradation, including methanogenic biodegradation. The model is verified against data generated in a 215 day-long batch experiment with soil collected from a PHC contaminated site in Ontario, Canada. The fully saturated soil incubations with six different treatments were exposed to successive 4-week FTCs, with temperatures oscillating between −10 °C and +15 °C, under anoxic conditions to stimulate methanogenic biodegradation. We measured the headspace concentrations and 13C isotope compositions of CH4 and CO2 and analyzed the porewater for pH, acetate, dissolved organic and inorganic carbon, and toluene. The numerical model represents solute diffusion, volatilization, sorption, as well as a reaction network of 13 biogeochemical processes. The model successfully simulates the soil porewater and headspace concentration time series data by representing the temperature dependencies of microbial reaction and gas diffusion rates during FTCs. According to the model results, the observed increases in the headspace concentrations of CH4 and CO2 by 87% and 136%, respectively, following toluene addition are explained by toluene fermentation and subsequent methanogenesis reactions. The experiment and the numerical simulation show that methanogenic degradation is the primary toluene attenuation mechanism under the electron acceptor-limited conditions experienced by the soil samples, representing 74% of the attenuation, with sorption contributing to 11%, and evaporation contributing to 15%. Also, the model-predicted contribution of acetate-based methanogenesis to total produced CH4 agrees with that derived from the 13C isotope data. The freezing-induced soil matrix organic carbon release is considered as an important process causing DOC increase following each freezing period according to the calculations of carbon balance and SUVA index. The simulation results of a no FTC scenario indicate that, in the absence of FTCs, CO2 and CH4 generation would decrease by 29% and 26%, respectively, and that toluene would be biodegraded 23% faster than in the FTC scenario. Because our modeling approach represents the dominant processes controlling PHC biodegradation and the associated CH4 and CO2 fluxes, it can be used to analyze the sensitivity of these processes to FTC frequency and duration driven by temperature fluctuations.</abstract>
			<url hash="facc11ab">G23-65001</url>
			<pages>138405</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.138405</doi>
			<bibkey>Ramezanzadeh-2023-Effects</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="66">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Microorganisms, Volume 11, Issue 2</booktitle>
			<publisher>MDPI AG</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Aqueous Geochemical Controls on the Sestonic Microbial Community in Lakes Michigan and Superior</title>
			<author>
				<first>Asha</first>
				<last>Rani</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ravi</first>
				<last>Ranjan</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Solidea</first>
				<last>Bonina</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mahsa</first>
				<last>Izadmehr</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>An</first>
				<last>Li</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Neil C.</first>
				<last>Sturchio</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Karl J.</first>
				<last>Rockne</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Despite being the largest freshwater lake system in the world, relatively little is known about the sestonic microbial community structure in the Laurentian Great Lakes. The goal of this research was to better understand this ecosystem using high-throughput sequencing of microbial communities as a function of water depth at six locations in the westernmost Great Lakes of Superior and Michigan. The water column was characterized by gradients in temperature, dissolved oxygen (DO), pH, and other physicochemical parameters with depth. Mean nitrate concentrations were 32 μmol/L, with only slight variation within and between the lakes, and with depth. Mean available phosphorus was 0.07 μmol/L, resulting in relatively large N:P ratios (97:1) indicative of P limitation. Abundances of the phyla Actinobacteria, Bacteroidetes, Cyanobacteria, Thaumarchaeota, and Verrucomicrobia differed significantly among the Lakes. Candidatus Nitrosopumilus was present in greater abundance in Lake Superior compared to Lake Michigan, suggesting the importance of ammonia-oxidating archaea in water column N cycling in Lake Superior. The Shannon diversity index was negatively correlated with pH, temperature, and salinity, and positively correlated with DO, latitude, and N2 saturation. Results of this study suggest that DO, pH, temperature, and salinity were major drivers shaping the community composition in the Great Lakes.</abstract>
			<url hash="e879be45">G23-66001</url>
			<pages>504</pages>
			<doi>10.3390/microorganisms11020504</doi>
			<bibkey>Rani-2023-Aqueous</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="67">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Science, Volume 379, Issue 6627</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Global glacier change in the 21st century: Every increase in temperature matters</title>
			<author>
				<first>David</first>
				<last>Rounce</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Regine</first>
				<last>Hock</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fabien</first>
				<last>Maussion</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Romain</first>
				<last>Hugonnet</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>William</first>
				<last>Kochtitzky</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matthias</first>
				<last>Huss</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Etienne</first>
				<last>Berthier</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Douglas</first>
				<last>Brinkerhoff</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Loris</first>
				<last>Compagno</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Luke</first>
				<last>Copland</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Daniel</first>
				<last>Farinotti</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brian</first>
				<last>Menounos</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Robert</first>
				<last>McNabb</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Glacier mass loss affects sea level rise, water resources, and natural hazards. We present global glacier projections, excluding the ice sheets, for shared socioeconomic pathways calibrated with data for each glacier. Glaciers are projected to lose 26 ± 6% (+1.5°C) to 41 ± 11% (+4°C) of their mass by 2100, relative to 2015, for global temperature change scenarios. This corresponds to 90 ± 26 to 154 ± 44 millimeters sea level equivalent and will cause 49 ± 9 to 83 ± 7% of glaciers to disappear. Mass loss is linearly related to temperature increase and thus reductions in temperature increase reduce mass loss. Based on climate pledges from the Conference of the Parties (COP26), global mean temperature is projected to increase by +2.7°C, which would lead to a sea level contribution of 115 ± 40 millimeters and cause widespread deglaciation in most mid-latitude regions by 2100.</abstract>
			<url hash="50c5d920">G23-67001</url>
			<pages>78-83</pages>
			<doi>10.1126/science.abo1324</doi>
			<bibkey>Rounce-2023-Global</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="68">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Frontiers in Microbiology, Volume 14</booktitle>
			<publisher>Frontiers Media SA</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Realizing the value in “non-standard” parts of the qPCR standard curve by integrating fundamentals of quantitative microbiology</title>
			<author>
				<first>Philip J.</first>
				<last>Schmidt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nicole</first>
				<last>Acosta</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Alex H. S.</first>
				<last>Chik</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Patrick M.</first>
				<last>D'Aoust</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Robert</first>
				<last>Delatolla</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hadi A.</first>
				<last>Dhiyebi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Melissa B.</first>
				<last>Glier</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Casey R.J.</first>
				<last>Hubert</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jennifer</first>
				<last>Kopetzky</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Chand S.</first>
				<last>Mangat</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Xiaoli</first>
				<last>Pang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Shelley</first>
				<last>Peterson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Natalie</first>
				<last>Prystajecky</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yuanyuan</first>
				<last>Qiu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mark R.</first>
				<last>Servos</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Monica B.</first>
				<last>Emelko</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR), commonly known as quantitative PCR (qPCR), is increasingly common in environmental microbiology applications. During the COVID-19 pandemic, qPCR combined with reverse transcription (RT-qPCR) has been used to detect and quantify SARS-CoV-2 in clinical diagnoses and wastewater monitoring of local trends. Estimation of concentrations using qPCR often features a log-linear standard curve model calibrating quantification cycle (Cq) values obtained from underlying fluorescence measurements to standard concentrations. This process works well at high concentrations within a linear dynamic range but has diminishing reliability at low concentrations because it cannot explain &quot;non-standard&quot; data such as Cq values reflecting increasing variability at low concentrations or non-detects that do not yield Cq values at all. Here, fundamental probabilistic modeling concepts from classical quantitative microbiology were integrated into standard curve modeling approaches by reflecting well-understood mechanisms for random error in microbial data. This work showed that data diverging from the log-linear regression model at low concentrations as well as non-detects can be seamlessly integrated into enhanced standard curve analysis. The newly developed model provides improved representation of standard curve data at low concentrations while converging asymptotically upon conventional log-linear regression at high concentrations and adding no fitting parameters. Such modeling facilitates exploration of the effects of various random error mechanisms in experiments generating standard curve data, enables quantification of uncertainty in standard curve parameters, and is an important step toward quantifying uncertainty in qPCR-based concentration estimates. Improving understanding of the random error in qPCR data and standard curve modeling is especially important when low concentrations are of particular interest and inappropriate analysis can unduly affect interpretation, conclusions regarding lab performance, reported concentration estimates, and associated decision-making.</abstract>
			<url hash="08a6c976">G23-68001</url>
			<doi>10.3389/fmicb.2023.1048661</doi>
			<bibkey>Schmidt-2023-Realizing</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="69">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Water Resources and Economics, Volume 41</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Optimizing agricultural cropping patterns under irrigation water use restrictions due to environmental flow requirements and climate change</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mahdi</first>
				<last>Sedighkia</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bithin</first>
				<last>Datta</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Saman</first>
				<last>Razavi</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>This study proposes a reservoir operation optimization framework to maximize the regional agricultural profit under the constraints of downstream environmental flow requirements and climate change. Three climate change models—CanESM2, MIROC5, and NorESM1-M—and the soil and water assessment tool (SWAT) were used to simulate the reservoir inflow in future periods under uncertainty. Minimum and ideal environmental flow regimes were embedded in the structure of the reservoir operation model to optimize the environmental flow needs and water supply and assess their tradeoffs. Cropping pattern optimization was used to maximize farmer profit. Particle swarm optimization was applied in the optimization processes. The method was applied to a case study in the Tajan River basin, Iran, with the results showing the environmental flow regime considerably reduces irrigation supply and has significant impacts on farmer profits. The results showed that cropping pattern optimization was not an effective strategy to mitigate the economic impacts of climate change under environmental flow constraints, but this assessment may not be generalized to other areas. Uncertainties related to the climate change models are a notable weakness of the approach and should be considered in future studies.</abstract>
			<url hash="b01aae13">G23-69001</url>
			<pages>100216</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.wre.2023.100216</doi>
			<bibkey>Sedighkia-2023-Optimizing</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="70">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Irrigation Science, Volume 41, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Optimal agricultural plan for minimizing ecological impacts on river ecosystems</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mahdi</first>
				<last>Sedighkia</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zeynab</first>
				<last>Fathi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Saman</first>
				<last>Razavi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Asghar</first>
				<last>Abdoli</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="f072c829">G23-70001</url>
			<pages>93-106</pages>
			<doi>10.1007/s00271-022-00834-7</doi>
			<bibkey>Sedighkia-2023-Optimal</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="71">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrobiologia</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Monod parameterization and competition at low iron among freshwater cyanobacteria and chlorophytes</title>
			<author>
				<first>Purnank</first>
				<last>Shah</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Shelley K.</first>
				<last>McCabe</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jason J.</first>
				<last>Venkiteswaran</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Lewis A.</first>
				<last>Molot</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sherry L.</first>
				<last>Schiff</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="48ceaf4c">G23-71001</url>
			<doi>10.1007/s10750-023-05150-5</doi>
			<bibkey>Shah-2023-Monod</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="72">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Environmental Pollution, Volume 318</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Acute exposure to microcystins affects hypothalamic-pituitary axes of male rats</title>
			<author>
				<first>Ting</first>
				<last>Shi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Linlin</first>
				<last>Xu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Liang</first>
				<last>Chen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jun</first>
				<last>He</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yeke</first>
				<last>Wang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Feng</first>
				<last>Chen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yang</first>
				<last>Chen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John P.</first>
				<last>Giesy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yu-Ting</first>
				<last>Wang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Qianhui</first>
				<last>Wu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Wenli</first>
				<last>Xu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jun</first>
				<last>Chen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ping</first>
				<last>Xie</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Microcystins (MCs) produced by some cyanobacteria can cause toxicity in animals and humans. In recent years, growing evidence suggests that MCs can act as endocrine disruptors. This research systematically investigated effects of microcystin-LR (MC-LR) on endocrine organs, biosynthesis of hormones and positive/negative feedback of the endocrine system in rats. Male, Sprague-Dawley rats were acutely administrated MC-LR by a single intraperitoneal injection at doses of 45, 67.5 or 90 μg MC-LR/kg body mass (bm), and then euthanized 24 h after exposure. In exposed rats, histological damage of hypothalamus, pituitary, adrenal, testis and thyroid were observed. Serum concentrations of corticotropin-releasing hormone (CRH), adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) and corticosterone (CORT), expressions of genes and proteins for biosynthesis of hormones were lesser, which indicated an overall suppression of the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis. Along the hypothalamus-pituitary-gonadal (HPG) axis, lesser concentrations of gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) and testosterone (T), but greater concentrations of luteinizing hormone (LH), follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and estradiol (E2) were observed. Except for greater transcription of cyp19a1 in testes, transcriptions of genes and proteins for T and E2 biosynthesis along the HPG axis were lesser. As for the hypothalamus-pituitary-thyroid (HPT) axis, after MCs treatment, greater concentrations of thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH), but lesser concentrations of free tri-iodothyronine (fT3) were observed in serum. Concentrations of free tetra-iodothyronine (fT4) were greater in rats dosed with 45 μg MCs/kg, bm, but lesser in rats dosed with 67.5 or 90 μg MCs/kg, bm. Transcripts of genes for biosynthesis of hormones and receptors along the HPT axis and expressions of proteins for biosynthesis of tetra-iodothyronine (T4) and tri-iodothyronine (T3) in thyroid were significantly altered. Cross-talk among the HPA, HPG and HPT axes probably occurred. It was concluded that MCs caused an imbalance of positive and negative feedback of hormonal regulatory axes, blocked biosynthesis of key hormones and exhibited endocrine-disrupting effects.</abstract>
			<url hash="5a7b00a2">G23-72001</url>
			<pages>120843</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.envpol.2022.120843</doi>
			<bibkey>Shi-2023-Acute</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="73">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>International Journal of Climatology</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Spatiotemporal distribution and trend analyses of atmospheric rivers affecting British Columbia's Nechako Watershed</title>
			<author>
				<first>Bruno W. S.</first>
				<last>Sobral</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stephen J.</first>
				<last>Déry</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Research and shared interest in atmospheric rivers (ARs) have increased significantly in recent years, alongside technological improvements that allow better comprehension of these storms. The Nechako River Basin (NRB) in British Columbia, Canada, is significantly affected by ARs originating in the Pacific Ocean. This work analyses the frequency, intensity, duration and trends of ARs in two regions (South and North) near the NRB. Analyses are based on data provided by an updated AR catalogue. The AR catalogue is matched on a daily scale to an adaptation of the AR scale to compile so‐called AR‐Days (ARDs). In the South region, ARDs exhibit stronger associations with hydroclimatic variables total precipitation, rain, snow and snow depth water equivalent (SWE). The Mann–Kendall (MK) trend test was applied to 364 time series created by combining the two closest AR‐monitored regions to the NRB with the annual and seasonal scales of climate data and the adapted AR scale (ARD0‐ARD5). Results show higher AR frequency of mainly beneficial ARDs during fall and a significant reduction of ARD1‐ARD3 in both analysed regions. Rain and total precipitation related to ARD2‐ARD3 also present significant decreasing trends for most sub‐basins of the NRB. The MK test shows a shift in water contribution from total precipitation and rainfall linked to more potentially dangerous ARDs to short‐duration, beneficial ARDs (ARD0). Rain from non‐AR‐related meteorological systems presents an increasing trend for the Upper Nechako sub‐basin, where the Nechako Reservoir is located. Trends are mainly for AR‐related total precipitation and rainfall, and in the northern part of the NRB, results point to the increase of AR‐related SWE.</abstract>
			<url hash="e2c767c7">G23-73001</url>
			<doi>10.1002/joc.8230</doi>
			<bibkey>Sobral-2023-Spatiotemporal</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="74">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Ecological Economics, Volume 205</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Disparities in economic values for nature-based activities in Canada</title>
			<author>
				<first>Danielle S.</first>
				<last>Spence</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Corinne J.</first>
				<last>Schuster-Wallace</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Patrick</first>
				<last>Lloyd-Smith</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Differential impacts of policies or changes in environmental conditions on people is a growing area of interest to decision-makers, yet remains an often neglected area of study for the environmental valuation literature. Using data from a large national survey of over 24,000 people conducted in Canada, this paper implements a latent class Kuhn-Tucker recreation demand model to assess differences in preferences and values for nature-based activities. Preferences are disaggregated by self-reported Indigeneity, immigration status, and gender. We find that Indigenous people receive 63% greater benefits from participating in nature-based activities compared to non-Indigenous people living in Canada. Immigrants have the lowest participation in, and benefits associated with, nature-based activities. Similarly, women receive 21% lesser benefits associated with nature-based activities when compared to men. These results demonstrate that Indigenous peoples may be more vulnerable to adverse impacts on nature-based activities such as land-use changes, climate change, and government policies. The study also highlights the importance of disaggregated data and incorporating aspects of identity in the ecosystem service literature towards more equitable decision-making and reconciliation.</abstract>
			<url hash="7f105f7e">G23-74001</url>
			<pages>107724</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.ecolecon.2022.107724</doi>
			<bibkey>Spence-2023-Disparities</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="75">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Frontiers in Sustainable Food Systems, Volume 6</booktitle>
			<publisher>Frontiers Media SA</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Learning from the past to deal with the future: Using different knowledges to ensure food security in the Tsá Tué biosphere reserve (Northwest Territories, Canada)</title>
			<author>
				<first>Andrew</first>
				<last>Spring</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Michael</first>
				<last>Neyelle</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Walter</first>
				<last>Bezha</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Deborah</first>
				<last>Simmons</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Alison</first>
				<last>Blay-Palmer</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The community of Délı̨nę, located in the UNESCO Tsá Tué Biosphere Reserve, is experiencing the impacts of climate change on the lands surrounding Great Bear Lake, in Northwest Territories, Canada. These impacts are limiting the community's ability to access the land to support their food system, which depends on harvesting traditional foods. This article details a participatory action research approach, driven by the community, that used on-the-land activities, workshops, community meetings and interviews to develop a community food security action plan to deal with the uncertainties of a changing climate on the food system. Data was analyzed using the Community Capitals Framework (CCF) to describe the complex nature of the community's food system in terms of available or depleting capitals, as well as how the impacts of climate change affect these capitals, and the needs identified by the community to aid in adaptation. For Délı̨nę, the theme of self-sufficiency emerged out of concerns that climate change is negatively impacting supplies from the south and that building and maintaining both social and cultural capital are key to achieving food security in an uncertain future. Learning from the past and sharing Traditional Knowledge 1 was a key element of food security planning. However, other types of knowledge, such as research and monitoring of the health of the land, and building capacity of the community through training, were important aspects of adaptation planning in the community. This knowledge, in its many forms, may assist the community in determining its own direction for achieving food security, and offers a glimpse into food sovereignty in Northern regions.</abstract>
			<url hash="c7ac381b">G23-75001</url>
			<doi>10.3389/fsufs.2022.984290</doi>
			<bibkey>Spring-2023-Learning</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="76">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Geophysical Research: Atmospheres, Volume 128, Issue 6</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Geophysical Union (AGU)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>The Occurrence of Near‐0°C Surface Air Temperatures in the Current and Pseudo‐Global Warming Future Over Southern Canada</title>
			<author>
				<first>Ronald E.</first>
				<last>Stewart</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Z.</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Julie M.</first>
				<last>Thériault</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>C. J.</first>
				<last>Ruman</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Temperatures near 0°C represent a critical threshold for many environmental processes and socio‐economic activities. This study examines surface air temperatures ( T ) near 0°C (−2°C ≤ T ≤ 2°C) across much of southern Canada over a 13 year period (October 2000–September 2013). It utilized hourly data from 39 weather stations and from 4‐km resolution Weather Research and Forecasting model simulations that were both a retrospective simulation as well as a pseudo‐global warming simulation applicable near the end of the 21st century. Average annual occurrences of near‐0°C conditions increase by a relatively small amount of 5.1% from 985 hr in the current climate to 1,035 hr within the future one. Near‐0°C occurrences with precipitation vary from &lt;5% to approximately 50% of these values. Near‐0°C occurrences are sometimes higher than values of neighboring temperatures. These near‐0°C peaks in temperature distributions can occur in both the current and future climate, in only one, or in neither. Only 4.3% of southern Canada is not associated with a near‐0°C peak and 65.8% is associated with a near‐0°C peak in both climates. It is inferred that latent heat exchanges from the melting and freezing of, for example, precipitation and the snowpack contribute significantly to some of these findings.</abstract>
			<url hash="d51997f5">G23-76001</url>
			<doi>10.1029/2022jd037981</doi>
			<bibkey>Stewart-2023-The</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="77">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Atmosphere, Volume 14, Issue 2</booktitle>
			<publisher>MDPI AG</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Adhering Solid Precipitation in the Current and Pseudo-Global Warming Future Climate over the Canadian Provinces of Manitoba and Saskatchewan</title>
			<author>
				<first>Ronald E.</first>
				<last>Stewart</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zhuo</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Dylan</first>
				<last>Painchaud-Niemi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John</first>
				<last>Hanesiak</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Julie M.</first>
				<last>Thériault</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Solid precipitation falling near 0 °C, mainly snow, can adhere to surface features and produce major impacts. This study is concerned with characterizing this precipitation over the Canadian Prairie provinces of Manitoba and Saskatchewan in the current (2000–2013) and pseudo-global warming future climate, with an average 5.9 °C temperature increase, through the use of high resolution (4 km) model simulations. On average, simulations in the current climate suggest that this precipitation occurs within 11 events per year, lasting 33.6 h in total and producing 27.5 mm melted equivalent, but there are wide spatial variations that are partly due to enhancements arising from its relatively low terrain. Within the warmer climate, average values generally increase, and spatial patterns shift somewhat. This precipitation consists of four categories covering its occurrence just below and just above a wet-bulb temperature of 0 °C, and with or without liquid precipitation. It generally peaks in March or April, as well as in October, and these peaks move towards mid-winter by approximately one month within the warmer climate. Storms producing this precipitation generally produce winds with a northerly component during or shortly after the precipitation; these winds contribute to further damage. Overall, this study has determined the features of and expected changes to adhering precipitation across this region.</abstract>
			<url hash="6da5f090">G23-77001</url>
			<pages>396</pages>
			<doi>10.3390/atmos14020396</doi>
			<bibkey>Stewart-2023-Adhering</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="78">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Water Resources Research, Volume 58, Issue 12</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Geophysical Union (AGU)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Snow Level From Post‐Processing of Atmospheric Model Improves Snowfall Estimate and Snowpack Prediction in Mountains</title>
			<author>
				<first>Vincent</first>
				<last>Vionnet</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>M.</first>
				<last>Verville</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Vincent</first>
				<last>Fortin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Melinda M.</first>
				<last>Brugman</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Maria</first>
				<last>Abrahamowicz</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>François</first>
				<last>Lemay</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Julie M.</first>
				<last>Thériault</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matthieu</first>
				<last>Lafaysse</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jason A.</first>
				<last>Milbrandt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Vincent</first>
				<last>Vionnet</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>M.</first>
				<last>Verville</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Vincent</first>
				<last>Fortin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Melinda M.</first>
				<last>Brugman</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Maria</first>
				<last>Abrahamowicz</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>François</first>
				<last>Lemay</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Julie M.</first>
				<last>Thériault</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matthieu</first>
				<last>Lafaysse</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jason A.</first>
				<last>Milbrandt</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>In mountains, the precipitation phase greatly varies in space and time and affects the evolution of the snow cover. Snowpack models usually rely on precipitation-phase partitioning methods (PPMs) that use near-surface variables. These PPMs ignore conditions above the surface thus limiting their ability to predict the precipitation phase at the surface. In this study, the impact on snowpack simulations of atmospheric-based PPMs, incorporating upper atmospheric information, is tested using the snowpack scheme Crocus. Crocus is run at 2.5-km grid spacing over the mountains of southwestern Canada and northwestern United States and is driven by meteorological fields from an atmospheric model at the same resolution. Two atmospheric-based PPMs were considered from the atmospheric model: the output from a detailed microphysics scheme and a post-processing algorithm determining the snow level and the associated precipitation phase. Two ground-based PPMs were also included as lower and upper benchmarks: a single air temperature threshold at 0°C and a PPM using wet-bulb temperature. Compared to the upper benchmark, the snow-level based PPM improved the estimation of snowfall occurrence by 5% and the simulation of snow water equivalent (SWE) by 9% during the snow melting season. In contrast, due to missing processes, the microphysics scheme decreased performances in phase estimate and SWE simulations compared to the upper benchmark. These results highlight the need for detailed evaluation of the precipitation phase from atmospheric models and the benefit for mountain snow hydrology of the post-processed snow level. The limitations to drive snowpack models at slope scale are also discussed.</abstract>
			<url hash="35c6e0c6">G23-78001</url>
			<doi>10.1029/2021wr031778</doi>
			<bibkey>Vionnet-2023-Snow</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="79">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Global Change Biology, Volume 29, Issue 8</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Modeled production, oxidation, and transport processes of wetland methane emissions in temperate, boreal, and Arctic regions</title>
			<author>
				<first>Masahito</first>
				<last>Ueyama</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sara</first>
				<last>Knox</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kyle</first>
				<last>Delwiche</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sheel</first>
				<last>Bansal</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>William J.</first>
				<last>Riley</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Dennis</first>
				<last>Baldocchi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Takashi</first>
				<last>Hirano</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Gavin</first>
				<last>McNicol</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>K. V.</first>
				<last>Schafer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Lisamarie</first>
				<last>Windham-Myers</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Benjamin</first>
				<last>Poulter</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Robert B.</first>
				<last>Jackson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kuang-Yu</first>
				<last>Chang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jiquen</first>
				<last>Chen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Housen</first>
				<last>Chu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ankur R.</first>
				<last>Desai</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Sébastien</first>
				<last>Gogo</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hiroyasu</first>
				<last>Iwata</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Minseok</first>
				<last>Kang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ivan</first>
				<last>Mammarella</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matthias</first>
				<last>Peichl</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Oliver</first>
				<last>Sonnentag</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Eeva-Stiina</first>
				<last>Tuittila</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Youngryel</first>
				<last>Ryu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Eugénie S.</first>
				<last>Euskirchen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mathias</first>
				<last>Göckede</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Adrien</first>
				<last>Jacotot</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mats</first>
				<last>Nilsson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Torsten</first>
				<last>Sachs</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Wetlands are the largest natural source of methane (CH4 ) to the atmosphere. The eddy covariance method provides robust measurements of net ecosystem exchange of CH4 , but interpreting its spatiotemporal variations is challenging due to the co-occurrence of CH4 production, oxidation, and transport dynamics. Here, we estimate these three processes using a data-model fusion approach across 25 wetlands in temperate, boreal, and Arctic regions. Our data-constrained model-iPEACE-reasonably reproduced CH4 emissions at 19 of the 25 sites with normalized root mean square error of 0.59, correlation coefficient of 0.82, and normalized standard deviation of 0.87. Among the three processes, CH4 production appeared to be the most important process, followed by oxidation in explaining inter-site variations in CH4 emissions. Based on a sensitivity analysis, CH4 emissions were generally more sensitive to decreased water table than to increased gross primary productivity or soil temperature. For periods with leaf area index (LAI) of ≥20% of its annual peak, plant-mediated transport appeared to be the major pathway for CH4 transport. Contributions from ebullition and diffusion were relatively high during low LAI (&lt;20%) periods. The lag time between CH4 production and CH4 emissions tended to be short in fen sites (3 ± 2 days) and long in bog sites (13 ± 10 days). Based on a principal component analysis, we found that parameters for CH4 production, plant-mediated transport, and diffusion through water explained 77% of the variance in the parameters across the 19 sites, highlighting the importance of these parameters for predicting wetland CH4 emissions across biomes. These processes and associated parameters for CH4 emissions among and within the wetlands provide useful insights for interpreting observed net CH4 fluxes, estimating sensitivities to biophysical variables, and modeling global CH4 fluxes.</abstract>
			<url hash="8d7a87a3">G23-79001</url>
			<pages>2313-2334</pages>
			<doi>10.1111/gcb.16594</doi>
			<bibkey>Ueyama-2023-Modeled</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="80">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Nature Climate Change</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Arctic soil methane sink increases with drier conditions and higher ecosystem respiration</title>
			<author>
				<first>Carolina</first>
				<last>Voigt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Anna-Maria</first>
				<last>Virkkala</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Gabriel</first>
				<last>Gosselin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kathryn A.</first>
				<last>Bennett</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>T. Andrew</first>
				<last>Black</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matteo</first>
				<last>Detto</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Charles</first>
				<last>Chevrier-Dion</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Georg</first>
				<last>Guggenberger</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Wasi</first>
				<last>Hashmi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Leonie</first>
				<last>Kohl</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Dan</first>
				<last>Kou</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Charlotte</first>
				<last>Marquis</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philip</first>
				<last>Marsh</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Maija E.</first>
				<last>Marushchak</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zoran</first>
				<last>Nesic</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hannu</first>
				<last>Nykänen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Taija</first>
				<last>Saarela</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Leopold</first>
				<last>Sauheitl</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Branden</first>
				<last>Walker</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Niels</first>
				<last>Weiss</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Evan J.</first>
				<last>Wilcox</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Oliver</first>
				<last>Sonnentag</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Arctic wetlands are known methane (CH 4 ) emitters but recent studies suggest that the Arctic CH 4 sink strength may be underestimated. Here we explore the capacity of well-drained Arctic soils to consume atmospheric CH 4 using &gt;40,000 hourly flux observations and spatially distributed flux measurements from 4 sites and 14 surface types. While consumption of atmospheric CH 4 occurred at all sites at rates of 0.092 ± 0.011 mgCH 4 m −2 h −1 (mean ± s.e.), CH 4 uptake displayed distinct diel and seasonal patterns reflecting ecosystem respiration. Combining in situ flux data with laboratory investigations and a machine learning approach, we find biotic drivers to be highly important. Soil moisture outweighed temperature as an abiotic control and higher CH 4 uptake was linked to increased availability of labile carbon. Our findings imply that soil drying and enhanced nutrient supply will promote CH 4 uptake by Arctic soils, providing a negative feedback to global climate change.</abstract>
			<url hash="72225ff8">G23-80001</url>
			<doi>10.1038/s41558-023-01785-3</doi>
			<bibkey>Voigt-2023-Arctic</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="81">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Ecohydrology, Volume 16, Issue 3</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Effects of microforms on the evaporation of peat‐bryophyte‐litter column in a montane peatland in Canadian Rocky Mountain</title>
			<author>
				<first>Yi</first>
				<last>Wang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Richard M.</first>
				<last>Petrone</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Peatland microtopography contains hummocks (local high points) and hollows (local low points). Little is known about how the evaporation of peat (P), peat-bryophyte (BP), peat-litter (LP) and peat-bryophyte-litter (LBP) columns varies with peatland microforms. That is, whether there are fine-scale variations in peatland evaporation, and if they are critical when being upscaled to the entire peatland ecosystem is yet to be answered. This study found that evaporation was significantly affected by cover type (P, BP, LP or LBP) and the interaction effect of the cover type and microform, based on the field evaporation experiments in a montane peatland in the Canadian Rocky Mountains, during the growing season of 2021. Mean daily evaporation of P-Hummock and P-Hollow is 14.16 and 11.76 g day−1, respectively; BP-Hummock and BP-Hollow is 9.57 and 14.38 g day−1, respectively; LBP-Hummock and LBP-Hollow is 9.44 and 9.91 g day−1, respectively; and evaporation of LP-Hummock and LP-Hollow is 5.68 and 7.64 g day−1, respectively. Peatland microform indirectly affected evaporation through interactions with cover type, modifying the vertical profile of soil temperature and changing key environmental drivers of evaporation. Moreover, the ability of two widely used models in modelling the spatial variation of peatland evaporation was also tested. It was found that Penman–Monteith (P–M) model and the bryophyte layer model in the Atmosphere-Plant Exchange Simulator (APES) were able to yield satisfactory results based on field measurements of soil temperature and soil moisture. This study supports developing more practical evaluation tools on the hydrological state of peatland ecosystems.</abstract>
			<url hash="ca9e389d">G23-81001</url>
			<doi>10.1002/eco.2516</doi>
			<bibkey>Wang-2023-Effects</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="82">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>The Cryosphere, Volume 17, Issue 1</booktitle>
			<publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Significant underestimation of peatland permafrost along the Labrador Sea coastline in northern Canada</title>
			<author>
				<first>Yifeng</first>
				<last>Wang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Robert G.</first>
				<last>Way</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jordan</first>
				<last>Beer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Anika</first>
				<last>Forget</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Rosamond</first>
				<last>Tutton</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Meredith C.</first>
				<last>Purcell</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. Northern peatlands cover approximately four million km2, and about half of these peatlands are estimated to contain permafrost and periglacial landforms, like palsas and peat plateaus. In northeastern Canada, peatland permafrost is predicted to be concentrated in the western interior of Labrador but is assumed to be largely absent along the Labrador Sea coastline. However, the paucity of observations of peatland permafrost in the interior, coupled with traditional and ongoing use of perennially frozen peatlands along the coast by Labrador Inuit and Innu, suggests a need for re-evaluation of the reliability of existing peatland permafrost distribution estimates for the region. In this study, we develop a multi-stage consensus-based point inventory of peatland permafrost complexes in coastal Labrador and adjacent parts of Quebec using high-resolution satellite imagery, and we validate it with extensive field visits and low-altitude aerial photography and videography. A subset of 2092 wetland complexes that potentially contained peatland permafrost were inventoried, of which 1119 were classified as likely containing peatland permafrost. Likely peatland permafrost complexes were mostly found in lowlands within 22 km of the coastline, where mean annual air temperatures often exceed +1 ∘C. A clear gradient in peatland permafrost distribution exists from the outer coasts, where peatland permafrost is more abundant, to inland peatlands, where permafrost is generally absent. This coastal gradient may be attributed to a combination of climatic and geomorphological influences which lead to lower insolation, thinner snowpacks, and poorly drained, frost-susceptible materials along the coast. The results of this study suggest that existing estimates of permafrost distribution for southeastern Labrador require adjustments to better reflect the abundance of peatland permafrost complexes to the south of the regional sporadic discontinuous permafrost limit. This study constitutes the first dedicated peatland permafrost inventory for Labrador and provides an important baseline for future mapping, modelling, and climate change adaptation strategy development in the region.</abstract>
			<url hash="d82b9773">G23-82001</url>
			<pages>63-78</pages>
			<doi>10.5194/tc-17-63-2023</doi>
			<bibkey>Wang-2023-Significant</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="83">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Global Change Biology, Volume 29, Issue 7</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Carbon uptake in Eurasian boreal forests dominates the high‐latitude net ecosystem carbon budget</title>
			<author>
				<first>Jennifer D.</first>
				<last>Watts</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mary</first>
				<last>Farina</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>J. S.</first>
				<last>Kimball</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Luke</first>
				<last>Schiferl</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zhihua</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kyle A.</first>
				<last>Arndt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Donatella</first>
				<last>Zona</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ashley P.</first>
				<last>Ballantyne</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Eugénie S.</first>
				<last>Euskirchen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Frans-Jan W.</first>
				<last>Parmentier</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Manuel</first>
				<last>Helbig</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Oliver</first>
				<last>Sonnentag</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Torbern</first>
				<last>Tagesson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Janne</first>
				<last>Rinne</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hiroki</first>
				<last>Ikawa</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Masahito</first>
				<last>Ueyama</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hideki</first>
				<last>Kobayashi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Torsten</first>
				<last>Sachs</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Daniel F.</first>
				<last>Nadeau</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>John</first>
				<last>Kochendorfer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Marcin</first>
				<last>Jackowicz-Korczynski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Anna-Maria</first>
				<last>Virkkala</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mika</first>
				<last>Aurela</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>R.</first>
				<last>Commane</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brendan</first>
				<last>Byrne</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Leah</first>
				<last>Birch</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matthew S.</first>
				<last>Johnson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nima</first>
				<last>Madani</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brendan M.</first>
				<last>Rogers</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jinyang</first>
				<last>Du</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Arthur</first>
				<last>Endsley</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>K. E.</first>
				<last>Savage</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>B.</first>
				<last>Poulter</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zhen</first>
				<last>Zhang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>L.</first>
				<last>Bruhwiler</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Charles E.</first>
				<last>Miller</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Scott J.</first>
				<last>Goetz</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Walter C.</first>
				<last>Oechel</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Arctic-boreal landscapes are experiencing profound warming, along with changes in ecosystem moisture status and disturbance from fire. This region is of global importance in terms of carbon feedbacks to climate, yet the sign (sink or source) and magnitude of the Arctic-boreal carbon budget within recent years remains highly uncertain. Here, we provide new estimates of recent (2003-2015) vegetation gross primary productivity (GPP), ecosystem respiration (Reco ), net ecosystem CO2 exchange (NEE; Reco - GPP), and terrestrial methane (CH4 ) emissions for the Arctic-boreal zone using a satellite data-driven process-model for northern ecosystems (TCFM-Arctic), calibrated and evaluated using measurements from &gt;60 tower eddy covariance (EC) sites. We used TCFM-Arctic to obtain daily 1-km2 flux estimates and annual carbon budgets for the pan-Arctic-boreal region. Across the domain, the model indicated an overall average NEE sink of -850 Tg CO2 -C year-1 . Eurasian boreal zones, especially those in Siberia, contributed to a majority of the net sink. In contrast, the tundra biome was relatively carbon neutral (ranging from small sink to source). Regional CH4 emissions from tundra and boreal wetlands (not accounting for aquatic CH4 ) were estimated at 35 Tg CH4 -C year-1 . Accounting for additional emissions from open water aquatic bodies and from fire, using available estimates from the literature, reduced the total regional NEE sink by 21% and shifted many far northern tundra landscapes, and some boreal forests, to a net carbon source. This assessment, based on in situ observations and models, improves our understanding of the high-latitude carbon status and also indicates a continued need for integrated site-to-regional assessments to monitor the vulnerability of these ecosystems to climate change.</abstract>
			<url hash="6097f016">G23-83001</url>
			<pages>1870-1889</pages>
			<doi>10.1111/gcb.16553</doi>
			<bibkey>Watts-2023-Carbon</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="84">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrological Processes, Volume 37, Issue 7</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Quantifying seasonal, depression focused recharge in the context of public supply well vulnerability</title>
			<author>
				<first>Andrew J.</first>
				<last>Wiebe</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Paul G.</first>
				<last>Menkveld</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>David L.</first>
				<last>Rudolph</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract Depression focused recharge (DFR) may be a hydrologically important process that impacts the vulnerability of public supply wells, specifically related to pathogenic contaminants. The nature of DFR in glacial moraine environments, such as those located in northern latitudes within North America and Europe, is less well established than in other regions such as the Prairie Pothole Region (Northern United States, Western Canada) and the High Plains Aquifer (Central United States). The objectives of this study were to quantify seasonal infiltration flux beneath a topographically‐closed depression within 50 m of a public supply well and to interpret the impact of this DFR process on well vulnerability. Field instruments including groundwater monitoring wells, pressure transducers, soil moisture sensors and temperature sensors were installed in vertical clusters to capture the dynamics of infiltration, drainage and recharge within the depression feature. Continuous weather data were recorded by a meteorological station at the site. Transient infiltration was quantified during two contrasting hydrological events. The first event (~2 days) was an intense rainfall (&gt;50 mm) on a melting snowpack during the fall season when the soils were unfrozen. The second was a longer (35 day) period during the spring freshet when the surficial soils were initially frozen and subject to diurnal freezing and thawing and occasional precipitation events. The water table fluctuation method augmented by Darcy flux contributions, in addition to numerical modelling using the HYDRUS‐1D model, were used to quantify recharge rates beneath the depression. Numerical DFR estimates and analytical results differed by ±8%. Results indicate that recharge rates on the order of the annual regional average can occur beneath localized features in response to extreme events associated with snowmelt and intense rainfall. Such events may represent a microbial threat to groundwater quality if public supply wells are located nearby.</abstract>
			<url hash="fd40c8af">G23-84001</url>
			<doi>10.1002/hyp.14938</doi>
			<bibkey>Wiebe-2023-Quantifying</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="85">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Nature Climate Change, Volume 13, Issue 5</booktitle>
			<publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Wildfire and degradation accelerate northern peatland carbon release</title>
			<author>
				<first>Sophie</first>
				<last>Wilkinson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Roxane</first>
				<last>Andersen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Paul A.</first>
				<last>Moore</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Scott J.</first>
				<last>Davidson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Gustaf</first>
				<last>Granath</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>J. M.</first>
				<last>Waddington</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The northern peatland carbon sink plays a vital role in climate regulation; however, the future of the carbon sink is uncertain, in part, due to the changing interactions of peatlands and wildfire. Here, we use empirical datasets from natural, degraded and restored peatlands in non-permafrost boreal and temperate regions to model net ecosystem exchange and methane fluxes, integrating peatland degradation status, wildfire combustion and post-fire dynamics. We find that wildfire processes reduced carbon uptake in pristine peatlands by 35% and further enhanced emissions from degraded peatlands by 10%. The current small net sink is vulnerable to the interactions of peatland degraded area, burn rate and peat burn severity. Climate change impacts accelerated carbon losses, where increased burn severity and burn rate reduced the carbon sink by 38% and 65%, respectively, by 2100. However, our study demonstrates the potential for active peatland restoration to buffer these impacts. Northern peatland carbon sink plays a vital role in climate regulation. Here, the authors show that wildfire reduced peatland carbon uptake and enhanced emissions from degraded peatlands; climate change impacts accelerated carbon losses where increased burn rate and severity reduced carbon sink.</abstract>
			<url hash="45fcafca">G23-85001</url>
			<pages>456-461</pages>
			<doi>10.1038/s41558-023-01657-w</doi>
			<bibkey>Wilkinson-2023-Wildfire</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="86">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Hydrologic Engineering, Volume 28, Issue 4</booktitle>
			<publisher>American Society of Civil Engineers (ASCE)</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Mixture Probability Models with Covariates: Applications in Estimating Risk of Hydroclimatic Extremes</title>
			<author>
				<first>Nawres</first>
				<last>Yousfi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Salaheddine El</first>
				<last>Adlouni</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>S.</first>
				<last>Papalexiou</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe</first>
				<last>Gachon</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Modeling of extreme events is important in many scientific fields, including environmental and civil engineering, and impacts and risk assessments. Among available methods, statistical models that allow estimating extremes’ frequency and intensity are regularly used in procedures to anticipate potential changes in extreme events. Extreme value theory provides a theoretical basis for statistical estimation of extreme events using frequency analysis. The challenge in modeling is knowing when to use the block maxima method or the peaks-over-threshold (POT) method. Each has its drawbacks. POT describes the main characteristics of the observed extreme series; the threshold selection is always challenging and might affect the accuracy of the simulated results and the credibility of changes in extreme values. To encompass this challenge, mixture models offer more flexibility to represent samples with nonhomogeneous data. This study presents the gamma generalized Pareto (GGP) mixture model for estimating risk occurrence of hydroclimatic extremes. The model was developed in its general form, whereas the observed hydrometeorological extreme events depend on multidimensional covariates. A maximum likelihood algorithm is proposed to estimate the parameters with a constraint on the shape parameter of the generalized Pareto (GP) distribution. A Monte Carlo (MC) simulation compared the proposed model with the classical POT approach, with a fixed threshold, and the annual maximum series of streamflow. The approach was applied using a daily hydrological data set from an observed station located in the Saint John River at Fort Kent (01AD002), New Brunswick, Canada. The results show a flexibility to model extremes for dependent or nonstationary time series and adequately describes the central part of the observed frequencies, as well as the tails.</abstract>
			<url hash="57490024">G23-86001</url>
			<doi>10.1061/jhyeff.heeng-5831</doi>
			<bibkey>Yousfi-2023-Mixture</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="87">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Global Change Biology, Volume 29, Issue 5</booktitle>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>&lt;scp&gt;Pan‐Arctic&lt;/scp&gt; soil moisture control on tundra carbon sequestration and plant productivity</title>
			<author>
				<first>Donatella</first>
				<last>Zona</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Peter M.</first>
				<last>Lafleur</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Koen</first>
				<last>Hufkens</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Beniamino</first>
				<last>Gioli</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Barbara</first>
				<last>Bailey</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>George</first>
				<last>Burba</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Eugénie S.</first>
				<last>Euskirchen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Jennifer D.</first>
				<last>Watts</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Kyle A.</first>
				<last>Arndt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mary</first>
				<last>Farina</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>J. S.</first>
				<last>Kimball</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Martin</first>
				<last>Heimann</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mathias</first>
				<last>Goeckede</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Martijn</first>
				<last>Pallandt</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Torben R.</first>
				<last>Christensen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mikhail</first>
				<last>Mastepanov</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Efrén</first>
				<last>López-Blanco</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>A.J.</first>
				<last>Dolman</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>R.</first>
				<last>Commane</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Charles E.</first>
				<last>Miller</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Josh</first>
				<last>Hashemi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Lars</first>
				<last>Kutzbach</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>David</first>
				<last>Holl</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Julia</first>
				<last>Boike</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Christian</first>
				<last>Wille</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Torsten</first>
				<last>Sachs</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Aram</first>
				<last>Kalhori</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Elyn</first>
				<last>Humphreys</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Oliver</first>
				<last>Sonnentag</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Gesa</first>
				<last>Meyer</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Gabriel</first>
				<last>Gosselin</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philip</first>
				<last>Marsh</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Walter C.</first>
				<last>Oechel</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Long-term atmospheric CO2 concentration records have suggested a reduction in the positive effect of warming on high-latitude carbon uptake since the 1990s. A variety of mechanisms have been proposed to explain the reduced net carbon sink of northern ecosystems with increased air temperature, including water stress on vegetation and increased respiration over recent decades. However, the lack of consistent long-term carbon flux and in situ soil moisture data has severely limited our ability to identify the mechanisms responsible for the recent reduced carbon sink strength. In this study, we used a record of nearly 100 site-years of eddy covariance data from 11 continuous permafrost tundra sites distributed across the circumpolar Arctic to test the temperature (expressed as growing degree days, GDD) responses of gross primary production (GPP), net ecosystem exchange (NEE), and ecosystem respiration (ER) at different periods of the summer (early, peak, and late summer) including dominant tundra vegetation classes (graminoids and mosses, and shrubs). We further tested GPP, NEE, and ER relationships with soil moisture and vapor pressure deficit to identify potential moisture limitations on plant productivity and net carbon exchange. Our results show a decrease in GPP with rising GDD during the peak summer (July) for both vegetation classes, and a significant relationship between the peak summer GPP and soil moisture after statistically controlling for GDD in a partial correlation analysis. These results suggest that tundra ecosystems might not benefit from increased temperature as much as suggested by several terrestrial biosphere models, if decreased soil moisture limits the peak summer plant productivity, reducing the ability of these ecosystems to sequester carbon during the summer.</abstract>
			<url hash="eff56741">G23-87001</url>
			<pages>1267-1281</pages>
			<doi>10.1111/gcb.16487</doi>
			<bibkey>Zona-2023-&lt;scp&gt;Pan‐Arctic&lt;/scp&gt;</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="88">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>The Cryosphere Discussions, Volume 15</booktitle>
			<publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>The Ability of Hydrologic-Land Surface Models to Concurrently Simulate Permafrost and Hydrology</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mohamed S.</first>
				<last>Abdelhamed</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mohamed</first>
				<last>Elshamy</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Saman</first>
				<last>Razavi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>H. S.</first>
				<last>Wheater</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. Hydrologic-land surface models (H-LSMs) provide physically-based understanding and predictions of the current and future states of the world’s vast high-latitude permafrost regions. Two major challenges, however, hamper their parametrization and validation when concurrently representing hydrology and permafrost. One is the high computational complexity, exacerbated by the need to include a deep soil profile to adequately capture the freeze/thaw cycles and heat storage. The other is that soil-temperature data are severely limited, and traditional model validation, based on streamflow, can show the right fit to these data for the wrong reasons. There are few observational sites for such vast, heterogeneous regions, and remote sensing provides only limited support. In light of these challenges, we develop 16 parametrizations of a Canadian H-LSM, MESH, for the sub-arctic Liard River Basin and validate them using three data sources: streamflows at multiple gauges, soil temperature profiles from few available boreholes, and multiple permafrost maps. The different parametrizations favor different sources of data and it is challenging to configure a model faithful to all three data sources, which are at times inconsistent with each other. Overall, the results show that: (1) surface insulation through snow cover primarily regulates permafrost dynamics after model initialization effects decay over, relatively long time and (2) different parametrizations yield different partitioning patterns of solid-vs-liquid soil-water and produce different low-flow but similar high-flow regimes. We conclude that, given data scarcity, an ensemble of model parametrizations is essential to provide a reliable picture of the current states and future spatio-temporal co-evolution of permafrost and hydrology.</abstract>
			<url hash="32e8dd23">G23-2001</url>
			<doi>10.5194/tc-2023-20</doi>
			<bibkey>Abdelhamed-2023-The</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="89">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Sensors and Actuators A: Physical, Volume 362</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Real-Time Lead Detection Device Based on Nanomaterials Modified Microwave-Microfluidic Sensor</title>
			<author>
				<first>Weijia</first>
				<last>Cui</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ren</first>
				<last>Zhe</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zahra</first>
				<last>Abbasi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yongxin</first>
				<last>Song</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Carolyn L.</first>
				<last>Ren</last>
			</author>
			<abstract/>
			<url hash="abe18c99">G23-2002</url>
			<doi>10.2139/ssrn.4483935</doi>
			<bibkey>Cui-2023-Real-Time</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="90">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Earth System Science Data Discussions, Volume 2023</booktitle>
			<publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Atmospheric and surface observations during the Saint John River Experiment on Cold Season Storms (SAJESS)</title>
			<author>
				<first>Hadleigh D.</first>
				<last>Thompson</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Julie M.</first>
				<last>Thériault</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stephen J.</first>
				<last>Déry</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ronald E.</first>
				<last>Stewart</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Dominique</first>
				<last>Boisvert</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Lisa</first>
				<last>Rickard</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Nicolas</first>
				<last>Leroux</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Matteo</first>
				<last>Colli</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Vincent</first>
				<last>Vionnet</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. The amount and phase of cold season precipitation accumulating in the upper Saint John River basin are critical factors in determining spring runoff, ice-jams, and flooding in downstream communities. To study the impact of winter and spring storms on the snowpack in the upper Saint John River (SJR) basin, the Saint John River Experiment on Cold Season Storms (SAJESS) utilized meteorological instrumentation, upper air soundings, human observations, and hydrometeor macrophotography during winter/spring 2020–21. Here, we provide an overview of the SAJESS study area, field campaign, and existing data networks surrounding the upper SJR basin. Initially, meteorological instrumentation was co-located with an Environment and Climate Change Canada station near Edmundston, New Brunswick, in early December 2020. This was followed by an intensive observation period that involved manual observations, upper-air soundings, a multi-angle snowflake camera, macrophotography of solid hydrometeors, and advanced automated instrumentation throughout March and April 2021. The resulting datasets include optical disdrometer size and velocity distributions of hydrometeors, micro rain radar output, near-surface meteorological observations, and wind speed, temperature, pressure and precipitation amounts from a K63 Hotplate precipitation gauge, the first one operating in Canada. These data are publicly available from the Federated Research Data Repository at https://doi.org/10.20383/103.0591 (Thompson et al., 2022). We also include a synopsis of the data management plan and data processing, and a brief assessment of the rewards and challenges of utilizing community volunteers for hydro-meteorological citizen science.</abstract>
			<url hash="3585193a">G23-2005</url>
			<doi>10.5194/essd-2023-59</doi>
			<bibkey>Thompson-2023-Atmospheric</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="91">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Hydrology and Earth System Sciences, Volume 27</booktitle>
			<publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Hydrological, meteorological and watershed controls on the water balance of thermokarst lakes between Inuvik and Tuktoyaktuk, Northwest Territories, Canada</title>
			<author>
				<first>Evan J.</first>
				<last>Wilcox</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Brent B.</first>
				<last>Wolfe</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philip</first>
				<last>Marsh</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. Thermokarst lake water balances are becoming increasingly vulnerable to change in the Arctic as air temperature increases and precipitation patterns shift. In the tundra uplands east of the Mackenzie Delta in the Northwest Territories, Canada, previous research has found that lakes responded non-uniformly to changes in precipitation, suggesting that lake and watershed properties moderate the response of lakes to climate change. To investigate how lake and watershed properties and meteoro5 logical conditions influence the water balance of thermokarst lakes in this region, we sampled 25 lakes for isotope analysis five times in 2018, beginning before snowmelt on May 1 and ending on September 3. Water isotope data were used to calculate the ratio of evaporation-to-inflow (E/I) and the average isotope composition of lake source water (δI). We identified four distinct water balance phases as lakes responded to seasonal shifts in meteorological conditions and hydrological processes. During the freshet phase from May 1 to June 15, the median E/I ratio of lakes decreased from 0.20 to 0.13 in response to freshet runoff 10 and limited evaporation due to lake ice presence that persisted for the duration of this phase. During the following warm, dry, and ice-free period from June 15 to July 26, designated the evaporation phase, the median E/I ratio increased to 0.19. During the brief soil wetting phase, E/I ratios did not respond to rainfall between July 26 and August 2, likely because watershed soils absorbed most of the precipitation which resulted in minimal runoff to lakes. The median E/I ratio decreased to 0.11 after an unseasonably cool and rainy August, identified as the recharge phase. Throughout the sampling period, δI remained relatively 15 stable and most lakes contained a greater amount of rainfall-sourced water than snow-sourced water, even after the freshet phase due to snowmelt bypass. The range of average E/I ratios we observed at lakes (0.00–0.43) was relatively narrow and low compared to thermokarst lakes in other regions, likely owing to the large watershed area to lake area (WA/LA), efficient preferential flow pathways for runoff, and a shorter ice-free season. WA/LA strongly predicted average lake E/I ratio (R2 = 0.74), as lakes with smaller WA/LA tended to have higher E/I ratios because they received relatively less inflow. We used this 20 relationship to predict the average E/I ratio of 7340 lakes in the region, finding that lakes are not vulnerable to desiccation in this region, given that all predicted average E/I values were &lt;0.33. If future permafrost thaw and warming cause less runoff to flow into lakes, we expect that lakes with smaller WA/LA will be more influenced by increasing evaporation, while lakes with larger WA/LA will be more resistant to lake-level drawdown. However under wetter conditions, lakes with larger WA/LA will likely experience greater increases in lake level and could be more susceptible to rapid drainage as a result.</abstract>
			<url hash="ac8c4880">G23-2006</url>
			<doi>10.5194/hess-2022-279</doi>
			<bibkey>Wilcox-2023-Hydrological,</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="92">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Geoscientific Model Development, Volume 16</booktitle>
			<publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
			<address/>
			<year>2023</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Developing Spring Wheat in the Noah-MP LSM (v4.4) for Growing Season Dynamics and Responses to Temperature Stress</title>
			<author>
				<first>Zhe</first>
				<last>Zhang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Yanping</first>
				<last>Li</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fei</first>
				<last>Chen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Phillip</first>
				<last>Harder</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Warren</first>
				<last>Helgason</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>J. S.</first>
				<last>Famiglietti</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Prasanth</first>
				<last>Valayamkunnath</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Cenlin</first>
				<last>He</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Zhenhua</first>
				<last>Li</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Abstract. The US Northern Great Plains and the Canadian Prairies are known as the world’s breadbaskets for its large spring wheat production and exports to the world. It is essential to accurately represent spring wheat growing dynamics and final yield and improve our ability to predict food production under climate change. This study attempts to incorporate spring wheat growth dynamics into the Noah-MP crop model, for a long time period (13-year) and fine spatial scale (4-km). The study focuses on three aspects: (1) developing and calibrating the spring wheat model at point-scale, (2) applying a dynamic planting/harvest date to facilitate large-scale simulations, and (3) applying a temperature stress function to assess crop responses to heat stress amid extreme heat. Model results are evaluated using field observations, satellite leaf area index (LAI), and census data from Statistics Canada and the US Department of Agriculture (USDA). Results suggest that incorporating a dynamic planting/harvest threshold can better constrain the growing season, especially the peak timing and magnitude of wheat LAI, as well as obtain realistic yield compared to prescribing a static province/state-level map. Results also demonstrate an evident control of heat stress upon wheat yield in three Canadian Prairies Provinces, which are reasonably captured in the new temperature stress function. This study has important implications for estimating crop production, simulating the land-atmosphere interactions in croplands, and crop growth’s responses to the raising temperatures amid climate change.</abstract>
			<url hash="db8b7816">G23-2007</url>
			<doi>10.5194/gmd-2022-311</doi>
			<bibkey>Zhang-2023-Developing</bibkey>
			<project>prj6</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
</collection>
