<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G24">
	<volume id="1">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Geoderma, Volume 443</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>The apparent temperature sensitivity (Q10) of peat soil respiration: A synthesis study</title>
			<author>
				<first>Haojie</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fereidoun</first>
				<last>Rezanezhad</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Ying</first>
				<last>Zhao</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hongxing</first>
				<last>He</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bernd</first>
				<last>Lennartz</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The temperature sensitivity (Q10) of soil respiration is a critical parameter in modeling soil carbon dynamics; yet the regulating factors and the underlying mechanisms of Q10 in peat soils remain unclear. To address this gap, we conducted a comprehensive synthesis data analysis from 87 peatland sites (350 observations) spanning boreal, temperate, and tropical zones, and investigated the spatial distribution pattern of Q10 and its correlation with climate conditions, soil properties, and hydrology. Findings revealed distinct Q10 values across climate zones: boreal peatlands exhibited the highest Q10, trailed by temperate and then tropical peatlands. Latitude presented a positive correlation with Q10, while mean annual air temperature and precipitation revealed a negative correlation. The results from the structural equation model suggest that soil properties, such as carbon-to-nitrogen ratio (C/N) and peat type, were the primary drivers of the variance in Q10 of peat respiration. Peat C/N ratios negatively correlated with Q10 of peat respiration and the relationship between C/N and Q10 varied significantly between peat types. Our data analyses also revealed that Q10 was influenced by soil moisture levels, with significantly lower values observed for peat soils under wet than dry conditions. Essentially, boreal and temperate peatlands seem more vulnerable to global warming-induced soil organic carbon decomposition than tropical counterparts, with wet peatlands showing higher climate resilience.</abstract>
			<url hash="3d584275">G24-1001</url>
			<pages>116844</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.geoderma.2024.116844</doi>
			<bibkey>Liu-2024-The</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="2">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Applied Geochemistry, Volume 162</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Road salt-induced salinization impacts water geochemistry and mixing regime of a Canadian urban lake</title>
			<author>
				<first>Jovana</first>
				<last>Radosavljevic</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stephanie</first>
				<last>Slowinski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fereidoun</first>
				<last>Rezanezhad</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Mahyar</first>
				<last>Shafii</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Bahram</first>
				<last>Gharabaghi</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The extensive use of road salts as deicers during winter months is causing the salinization of freshwater systems in cold climate regions worldwide. We analyzed 20 years (2001–2020) of data on lake water chemistry, land cover changes, and road salt applications for Lake Wilcox (LW) located in southern Ontario, Canada. The lake is situated within a rapidly urbanizing watershed in which, during the period of observation, on average 785 tons of road salt were applied annually. However, only about a quarter of this salt has reached the lake so far. That is, most salt has been retained in the watershed, likely through accumulation in soils and groundwater. Despite the high watershed salt retention, time series trend analyses for LW show significant increases in the dissolved concentrations of sodium (Na+) and chloride (Cl−), as well as those of sulfate (SO42−), calcium (Ca2+), and magnesium (Mg2+). The relative changes in the major ion concentrations indicate a shift of the lake water chemistry from the mixed SO42–Cl–Ca2+-Mg2+ type to the Na + -Cl- type. Salinization of LW has further been strengthening and lengthening the lake's summer stratification, which, in turn, has been enhancing hypoxia in the hypolimnion and increasing the internal loading of the limiting nutrient phosphorus. The theoretical salinity threshold at which fall overturn would become increasingly unlikely was estimated at around 1.23 g kg−1. A simple chloride mass balance model predicts that, under the current trend of impermeable land cover expansion, LW could reach this salinity threshold by mid-century. Our results also highlight the need for additional research on the accruing salt legacies in urbanizing watersheds because they represent potential long-term threats to water quality for receiving freshwater ecosystems and regional groundwater resources.</abstract>
			<url hash="2feded9b">G24-2001</url>
			<pages>105928</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.apgeochem.2024.105928</doi>
			<bibkey>Radosavljevic-2024-Road</bibkey>
			<project>prj26</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="3">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Chemosphere, Volume 349</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Co-precipitation of iron and silicon: Reaction kinetics, elemental ratios and the influence of phosphorus</title>
			<author>
				<first>Lu</first>
				<last>Huang</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Chris T.</first>
				<last>Parsons</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stephanie</first>
				<last>Slowinski</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Philippe Van</first>
				<last>Cappellen</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>A sufficient supply of dissolved silicon (DSi) relative to dissolved phosphorus (DP) may decrease the likelihood of harmful algal blooms in eutrophic waters. Oxidative precipitation of Fe(II) at oxic-anoxic interfaces may contribute to the immobilization of DSi, thereby exerting control over the DSi availability in the overlying water. Nevertheless, the efficacy of DSi immobilization in this context remains to be precisely determined. To investigate the behavior of DSi during Fe(II) oxidation, anoxic solutions containing mixtures of aqueous Fe(II), DSi, and dissolved phosphorus (DP) were exposed to dissolved oxygen (DO) in the batch system. The experimental data, combined with kinetic reaction modeling, indicate that DSi removal during Fe(II) oxidation occurs via two pathways. At the beginning of the experiments, the oxidation of Fe(II)-DSi complexes induces the fast removal of DSi. Upon complete oxidation of Fe(II), further DSi removal is due to adsorption to surface sites of the Fe(III) oxyhydroxides. The presence of DP effectively competes with DSi via both of these pathways during the initial and later stages of the experiments, with as a result more limited removal of DSi during Fe(II) oxidation. Overall, we conclude that at near neutral pH the oxidation of Fe(II) has considerable capacity to immobilize DSi, where the rapid homogeneous oxidation of Fe(II)-DSi results in greater DSi removal compared to surface adsorption. Elevated DP concentration, however, effectively outcompetes DSi in co-precipitation interactions, potentially contributing to enhanced DSi availability within aquatic systems.</abstract>
			<url hash="97518afe">G24-3001</url>
			<pages>140930</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.140930</doi>
			<bibkey>Huang-2024-Co-precipitation</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="4">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Journal of Hydrology, Volume 630</booktitle>
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2024</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Advancement and perspectives of hyporheic zone hydrology: Technology, theory and environmental implication</title>
			<author>
				<first>Zhang</first>
				<last>Wen</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Hui</first>
				<last>Liu</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Fereidoun</first>
				<last>Rezanezhad</last>
			</author>
			<author>
				<first>Stefan</first>
				<last>Krause</last>
			</author>
			<abstract />
			<url hash="0a86b247">G24-4001</url>
			<pages>130721</pages>
			<doi>10.1016/j.jhydrol.2024.130721</doi>
			<bibkey>Wen-2024-Advancement</bibkey>
			<project>prj10</project>
		</paper>
	</volume>
</collection>