<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Buono-etal-2016-Proceedings">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Proceedings of the International Working Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">P</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Buono</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">R</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Lanzilotti</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">M</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Matera</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">M</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Costabile</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2016</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Global Water Futures 2016</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
            <place>
                <placeTerm type="text">Online</placeTerm>
            </place>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">conference publication</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>AVI 2016 is the 13th edition of the International Working Conferences on Advanced Visual Interfaces, held in Bari, Italy, during June 7-10 2016. Since 1992, the AVI conferences are held every two years and have become well appreciated by the international community, attracting experts with a broad range of backgrounds, coming from all over the world and sharing a common interest on HCI, with the aim of making technology effective and useful for all people in their daily life. Because of advanced technology and new possibilities for user interaction, AVI has broadened the topics it covers, still keeping its main focus on the conception, design, implementation and evaluation of novel visual interfaces. While rooted in Italy, AVI is a true international conference with respect to nationality of participants, authors of papers, and program committee members. AVI 2016 presents an articulated strong scientific program. A rigorous double-blind reviewing process was carried out, with an acceptance rate of 27% for long papers (96 submissions). The various sessions explore research questions and solutions in several domains, and cover a wide range of topics. World leading researchers, from 22 different countries and 4 continents (Europe, America, Asia, and Australia) will present their work in 26 long papers, 17 short papers, 30 posters, 6 hands-on demos, and 5 workshops.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Buono-etal-2016-Proceedings</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1145/2909132</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/2016.GWF-1.9</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2016</date>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
