<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Haghnegahdar-2017-Insights">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Insights into sensitivity analysis of Earth and environmental systems models: On the impact of parameter perturbation scale</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Amin</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Haghnegahdar</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Saman</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Razavi</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2017</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="bibutilsgt">journal article</genre>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Environmental Modelling &amp;amp; Software, Volume 95</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
            <publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
        <genre authority="bibutilsgt">academic journal</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>Abstract This paper investigates the commonly overlooked “sensitivity” of sensitivity analysis (SA) to what we refer to as parameter “perturbation scale”, which can be defined as a prescribed size of the sensitivity-related neighbourhood around any point in the parameter space (analogous to step size Δ x for numerical estimation of derivatives). We discuss that perturbation scale is inherent to any (local and global) SA approach, and explain how derivative-based SA approaches (e.g., method of Morris) focus on small-scale perturbations, while variance-based approaches (e.g., method of Sobol) focus on large-scale perturbations. We employ a novel variogram-based approach, called Variogram Analysis of Response Surfaces (VARS), which bridges derivative- and variance-based approaches. Our analyses with different real-world environmental models demonstrate significant implications of subjectivity in the perturbation-scale choice and the need for strategies to address these implications. It is further shown how VARS can uniquely characterize the perturbation-scale dependency and generate sensitivity measures that encompass all sensitivity-related information across the full spectrum of perturbation scales.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Haghnegahdar-2017-Insights</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1016/j.envsoft.2017.03.031</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/G17-13001</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2017</date>
        <detail type="volume"><number>95</number></detail>
        <extent unit="page">
            <start>115</start>
            <end>131</end>
        </extent>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
