<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Krogh-2018-Recent">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Recent changes to the hydrological cycle of an Arctic basin at the tundra–taiga transition</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Sebastian</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">A</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Krogh</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">John</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">W</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Pomeroy</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2018</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="bibutilsgt">journal article</genre>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Hydrology and Earth System Sciences, Volume 22, Issue 7</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
            <publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
        <genre authority="bibutilsgt">academic journal</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>\textlessjats:p\textgreaterAbstract. The impact of transient changes in climate and vegetation on the hydrology ofsmall Arctic headwater basins has not been investigated before, particularly in thetundra–taiga transition region. This study uses weather and land coverobservations and a hydrological model suitable for cold regions to investigate historicalchanges in modelled hydrological processes driving the streamflow response ofa small Arctic basin at the treeline. The physical processes found in thisenvironment and explicit changes in vegetation extent and density weresimulated and validated against observations of streamflow discharge, snowwater equivalent and active layer thickness. Mean air temperature andall-wave irradiance have increased by 3.7 ∘C and 8.4 W m−2,respectively, while precipitation has decreased 48 mm (10 %) since 1960.Two modelling scenarios were created to separate the effects of changingclimate and vegetation on hydrological processes. Results show that over1960–2016 most hydrological changes were driven by climate changes, such asdecreasing snowfall, evapotranspiration, deepening active layer thickness,earlier snow cover depletion and diminishing annual sublimation and soilmoisture. However, changing vegetation has a significant impact on decreasingblowing snow redistribution and sublimation, counteracting the impact ofdecreasing precipitation on streamflow, demonstrating the importance ofincluding transient changes in vegetation in long-term hydrological studies.Streamflow dropped by 38 mm as a response to the 48 mm decrease inprecipitation, suggesting a small degree of hydrological resiliency. Theseresults represent the first detailed estimate of hydrological changesoccurring in small Arctic basins, and can be used as a reference to informother studies of Arctic climate change impacts. \textless/jats:p\textgreater</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Krogh-2018-Recent</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.5194/hess-22-3993-2018</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/G18-64001</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2018</date>
        <detail type="volume"><number>22</number></detail>
        <detail type="issue"><number>7</number></detail>
        <extent unit="page">
            <start>3993</start>
            <end>4014</end>
        </extent>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
