<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Akbarzadeh-etal-2019-Effects">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Effects of Damming on River Nitrogen Fluxes: A Global Analysis</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Zahra</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Akbarzadeh</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">T</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Maavara</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">S</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Slowinski</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">P</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Van Cappellen</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2019</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Global Water Futures 2019</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
            <place>
                <placeTerm type="text">Online</placeTerm>
            </place>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">conference publication</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>Damming creates biogeochemical hotspots along rivers that modify the riverine flow of nutrients, including nitrogen (N). Here, we quantify the impact of dams on global riverine N fluxes using a reservoir N mass balance model. In‐reservoir processes represented in the model include primary production, mineralization of organic N, denitrification, and sedimentary burial. In addition, we explicitly account for N fixation as a source of N, assuming that the N to phosphorus (P) ratio of the inflow regulates the magnitude of N fixation in reservoirs. The model is scaled up via a Monte Carlo analysis that yields global relationships between N elimination in reservoirs, either by denitrification or burial, and the hydraulic residence time. These relationships are then combined with N loads to the world’s dam reservoirs generated by the Global‐NEWS model and the estimated N fixation fluxes. According to the results, in year 2000, worldwide N fixation in reservoirs was on the order of 70 Gmol yr−1, while denitrification and burial in reservoirs eliminated around 270 Gmol yr−1, equal to 7% of N loading to the global river network. The latter is predicted to double to 14% by 2030, mainly as a result of the current boom in dam building. The results further imply that, largely due to N fixation in reservoirs, damming causes a global upward shift in riverine N:P ratios, thus lessening N limitation in receiving water bodies.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Akbarzadeh-etal-2019-Effects</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1029/2019GB006222</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/2019.GWF-1.20</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2019</date>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
