<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Domenici-etal-2019-Smoke">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Smoke, Flames, and the Human Body in Mesoamerican Ritual Practice. VERA TIESLER and ANDREW K. SCHERER, editors. 2018. Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection, Washington, DC. viii + 471 pp. $ 75.00 (cloth), ISBN 978-0-88402-426-2.</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">D</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Domenici</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2019</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Global Water Futures 2019</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
            <place>
                <placeTerm type="text">Online</placeTerm>
            </place>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">conference publication</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>tion to Mesoamerican sites. For instance, the total population for Teotihuacan is listed as 14,485 in Table 11.1, which is the same number given for its households; a similar error in the number of households and total population is also found for Mayapan, Capilco, and Tenochtitlan. The total site populations for Tikal and Caracol do not match published figures, and no supporting data or references are provided to indicate why these numbers were used. References in Chapters 1 and 11 are made to supplementary materials associated with an earlier 2017 publication, but similarly problematic population estimates without easily accessible supporting data, methodology, and references are found here as well. I hope that some of these issues can be corrected and resolved before the volume appears in paperback, so that researchers are able to see from whom and how these data were derived. Despite these referencing and numerical issues, this is an important volume that serves as a concrete example of how and why archaeology is relevant in the modern world. Any serious researcher on past social complexity should add it to his or her methodological repertoire.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Domenici-etal-2019-Smoke</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1017/laq.2019.5</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/2019.GWF-1.237</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2019</date>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
