<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Harder-etal-2020-Improving">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Improving sub-canopy snow depth mapping with unmanned aerial vehicles: lidar versus structure-from-motion techniques</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">P</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Harder</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">J</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Pomeroy</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">W</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Helgason</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2020</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Global Water Futures 2020</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
            <place>
                <placeTerm type="text">Online</placeTerm>
            </place>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">conference publication</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>Abstract. Vegetation has a tremendous influence on snow processesand snowpack dynamics, yet remote sensing techniques to resolve the spatialvariability of sub-canopy snow depth are not always available and aredifficult from space-based platforms. Unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) havehad recent widespread application to capture high-resolution information onsnow processes and are herein applied to the sub-canopy snow depthchallenge. Previous demonstrations of snow depth mapping with UAV structurefrom motion (SfM) and airborne lidar have focussed on non-vegetated surfacesor reported large errors in the presence of vegetation. In contrast,UAV-lidar systems have high-density point clouds and measure returns from awide range of scan angles, increasing the likelihood of successfully sensingthe sub-canopy snow depth. The effectiveness of UAV lidar and UAV SfM inmapping snow depth in both open and forested terrain was tested in a 2019field campaign at the Canadian Rockies Hydrological Observatory, Alberta, andat Canadian prairie sites near Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, Canada. OnlyUAV lidar could successfully measure the sub-canopy snow surface withreliable sub-canopy point coverage and consistent error metrics(root mean square error (RMSE) \textless0.17 m and bias −0.03 to −0.13 m). Relative to UAV lidar, UAV SfMdid not consistently sense the sub-canopy snow surface, the interpolationneeded to account for point cloud gaps introduced interpolation artefacts,and error metrics demonstrated relatively large variability (RMSE\textless0.33 m and bias 0.08 to −0.14 m). With the demonstration of sub-canopy snowdepth mapping capabilities, a number of early applications are presented toshowcase the ability of UAV lidar to effectively quantify the manymultiscale snow processes defining snowpack dynamics in mountain and prairieenvironments.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Harder-etal-2020-Improving</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.5194/tc-14-1919-2020</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/2020.GWF-1.19</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2020</date>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
