<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Bazin-2020-Rezistans">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Rezistans Klimatik: Building Climate Change Resilience in Haiti through Educational Radio Programming.</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Ashley</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Bazin</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Christelle</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Saintis</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2020</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="bibutilsgt">journal article</genre>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Education and Climate Change</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
            <publisher>Springer International Publishing</publisher>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
        <genre authority="bibutilsgt">academic journal</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>\textlessjats:title\textgreaterAbstract\textless/jats:title\textgreater\textlessjats:p\textgreaterIn this chapter we address the challenge of responding to climate-related issues for vulnerable nations such as Haiti by adopting a non-formal radio-based approach to educate adults outside of the school system. We argue that to inform populations on climate change, we cannot solely rely on the K-12 school system. This is especially true for countries such as Haiti. where there is an inadequate education infrastructure, and much of the population, both juveniles, and adults, is not in school or has not attended school for some time. The effects of climate change are changing the lives of people globally, and third-world nations such as Haiti are even more susceptible to climate-related disasters. Given the severity of ongoing circumstances, a sense of urgency is necessary, and addressing the issue requires an approach that has a far, broad and rapid reach and concludes in immediate climate action as opposed to delayed. In order to efficiently respond to climate-related events, a population needs to build resilience through awareness, understanding, and skill development in the context of the country and region, which in this chapter is specifically Port-au-Prince, Haiti.\textless/jats:p\textgreater</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Bazin-2020-Rezistans</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-57927-2_4</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/G20-161001</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2020</date>
        <extent unit="page">
            <start>113</start>
            <end>136</end>
        </extent>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
