<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="UlAlam-etal-2021-A">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>A reusable, reagent-less free chlorine sensor using gold thin film electrode.</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Arif</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Ul Alam</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Dennis</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Clyne</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">W</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Lush</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">M</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Deen</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2021</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Global Water Futures 2021</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
            <place>
                <placeTerm type="text">Online</placeTerm>
            </place>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">conference publication</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>Free chlorine is widely used as a disinfectant in the water industry. Accurate monitoring of the residual free chlorine concentration in water cycles is critical to maintain public health safety. Here, we report on a thin gold film-based reusable and reagent-less free chlorine sensor. A gold thin film of 300 nm thickness was deposited on a polyimide tape, which was placed on a glass substrate and a simple Styrofoam adhesive tape was used to cover the film and expose 0.36 cm2 circular area as the sensing surface. The sensor showed a high sensitivity of 0.327 μA ppm-1, with a linear range of 0 to 6 ppm, and an accuracy of \textless0.1 ppm with high selectivity in the presence of commonly interfering ions. The sensor response time was 50 s with a negligible hysteresis of 0.06 ppm. The sensor showed very little change in output current in the pH range between 5.2 to 8.4, and temperature range of 20 to 30 °C. Therefore, the sensor operation is reagent-less, does not need frequent calibration, and showed consistent sensing performance with real water samples. The simple fabrication, ease-of-use and reliable sensing performance of the proposed sensor shows feasibility for mass-production and application in remote and resource-limited areas.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Ul Alam-etal-2021-A</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1039/d1an00038a</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/2021.GWF-1.123</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2021</date>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
