<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Brouwer-2022-The">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>The economic value of the Brazilian Amazon rainforest ecosystem services: A meta-analysis of the Brazilian literature</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Roy</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Brouwer</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Rute</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Pinto</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Anders</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Dugstad</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Ståle</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Navrud</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2022</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="bibutilsgt">journal article</genre>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>PLOS ONE, Volume 17, Issue 5</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
            <publisher>Public Library of Science (PLoS)</publisher>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
        <genre authority="bibutilsgt">academic journal</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>The main objective of this study is to assess the economic value of the Brazilian Amazon’s ecosystem services accruing to Brazilians based on a meta-analysis of the Brazilian valuation literature. Insight in these local values provides an important benchmark to demonstrate the importance of preserving the Brazilian Amazon forest. The review covers almost 30 years of Brazilian valuation research on the Amazon, published predominantly in Portuguese, highlighting a high degree of study and data heterogeneity. The estimated mean value of the provision of habitat for species, carbon sequestration, water regulation, recreation and ecotourism to local populations is about 410 USD/ha/year. The standard deviation is however high, reflecting a wide dispersion in the distribution of values. Between 50 and 70 percent of the variation in these values can be explained with the help of the estimated meta-regression models, resulting in considerable prediction errors when applying a within-sample resampling procedure. These findings demonstrate the need for a more robust, common ecosystem services accounting and valuation framework before these values can be scaled up and aggregated across the entire Brazilian Amazon.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Brouwer-2022-The</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0268425</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/G22-92001</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2022</date>
        <detail type="volume"><number>17</number></detail>
        <detail type="issue"><number>5</number></detail>
        <detail type="page"><number>e0268425</number></detail>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
