<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="J.Huang-etal-2022-Selection">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Selection of Aptamers for Sensing Caffeine and Discrimination of Its Three Single Demethylated Analogues.</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">P</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">J. Huang</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Juewen</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Liu</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2022</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Global Water Futures 2022</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
            <place>
                <placeTerm type="text">Online</placeTerm>
            </place>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">conference publication</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>With the growing consumption of caffeine-containing beverages, detection of caffeine has become an important biomedical, bioanalytical, and environmental topic. We herein isolated four high-quality aptamers for caffeine with dissociation constants ranging from 2.2 to 14.6 μM as characterized using isothermal titration calorimetry. Different binding patterns were obtained for the three single demethylated analogues: theobromine, theophylline, and paraxanthine, highlighting the effect of the molecular symmetry of the arrangement of the three methyl groups in caffeine. A structure-switching fluorescent sensor was designed showing a detection limit of 1.2 μM caffeine, which reflected the labeled caffeine concentration within 6.1% difference for eight commercial beverages. In 20% human serum, a detection limit of 4.0 μM caffeine was achieved. With the four aptamer sensors forming an array, caffeine and the three analogues were well separated from nine other closely related molecules.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">J. Huang-etal-2022-Selection</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.1c04349</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://aclanthology.org/2022.GWF-1.57</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2022</date>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
