<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Wei-2022-Qualitative">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Qualitative property preservation of high-order operator splitting for the SIR model</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Siqi</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Wei</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Raymond</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">J</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Spiteri</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2022</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="bibutilsgt">journal article</genre>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Applied Numerical Mathematics, Volume 172</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
            <publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
        <genre authority="bibutilsgt">academic journal</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>The susceptible-infected-recovered (SIR) model is perhaps the most basic epidemiological model for the evolution of disease spread within a population. Because of its direct representation of fundamental physical quantities, a true solution to an SIR model possesses a number of qualitative properties, such as conservation of the total population or positivity or monotonicity of its constituent populations, that may only be guaranteed to hold numerically under step-size restrictions on the solver. Operator-splitting methods with order greater than two require backward sub-steps in each operator, and the effects of these backward sub-steps on the step-size restrictions for guarantees of qualitative correctness of numerical solutions are not well studied. In this study, we analyze the impact of backward steps on step-size restrictions for guaranteed qualitative properties by applying third- and fourth-order operator-splitting methods to the SIR epidemic model. We find that it is possible to provide step-size restrictions that guarantee qualitative property preservation of the numerical solution despite the negative sub-steps, but care must be taken in the choice of the method. Results such as this open the door for the design and application of high-order operator-splitting methods to other mathematical models in general for which qualitative property preservation is important.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Wei-2022-Qualitative</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1016/j.apnum.2021.10.003</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/G22-13001</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2022</date>
        <detail type="volume"><number>172</number></detail>
        <extent unit="page">
            <start>332</start>
            <end>350</end>
        </extent>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
