<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Huang-Liu-2022-A-DNA">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>A DNA Aptamer for Theophylline with Ultrahigh Selectivity Reminiscent of the Classic RNA Aptamer</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Po‐Jung</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">Jimmy</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Huang</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Juewen</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Liu</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2022</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="bibutilsgt">journal article</genre>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>ACS Chemical Biology, Volume 17, Issue 8</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
            <publisher>American Chemical Society (ACS)</publisher>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
        <genre authority="bibutilsgt">academic journal</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>Since the report of the RNA aptamer for theophylline, theophylline has become a key molecule in chemical biology for designing RNA switches and riboswitches. In addition, theophylline is an important drug for treating airway diseases including asthma. The classic RNA aptamer with excellent selectivity for theophylline has been used to design biosensors, although DNA aptamers are more desirable for stability and cost considerations. In this work, we selected DNA aptamers for theophylline, and all the top sequences shared the same binding motifs. Binding was confirmed using isothermal titration calorimetry and a nuclease digestion assay, showing a dissociation constant (Kd) around 0.5 μM theophylline. The Theo2201 aptamer can be truncated down to 23-mer while still has a Kd of 9.8 μM. The selectivity for theophylline over caffeine is around 250,000-fold based on a strand-displacement assay, which was more than 20-fold higher compared to the classic RNA aptamer. For other tested analogs, the DNA aptamer also showed better selectivity. Using the structure-switching aptamer sensor design method, a detection limit of 17 nM theophylline was achieved in the selection buffer, and a detection limit of 31 nM was obtained in 10% serum.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Huang-Liu-2022-A-DNA</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1021/acschembio.2c00179</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/G22-57001</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2022</date>
        <detail type="volume"><number>17</number></detail>
        <detail type="issue"><number>8</number></detail>
        <extent unit="page">
            <start>2121</start>
            <end>2129</end>
        </extent>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
