<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Macaskill-2022-Six">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Six decades of environmental resource valuation in Canada: A synthesis of the literature</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">James</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Macaskill</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Patrick</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Lloyd‐Smith</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2022</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="bibutilsgt">journal article</genre>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Canadian Journal of Agricultural Economics/Revue canadienne d’agroeconomie, Volume 70, Issue 1</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
            <publisher>Wiley</publisher>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
        <genre authority="bibutilsgt">academic journal</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>This paper synthesizes Canada’s environmental valuation literature over the last six decades. Focusing on primary valuation benefit estimates, we link multiple research outputs from the same data collection effort to obtain an accurate measure of unique studies. We identify a total of 269 unique valuation studies conducted in Canada between 1964 and 2019. The number of valuation studies conducted per year has not increased since 1975 and the median data collection year is 1996. Stated preference (SP) methods are the most popular valuation approaches being used in more than 50% of studies and this share has increased to over 80% within the last decade. We discuss numerous gaps in our knowledge for certain environmental resources and regions, in particular Canada’s three Northern territories. The paper provides information on the state of environmental valuation research in Canada and identifies future research needs.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Macaskill-2022-Six</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1111/cjag.12304</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/G22-15001</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2022</date>
        <detail type="volume"><number>70</number></detail>
        <detail type="issue"><number>1</number></detail>
        <extent unit="page">
            <start>73</start>
            <end>89</end>
        </extent>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
