<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Spence-2023-Disparities">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Disparities in economic values for nature-based activities in Canada</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Danielle</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">S</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Spence</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Corinne</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">J</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Schuster-Wallace</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Patrick</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Lloyd-Smith</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2023</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="bibutilsgt">journal article</genre>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Ecological Economics, Volume 205</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
            <publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
        <genre authority="bibutilsgt">academic journal</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>Differential impacts of policies or changes in environmental conditions on people is a growing area of interest to decision-makers, yet remains an often neglected area of study for the environmental valuation literature. Using data from a large national survey of over 24,000 people conducted in Canada, this paper implements a latent class Kuhn-Tucker recreation demand model to assess differences in preferences and values for nature-based activities. Preferences are disaggregated by self-reported Indigeneity, immigration status, and gender. We find that Indigenous people receive 63% greater benefits from participating in nature-based activities compared to non-Indigenous people living in Canada. Immigrants have the lowest participation in, and benefits associated with, nature-based activities. Similarly, women receive 21% lesser benefits associated with nature-based activities when compared to men. These results demonstrate that Indigenous peoples may be more vulnerable to adverse impacts on nature-based activities such as land-use changes, climate change, and government policies. The study also highlights the importance of disaggregated data and incorporating aspects of identity in the ecosystem service literature towards more equitable decision-making and reconciliation.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Spence-2023-Disparities</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2022.107724</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/G23-74001</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2023</date>
        <detail type="volume"><number>205</number></detail>
        <detail type="page"><number>107724</number></detail>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
