<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Shatilla-2023-Multi‐year">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Multi‐year high‐frequency sampling provides new runoff and biogeochemical insights in a discontinuous permafrost watershed</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Nadine</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">J</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Shatilla</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Weigang</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Tang</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Sean</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">K</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Carey</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2023</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="bibutilsgt">journal article</genre>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Hydrological Processes, Volume 37, Issue 5</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
            <publisher>Wiley</publisher>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
        <genre authority="bibutilsgt">academic journal</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>Abstract Permafrost‐underlain watersheds in the subarctic are sensitive to warming as small changes in ground thermal status will alter all components of the hydrological cycle. Globally, observed increases in winter flows and shifting water chemistry have most often been ascribed to permafrost thaw and deepening runoff pathways. However, there remain few studies in headwater catchments that examine coupled flow‐chemistry relations at high frequency over multiple years and seasons to evaluate the implications of environmental change. In this study, we use multi‐year high‐frequency measurement of discharge, specific conductance (SpC) and chromophoric dissolved organic matter (CDOM) along with traditional grab sampling of major ions to understand the sources and pathways of water and evaluate how distinct solutes are mobilized in a well‐studied subarctic basin in Yukon, Canada. Seasonally, the catchment exhibited considerable hysteresis in flow‐solute relations and had both chemostatic and dilution SpC–Q patterns with respect to major ions depending upon season and mobilization CDOM–Q signals. Storm events were extracted from high‐frequency data and normalized C–Q indices were determined and related to flow, catchment and meteorological variables. CDOM–Q events predominantly had an anti‐clockwise hysteresis and increases in DOC concentrations during storms, with some exception in the spring and fall. Conversely, SpC–Q events exhibited clockwise hysteresis and a dilution behaviour during events with less seasonal or inter‐annual variability. Information from this study supports previous conceptual models of thermally regulated runoff generation in a layered soil profile, yet also points to the importance of lateral connectivity and distal sources of solutes.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Shatilla-2023-Multi‐year</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1002/hyp.14898</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/G23-32001</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2023</date>
        <detail type="volume"><number>37</number></detail>
        <detail type="issue"><number>5</number></detail>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
