<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<modsCollection xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods ID="Moalemi-2024-Assessing">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Assessing Ice Break-Up Trends in Slave River Delta through Satellite Observations and Random Forest Modeling</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Ida</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Moalemi</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">Homa</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">Kheyrollah</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Pour</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
        <namePart type="given">K</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">Andrea</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">Scott</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="text">author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2024</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="bibutilsgt">journal article</genre>
    <relatedItem type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Remote Sensing, Volume 16, Issue 12</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
            <publisher>MDPI AG</publisher>
        </originInfo>
        <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
        <genre authority="bibutilsgt">academic journal</genre>
    </relatedItem>
    <abstract>The seasonal temperature trends and ice phenology in the Great Slave Lake (GSL) are significantly influenced by inflow from the Slave River. The river undergoes a sequence of mechanical break-ups all the way to the GSL, initiating the GSL break-up process. Additionally, upstream water management practices impact the discharge of the Slave River and, consequently, the ice break-up of the GSL. Therefore, monitoring the break-up process at the Slave River Delta (SRD), where the river meets the lake, is crucial for understanding the cascading effects of upstream activities on GSL ice break-up. This research aimed to use Random Forest (RF) models to monitor the ice break-up processes at the SRD using a combination of satellite images with relatively high spatial resolution, including Landsat-5, Landsat-8, Sentinel-2a, and Sentinel-2b. The RF models were trained using selected training pixels to classify ice, open water, and cloud. The onset of break-up was determined by data-driven thresholds on the ice fraction in images with less than 20% cloud coverage. Analysis of break-up timing from 1984 to 2023 revealed a significant earlier trend using the Mann–Kendall test with a p-value of 0.05. Furthermore, break-up data in recent years show a high degree of variability in the break-up rate using images in recent years with better temporal resolution.</abstract>
    <identifier type="citekey">Moalemi-2024-Assessing</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.3390/rs16122244</identifier>
    <location>
        <url>https://gwf-uwaterloo.github.io/gwf-publications/G24-15001</url>
    </location>
    <part>
        <date>2024</date>
        <detail type="volume"><number>16</number></detail>
        <detail type="issue"><number>12</number></detail>
        <detail type="page"><number>2244</number></detail>
    </part>
</mods>
</modsCollection>
